<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Youths instruction. Composed and written by William Martyn Esquire. Recorder of the honourable citie of Exeter</title>
            <author>Martyn, William, 1562-1617.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1612</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 219 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 71 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07129</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17530</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102312</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838101</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838101</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2460</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07129)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2460)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1074:01)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Youths instruction. Composed and written by William Martyn Esquire. Recorder of the honourable citie of Exeter</title>
                  <author>Martyn, William, 1562-1617.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 109, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Beale,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1612.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With an index.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Conduct of life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Education --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2460:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2460:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2460:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2460:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Youths Jnſtruction.</p>
            <p>COMPOSED AND WRITTEN by WILLIAM MARTYN <hi>Eſquire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Recorder of the honourable Citie of EXETER.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Praestat non naſci;</l>
               <l>Quam malé viuere.</l>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>Iohn Beale.</hi> 1612.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:2460:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To my deerely honoured Father in law WILLIAM MARTYN</hi> Eſquire.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>IF it be true, that <hi>Oppoſites together</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Being compar'd, ſeeme cleerer each by other:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Then my defects (comming from true affection)</l>
               <l>Shall not detract, but adde to your perfection.</l>
               <l>T'were to gild gold, your labors to commend;</l>
               <l>Few men can equall them, none reprehend:</l>
               <l>Yet ſome (no doubt) will caſt an enuious glance,</l>
               <l>For <hi>Art hath one ſworne Foe, call'd Ignorance.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>P. B.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:2460:3"/>
            <head>TO MY SONNE NICHOLAS MARTYN, NOVV A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>STVDENT IN THE VNIVERSITIE OF OXFORD.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S none but a faithfull friend, can perfectlie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue of thoſe requiſites, which truly belong vnto his friend: So none but a Father, can rightlie coniecture of that ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſing loue, which a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther beareth to his owne child.</p>
            <p>This loue of mine (my Sonne,) hath made me ouer-bold with mine owne buſineſſe, and with mine owne conuenient pleaſures; in borrowing
<pb facs="tcp:2460:4"/>ſome houres (which were indeede owing to my publike imployments and to my neceſſarie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creation) to compoſe, and to write this enſuing Diſcourſe; not to pleaſe my ſelfe, (if it were praiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthie) but to doe you good: and (by ſuch Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues, and by ſuch Inſtructions, as are therein com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed) to enrich your vnderſtanding and behaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, with thoſe ſelected virtues, and moſt commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded qualities, whoſe diſcourſe it doth containe.</p>
            <p>For like as the faireſt building, wanteth her chiefeſt beautie, except it bee exactlie flouriſhed, and bountifullie furniſhed within: ſo the outward lineaments of the bodie, are depriued of their choiſeſt, and of their chiefeſt luſter, if the inward parts and mind bee not adorned, with ſuch ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent virtues, and with ſuch Gentleman-like qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, as doe make a man to bee compleat, and conſequentlie, a profitable member in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-weale.</p>
            <p>J ſay, a profitable member in the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weale; becauſe it ſufficeth not, that a man doth know much, and can doe well, by meanes of that knowledge; except he alſo doe produce into action, ſuch effects as his virtues and his knowledge haue
<pb facs="tcp:2460:4"/>enabled him to performe. For, otherwiſe, ſuch a man may fitlie be compared, to a rare and perfect Diamond, which beeing vnpolliſhed, ſerueth for no vſe. Or to a faire Ship, loaden with Silkes, with Spices, and with Gold, beeing ſwallowed vp into the Seas mawe, whereby it is made of no value or eſteeme. For a recompence therefore, of theſe my labours, and in thankefulneſſe, for my loue towards you, I wiſh and doe aduiſe you, to imploy ſome times, not onely to reade this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe often, but alſo with diligence to meditate, and publikelie to exerciſe thoſe virtues, and thoſe qualities, which heerein are deſeruedlie praiſed, and commended.</p>
            <p>Eſpecially and aboue the reſt, thoſe two, which cannot too much bee applauded: I meane Religion, and honeſtie of life: which (as good Salt) will ſeaſon, whatſoeuer you take in hand: And will (as the South and the North Pole Starres) direct your courſe aright, whereſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer you chance to ſaile, in the troubleſome Ocean of this your worldly and tranſitorie pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimage: So ſhall your life bee profitable vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to others, and pleaſing to your quiet conſcience:
<pb facs="tcp:2460:5"/>And ſo ſhall your death bee crowned with me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rited praiſe and commendation; and both your life, and your death ſhall bee precious in the ſight of God: <hi>Who will reward euerie man according to his workes, be they good or euill.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your louing Father</hi>
William Martyn.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:2460:5"/>
            <head>YOVTHS INSTRVCTION: WHEREIN ARE BRIEFLY SET FORTH ALL NECESSARY Rules, for the ordering of a <hi>mans whole life.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y Sonne, ſeeing it hath pleaſed the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, to make you (who by creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on are his owne) by generation to be mine, I hold it to be a principall part of my duty vnto God, and of my loue towards you, both by Religion, and alſo by education in vertue, ſo to direct you, that you may euer continue to be his.</p>
            <p>For he hath not placed you on the Theater of this world, that (like to a fooliſh actor) you ſhould fulfill the luſts thereof; nor to embrace theſe earthly vanities, as chaynes of pearle, and of gold, do mens necks, which make them proude: but becauſe you ſhould duly ſerue him, in true obedience, and by your beſt endeuours ſet foorth his glory.</p>
            <p>Beaſts, Birds, and Fiſhes,
<note place="margin">Man muſt ſerue God.</note> are (together with men) the workmanſhip of one, and of the ſame diuine Maieſty, and power: but the end, for which they were by him made, is not one and the ſame. For thoſe vnreaſonable creatures were faſhioned to ſerue man; but man him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to ſerue God.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:2460:6"/>
            <p>So pleaſing was this ſeruice vnto <hi>Dauid,</hi> the kingly Prophet,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 84.10.</note> and the annointed of the Lord; that he affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med (with a moſt conſtant reſolution) that it was better to be a dorekeeper in the houſe of his God, then to dwell in the Tabernacles of the wicked.</p>
            <p>If <hi>Iacob</hi> for a double terme ſerued his vncle <hi>Laban,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 29.28.</note> that thereby he might obtaine <hi>Rahel</hi> for his wife (who being enioyed but a ſeaſon, ſhortly after died,) how much more ought you to dedicate your ſelfe to the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of God all the daies of your life? that at the length you may thereby attaine to thoſe heauenly bleſſings, which in goodneſſe, are ineſtimable, and in number endleſſe.
<note place="margin">1. Reg. cap. 10</note> You may reade in Holy writ, that the Queene of <hi>Sheba</hi> ſaid vnto <hi>Salomon</hi> (when ſhe had heard him, and had ſeene the greatneſſe of his honor, and of his riches, and of his ſtrength, and had viewed his Court, and conſidered the rareneſſe of his gouernment) hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py are thy men, and happy are theſe thy ſeruants, which ſtand euer before thee, and heare thy wiſedome: but much more truly may we conclude, that they are (indeed) bleſſed, who ſtand before, and do ſerue, not <hi>Salomon</hi> but their God.</p>
            <p>The ſeruice which is to be performed to the Kings, and Princes of the world, cannot be freed from ſerui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, and ſubiection, but that ſeruice, which is by vs due vnto God, is liberty it ſelfe; and no man is ſo free, as he, who ſincerely ſerueth him.</p>
            <p>There are but two maſters (God and the diuell) whom men can ſerue: and who ſo adhereth to one of them, is an enemy to the other.</p>
            <p>The diuell wageth warre againſt God, and againſt his choſen children: and (becauſe he is faithleſſe) he
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:2460:6"/>truſteth none: but being the muſter-maſter of his owne army) he preſſeth foorth all ſuch for his ſeruice, as are not ſouldiers vnder Gods banner. And hauing leuied huge troupes, and infinite numbers of deſperate, and forlorne people, he marcheth into the field of this world, and (ſtriuing in vaine to obtaine a victory, which no poſſibility can afford him) like to the practiſe of the Turkiſh Emperor, he maketh hauocke of his followers, and (by multitudes) mercileſly he deſtroyeth them: whereas (on the contrary part) God ſo gratiouſly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecteth, and defendeth his elected, that not one of them can periſh, or come to an vntimely end.</p>
            <p>Seeing then, that God is ſo powerfull, that he can, and ſo carefull, that he will, and doth preſerue all ſuch, as vnfainedly doe ſerue him,
<note place="margin">2. Reg. cap. 5.</note> you muſt not (as <hi>Naaman</hi> the Aſſyrian did) content your ſelfe in part to ſerue God, and in part to ſerue an earthly maſter, or a mortall king: but following the good example of <hi>Dauids</hi> wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thies, and of <hi>Gedeons</hi> three hundred valiant men of war,
<note place="margin">1. Chron. cap. 11. Iudg. 7.3.</note> you muſt neglect your owne ſafety, nay your life, and engage your ſelfe wholly to do him ſeruice.</p>
            <p>So did <hi>Moſes,</hi> when with ten grieuous plagues he corrected the hard hart of <hi>Pharaoh</hi> King of Egypt, who would not ſuffer the children of Iſraell to depart out of his land. So did <hi>Sadrach, Miſhael,</hi> and <hi>Abednago,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 3.</note> who (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſeruants of the great God of heauen) made choiſe rather to be throwne into a burning furnace, then to worſhip the golden Image, which <hi>Nebuchadne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zar</hi> (the great king of <hi>Babel</hi>) had ſet vp.</p>
            <p>And ſo did <hi>Daniel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 6.</note> who refuſed not to be caſt into the Lyons denne, rather then by prayer and worſhipping he would yeeld vnto <hi>Darius</hi> that ſeruice and that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:2460:7"/>nor which he owed only to the Lord his God.</p>
            <p>As you may obſerue, that when plants and trees, by ſtormes and by tempeſts, are robbed of their leaues, ſuch canckers are then diſcouered, as do blemiſh the comelineſſe of their beauty: ſo you may plainly ſee, that when men are exiled from Gods ſeruice, through the peruerſenes of their owne natures, their wickednes is ſpread abroad, to their ſhame; and is made an obiect to the eies of them, who (being more vertuous) doe loath their ſinne.</p>
            <p>You ſee then (my Sonne) how behoofefull it is for you to ſerue God; that by meanes thereof, you may be truly happy, and enioy that liberty, and that freedome, which is incident vnto none, but to ſuch only, as do vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fainedly ſerue him.</p>
            <p>It is therefore very requiſite,
<note place="margin">Man muſt feare God.</note> and fit that you be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully inſtructed, concerning the performance, and exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of this duty, which muſt be by a reuerent feare of his deity, and power, according to the direction of King <hi>Dauid,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 2.11.</note> who exhorteth all men to ſerue the Lord in feare, not in ſuch a timerous feare, as is abaſed by ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uility,
<note place="margin">Iob. 28.28. Prou. 1.7. Prou. 9.10. Prou. 15.33. Pſal 111.10. Pſal 25.9.</note> and bondage: but in ſuch a feare, as is mingled, and impalled with loue: This filiall, and louely feare, is the beginning of wiſedome, and of knowledge: and as (<hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith) the ſecret of the Lord is reuealed to them that feare him, and his couenant to giue them vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding.</p>
            <p>It is a welſpring of life,
<note place="margin">Prou. 14.27. Prou. 19.23. Prou. 16.6.</note> to auoide the ſnares of death: it leadeth vnto life; and he that is filled therewith, ſhall continue; and not be viſited with euill. It maketh his heart (by imputation, and by grace) cleane, and pure in the ſight of God;
<note place="margin">Pſal. 19.9.</note> 
               <hi>Bleſſed is the man</hi> (ſaith the Pſalmiſt)
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:2460:7"/>
               <hi>that feareth the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 112.1.2. Pſal. 128. Pſal. 115.13. Pſal. 147.11. Luk 1.50.</note> his ſeede ſhall be mighty vpon the earth: The Lord will bleſſe all ſuch as feare him: both ſmall, and great, his delight is in them that do feare him: And his mercy ſhall be vpon them, from generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to generation. The reward of humility,
<note place="margin">Prou. 22.4.</note> and of the feare of the Lord (as <hi>Salomon</hi> doth teſtifie) is riches,
<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 12.13.</note> and glory, and life: And in fearing of him, and in keeping of his commandements, doth conſiſt the whole duety of man. The Lyons do lacke, and ſuffer hunger, but ſuch as do feare the Lord ſhall want nothing that is good.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 34.10.</note> Such was the louely feare,
<note place="margin">Gen. 22.12.</note> that <hi>Abraham</hi> expreſſed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his God; that (being ſo commanded by him) he would haue ſacrificed <hi>Iſaac</hi> his only ſonne, whoſe ſeede (by Gods promiſe) was to be multiplied as the ſtarres in heauen, and as the ſands on the ſea ſhore,
<note place="margin">Gen. 26.4.24.</note> which are innumerable: And ſuch was the louely feare, which <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph</hi> expreſſed towards his God,
<note place="margin">Gen. 39.</note> that he rather choſe to be maligned, and reproched, by means of the vntrue, and falſe accuſements of his Miſtreſſe, and to be caſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to priſon, then he would be diſloiall, and vnfaithfull vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Putiphar</hi> his maſter. And ſuch was the louely feare,
<note place="margin">2. Sam. 66.</note> and reuerence, which <hi>Dauid</hi> expreſſed before his God, that he ceaſed not (for the ioy of his ſpirit) to dance before the Arke of Couenant, though for ſo doing, he were derided, ſkorned, and mocked by <hi>Michal</hi> his owne wife.</p>
            <p>And ſuch (my Sonne) muſt be your daily care, and conſtant reſolution, that you feare nothing which may terrifie you from the feare of God,
<note place="margin">Repetition.</note> becauſe it maketh her followers to bee wiſe; it gaineth long life; it bani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth euill; nay death it ſelfe: it cleanſeth the heart; it maketh men bleſſed, both in themſelues, &amp; alſo in their
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:2460:8"/>poſterities: it cauſeth the Lord to delight in them, and to enrich them; to multiply his mercies on them, and in the end to crowne them with immortality, and with glory.</p>
            <p>Now,
<note place="margin">Man muſt loath ſinne.</note> as theſe, and many others are the fruits, which the feare of God produceth and bringeth forth: ſo will it augment in you a loathing deteſtation, and a religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous hating of ſinne.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Firſt, in reſpect of God; becauſe hee is altogether righteous and pure, and none euill can dwell with him.</p>
            <p n="2">2 In reſpect of our ſelues; becauſe the guiltineſſe thereof maketh a ſeparation, &amp; pronounceth a diuorce betweene God and man.</p>
            <p n="3">3 And thirdly, in reſpect of ſinne it ſelfe, which is a moſt vgly monſter, proceeding from the diuell, for the finall and perpetuall deſtruction of all ſuch, as impiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and wickedly doe liue and die therein.</p>
            <p>As the grim looke of a ſterne Lion will make you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pierij Apho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſmi Hiero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glyphici.</hi> 19.</note> though he come not neere vnto you: ſo the view and ſight of ſinne muſt breed in you a loathing deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of her vgly fowlneſſe, though ſhe want power and ability to take hold of you to doe you any harme. And you muſt flie from the alluring enchantments and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocations of ſinne: as the Elephant (with all expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) betaketh himſelfe to his legges, as ſoone as he hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the grunting of a filthy ſwine.</p>
            <p>A fooliſh man delighteth in a ſinfull life, becauſe his outward ſenſes are pleaſed with the vanity, and with the varietie of his ſinnes: but he that is wiſe, abhorreth ſin, becauſe the fruits thereof are euill. Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith, that <hi>ſinners are ſeruants:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn 8.34. 1 Iohn 38.</note> and <hi>S. Paul</hi> telleth vs, that they <hi>are captiues;</hi> nay they are (indeed) <hi>the children of the diuell.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:2460:8"/>
            <p>It entreth into a man, as a Conqueror taketh poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of his vanquiſhed Kingdom; where he will not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of a part, but will bee Lord and Maſter of the whole.</p>
            <p>It is compared to a wedge; for as a wedge at the firſt maketh but a little hole; but beeing further driuen, it renteth, and teareth the whole wood in ſunder: ſo ſin, at his firſt entrance into the heart of a man, ſeemeth to hurt him but a little; but proceeding further by fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentaction, it begetteth in him an ardent deſire (by cuſtom) to enlarge it ſelfe, and ſo maketh him the bond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlaue of Sathan.</p>
            <p>For as the little fiſh called <hi>Remora</hi> (by ſticking faſt vnto a Shippe) ſtayeth her from ſayling towards the Port where ſhee ſhould bee:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pierij Apho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſmi Hiero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glyphici.</hi> 192.</note> ſo euery ſinne (bee it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo ſmall) will detaine and hold you backe from thoſe religious and vertuous courſes, wherein (other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe) you would or ſhould walke, to Gods glorie, and the ſaluation of your owne Soule.</p>
            <p>Philoſophers do affirme, that nothing is more feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full then Feare it ſelfe. And Diuines do teach truly, that there is not any thing more ſinnefull then ſinne it ſelfe. I haue read of a kind of Serpent, which is ſo venimous; that by ſtinging the foot of a Horſe onely, hee killeth the Horſe, and the rider alſo. Such a Serpent is ſinne, which no ſooner ſtingeth the body, but foorthwith it deſtroieth it, and the ſoule too: it is ſo peſtilent a diſeaſe, that it corrupteth the whole minde of him whom it poſſeſſeth, and driueth out of him all godly motions. As water (beeing powred into a veſſell) doth expell the Ayre: and as the children of Iſrael did the heathen Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions out of the Countries and Prouinces of the land
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:2460:9"/>of <hi>Canaan:</hi> it ſuddenly bereaueth a man of all his former practiſed vertues, as a little Axe (by few ſtrokes) cutteth downe; or as a whirlewind (with one furious blaſt) o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerturneth, the greateſt and the talleſt trees, which for many yeers haue bin growing to their perfect ſtrength and greatneſſe.</p>
            <p>In the winter, when the warme heat of the Sunne forſaketh vs, the earth is benummed with cold, with froſts, with ſnowes, and with vnpleaſing weather. And in like ſort, when Gods grace departeth from a ſinner, his ſoule is hardned with many vices, and robbed of all virtue: yea, ſuch is the bewitching nature, and quality of ſinne, that the more it plungeth men in the gulfes of their tranſgreſſions, the more pleaſure, and the greater delight they take therein. Like vnto mad men who are vnmeaſurably delighted with the ſight and gingling of thoſe chaynes, wherewith they are fettered and tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
            <p>It is true,
<note place="margin">Plato.</note> that no man liueth, and ſinneth not, and it is as true that <hi>Plato</hi> ſaid, <hi>It is better not to liue, then to liue wickedly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As there is no thorne without his prickles; ſo there is no man, that is vtterly deſtitute of ſinne. Yet muſt you ſtriue (my ſonne) with all your might, and with all your ſtrength, yea with your vttermoſt endeauours, to ſhake it off, becauſe the reward thereof is death: and the longer it is retained, the more hardly it is remoued: for like as a ſmall riuer, by running farre, is fellowſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped with many other ſtreams, which at length do make him great. So ſmall offences by long continuance, are augmented by greater faults which do concurre.
<note place="margin">Heming de Magiſtratu.</note> It is impoſſible to be a man, and not to ſinne; yet you muſt
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:2460:9"/>auoid ſinne, as fire, becauſe it burneth: as water, becauſe it drowneth: as a plague, becauſe it infecteth: Nay, as death it ſelfe, becauſe it mortally killeth:
<q>
                  <l>Principijs obſta, ſerò medicina paratur:</l>
                  <l>Cum mala per longas conualuére moras.</l>
               </q> Therefore before ſinne haue gotten in you the vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per hand, you muſt frame your ſelfe to be like vnto a ſhip, cloſe below, to reſiſt, and to keepe out the tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and the allurements of worldly vanities. And open aboue, whereby you may be capable of the grace, and mercy, and fauour of Almighty God: who (though he deteſt ſinne) yet in his infinite mercy, he imbraceth a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> repentant ſinner: as a kind mother lulleth her ſicke hild louingly in her armes, though ſhe repine at the diſeaſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Valerius</hi> writeth of one, who had the fit of an ague vpon him, when he was borne,
<note place="margin">Valerius.</note> which neuer left him for many yeeres vntill he died. Such an ague is ſinne, which (by naturall propagation, being deriued to vs from our firſt parents <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eue:</hi> by reaſon of their tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in eating of the forbidden fruit, contrary to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe commandement of Almighty God) neuer lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth, neuer forſaketh vs, vntill by death we be depriued of this mortall life.</p>
            <p>Yet muſt you not (by ſinning) foſter in your ſelfe, a longing deſire to ſinne more, like vnto ſuch as being drunken with wine, do vnmeaſurably couet to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies drinking. But contrariwiſe, you muſt be carefull that ſinne raigne not, that ſinne haue not dominion in your earthly members. <hi>Nam quot habemus vitia, tot ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bemus Dominos.</hi> A little rope ſufficeth to hang a great theefe: a little droſſe to abaſe much gold: a little poyſon to infect much wholſome liquor; a little hereſie to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:2460:10"/>good doctrine: and ſo do the ſmalleſt ſinnes (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Gods mercy) to damme your ſoule. The harts of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full men, may fitly be compared vnto ſnailes houſes, for as they haue no vacant places, to ſtore vp prouiſion enough for the neceſſary ſuſtentation of their liues, no more haue thoſe harts any roomes at all, to entertaine any vertuous, or godly motions, which would be profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table for the ſaluation of their ſoules.</p>
            <p>Euery ſinner (as much as in him lieth) is naturally an enemy vnto God: and with the ancient gyants conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, to caſt rockes, and ſtones againſt <hi>Iuptter,</hi> he ſaith in his heart,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 14.1.</note> there is no God and that his wickednes ſhall neuer be reuealed,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 2.4.</note> nor rewarded: But he that ſitteth in heauen ſhall laugh him to ſkorne: the Lord will haue him in deriſion.</p>
            <p>As a man that is ſuddenly taken out of a darke priſon, cannot (without much paine) behold the bright ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the cleere ſunne: no more can that man (which for a long ſeaſon hath bin enthralled in the darke dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon of iniquity and of ſinne) behold the faire beames of godlineſſe, and of vertue: but he rather delighteth to wallow in the beaſtly and lothſome puddle of his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer foule tranſgreſſions: as the ſwine doth in the mire, wherewith ſhe is polluted, and defiled.</p>
            <p>Some men there are who (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t the laſt caſt) doe ceaſe from perpetrating of ſuch groſſe and enormious ſinnes as in former times they haue committed.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lipſius</hi> 115.</note> 1. Either be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they want ability to maintaine them: 2. Or power to performe them: 3. or for the ſhame, or for the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which they feare, and do deſerue.</p>
            <p>But he that is vertuous, and he that is religious, dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth, and abhorreth ſinne, as a ghaſtly monſter, becauſe
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:2460:10"/>he feareth and loueth God.</p>
            <p>The ſmalleſt ſinnes do pricke,
<note place="margin">Conſcience.</note> but great ones doe wound the conſciences of men, and a feared, and terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied conſcience by reaſon of her ſinne, is the worme that neuer dieth.</p>
            <p>As a dogge, which ſecretly hath killed a ſheepe, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not with a ſetled eie, behold his maſters face, becauſe he is guilty to himſelfe of his foule fault: ſo a man (whoſe conſcience doth accuſe him of ſome hainous ſinne to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God) cannot behold the face of his creator: but by his bluſhing he will bewray his owne ſinne. A ſinfull conſcience (as <hi>Iuſtine Martyr</hi> doth affirme) is a ready witneſſe to accuſe, a ſeuere iudge to condemne, and a mercileſſe hangman to execute him that hath ſinned: and broken the commandements of his God. A guilty conſcience is firſt perplexed with feare, and terror: and is then from feare tranſported into fury: and laſt of all, it is tormented with deſpaire.</p>
            <p>A fierce and a cruell beaſt, whilſt he ſleepeth, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to be very mild and gentle: but being awaked, he ruſheth with a ſauage violence vpon the man which troubled him: and leaueth him not, vntill he haue torn him into many peeces. And ſo a guilty conſcience ſlee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping on the bed of deepe ſecurity, and careleſneſſe, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to enioy a continuall feaſt of happineſſe, and of peace: but being by God informed of the guiltineſſe of her ſinne, and being ſtartled out of her drowſie ſleepe, ſhe awaketh, and with continuall anguiſh, paines intol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable, and with perpetuall torments ſhe laſheth, and whippeth the body, in which ſhe dwelleth,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Oth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Caſman.</hi> 140. Solinus. Pliny.</note> and ceaſeth not to afflict it grieuouſly, vntill ſhe haue murdred it with perpetuall death. <hi>Solinus</hi> and <hi>Pliny</hi> do report, that
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:2460:11"/>
               <hi>when by too much rauening, and ill digeſtion, the belly of the Crocodile is filled vp, and diſtempered with many wormes ſhe laieth her mouth open vnto certaine birds, which liue vpon the riuer of Nilus in the country of Egypt,) who (entring into her throat) doe eat them, and deuour them, by meanes where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ſhe is reſtored to her former health.</hi> But the worme of an euill conſcience, is not ſo conſumed, there are no birds that can eaſe her of that paine.</p>
            <p>My ſonne, to conclude this point, let it be your chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt Study, and your daily practiſe: Firſt of all to ſerue God, then to feare him, and (in fearing of him) to abhor ſinne, as the greateſt enemy to vertue, and the death of your immortall ſoule.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quae iuuenibus arrident voluptates, eaſdem irrident ſenes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſinnes of youth are pleaſing for a while, but old age (waxing wiſe) abhorreth them as the ſoules poiſon. <hi>Caelum ſi vis pede calcare, vitium mente calca.</hi> And if you muſt needs behold ſinnes in other men, yet looke on them as ſailers do on rockes, not to come neere them, but to auoid them. And if (of force) you muſt behold ſinne in your ſelfe, then looke on it, <hi>as Iob did on his ſoares with a wofull eie:
<note place="margin">Iob. 2.8. Iob. 16.16. Math. 26.75. Mark. 14.72. Luk. 22.62.</note> Or as Peter did on Chriſt his maſter when he denied him and wept bitterly.</hi> Now, that you may be the better enabled to ſerue God, in feare, and to hate ſinne, which trecherouſly ſlaieth the ſoule, whilſt flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringly it ſmileth on her, as <hi>Ioab</hi> did on <hi>Amaſa,</hi> and as <hi>Iudas</hi> betraied his Lord and Maſter,
<note place="margin">2. Sam. 20 9. Math. 26.48.</note> when he kiſſed him.</p>
            <p>You muſt (with a true heart) embrace,
<note place="margin">RELIGION</note> and vnfai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedly loue religion, which will rectifie your conſcience towards God: and teacheth you to magnifie him with
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:2460:11"/>an holy worſhip, according to the rules and directions of his word: and to delight in vertue, as in your choiſeſt loue, and to loath vice, as the blackneſſe of an Ethio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pian, which no waſhing can make white, which wil con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme your obedience to your King and ſoueraigne, and to your other ſuperiors, and make you a worthy mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber in a floriſhing, and in a happy common weale. And will order your manners, generally towards all men, &amp; your ciuill behauior more particularly towards thoſe with whom you do mutually conuerſe. For as <hi>Lactan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> writeth, and <hi>Lipſius</hi> from him doth report,
<note place="margin">Lactantius.</note> 
               <hi>ſola Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gioeſt, quae hominum inter ſe cuſtodit ſocietatem,</hi> It is reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion only, that maintaineth, and preſerueth ſociety among men. And in another place, he ſaith, <hi>Tolle Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem, &amp; vita humana, Stultitia, &amp; Immunitate eſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleta:</hi> If religion clenſe not the heart, mans life will be fully fraughted with cruelty and with folly.</p>
            <p>Where religion wanteth, there the chiefeſt atchieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of men are obſcured, as the ſinner is, when his face is vailed, and masked with a cloud. Fiſhes muſt needs die, if the riuers be dried vp, and ſo muſt the thoughts of men periſh, when they are not watered, with the dew, and refreſhed with the comfortable ſtreames of a religious mind, and conuerſation. As <hi>Sauls</hi> honor was the more eminent, becauſe in ſtature he was taller then all the reſidue of his people: ſo no man (among wiſe men) is more reſpected then he, who fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth himſelfe to be more religious then the reſt. <hi>Cultus omnis eſt in cultus, ſine cultu Dei.</hi> A fit garment is eaſily ſhaped to ſerue a comly body, but hardly are deformed members couered by the taylors skill: ſo a man that is religious in all his waies, may (without difficulty or
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:2460:12"/>doubt) be the obiect of his owne praiſe, and commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation. But if he be irreligious, then no famous act can free him from in famy, and from ſhame. A ſpent candle (looſing her flame) leaueth nought behind but a ſtink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſnuffe, neither doth a man (when he dieth) leaue any thing behind him, but ignominy, and ſhame, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach: if (whilſt he liued) he beautifie not himſelfe with a religious life.</p>
            <p>The reuerent reſpect,
<note place="margin">Heathens in their kinds were religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.</note> and great regard to religion, which (from the beginning) all nations, and all people (though not illuminated with the true knowledge of the true God) haue had, being by the only inſtinct of nature inſtructed, that there was a diuine power, infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite, and ſupreme, which both created the world, and all things that were, and which are therein. And which alſo ruled, and preſerued them, by a ſingular wiſedome, and in a wonderfull order, and faſhion made ſome of them (in their blind zeale, and ſuperſtitious ignorance) to worſhip ſuch, and ſuch things as were no Gods.</p>
            <p>Hence it was,
<note place="margin">Idolatry.</note> that ſome of them adored <hi>Iupiter, Mars, Saturne, Mercury,</hi> and ſuch like poetically fained Gods. And that ſome others of them worſhipped the ſunne, the moone, the ſtarres, and other celeſtiall bodies, which were created only for the vſe of man. That ſome of them haue ſacrificed their deuotions to the works of mens-hands:
<note place="margin">Act. 19.</note> 
               <hi>As the Epheſians did to the Image of Diana, and as the children of Iſrael (in the wilderneſſe) did to the golden Calfe.
<note place="margin">Exod. 32. Dan. 3. 2. Reg. 5.18. 1. Sam. 5.</note> And as Nebuchadnezzars people did to the gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den ſtatue, which he had erected, and ſet vp, and as the king of Aram, and his ſubiects aid to the idoll Rymmon; And as the Philiſtins did vnto Dagon,
<note place="margin">Hiſtoria.</note> and as the</hi> Medes and Perſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans (vnder <hi>Cyrus</hi> their king) did to the image of <hi>Bel</hi> and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:2460:12"/>of the Dragon. And hence it is,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 135.</note> that the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> with a bitter taunt, reproueth and reprehendeth their groſſe, and abhominable follies, when he ſaith, <hi>the idols of the heathen, are ſiluer, and gold, euen the works of mens hands, they haue a mouth, and ſpeake not, they haue eares, and heare not; Neither is there any breath in their mouth: they that make them, are like vnto them, and ſo are all they that truſt in them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But contrariwiſe (my ſonne) true religion being foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vpon the truth of Gods word,
<note place="margin">Religion.</note> will direct you with vnderſtanding, and with knowledge, religiouſly and without ſuperſtitious blindneſſe, to adore, and to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip the true and the liuing God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cyrus</hi> an heathen King, (but in his kind and faſhion zealous and religious) was wont to ſay, that if ſubiects did religiouſly feare, and honor their Gods, they would not then commit abhominable ſinnes againſt them: nor hainous offences againſt their kings. And <hi>Cicero</hi> doth report, that the Romans conquered more nations and ſubdued more people, and prouinces, by the reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent obſeruances of their religious exerciſes, then they did by policy, and by the ſword.</p>
            <p>Where religion wanteth, there no chriſtian duety is performed for conſcience ſake: for religion is the beſt informer of the conſciences of men: where religion is not imbraced, the gouernment of kingdomes, and of common weales, are either neglected, or ſubuerted; like as a ſhip, vnder her ſailes in a tempeſtuous ſea, (wanting a cunning pilot to direct her) is ſuddenly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſhed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the rockes to her vtter ruine and confuſion.</p>
            <p>For like as bones do ſupport the fleſh of a mans bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and walles the building of an houſe, ſo doth religion
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:2460:13"/>the being, and the welbeing of euery ſtate, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon weale. And as the moone hath the greater light, when ſhe approacheth neereſt in oppoſition to the ſunne; ſo euery mans vertues are the more ſplendent, and the more eminent, by how much the neerer they are knit, and ioyned to religion. Nothing than religion is more excellent among men, neither doth any thing in this world make vs neerer to approach vnto God himſelfe. It is therefore to be ſought with your labor, to be bought with your chiefeſt treaſure, and to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected and defended with your deereſt bloud.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Without it no noble act muſt be attempted, and with it, no ſubtle or crafty plot or practiſe may be taken in hand.</p>
               <p>For ſuch things as by religion are warranted to be vertuous, to be profitable, to be good, are (without it) neither vertuous, nor profitable, nor good.</p>
            </q>
            <p>The chiefeſt vertue which a man poſſeſſeth in this life, is true religion, which mollifieth the hard, and the ſtony heart of man, and maketh him capable of Gods grace: As the Sunne, or Fire doth the hard wax, making it apt, and fit to receiue any impreſſion, that ſhall be made vpon it.</p>
            <p>Religion maketh a man warily, and carefully to looke vnto his waies, and wiſely to gouerne, and to rule him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. It maketh perſecutions to be tollerable, that we deſpaire not. And it moderateth our proſperity, that by meanes thereof, we do not wax inſolent, or proude, it maketh our worldly pilgrimage, a pleaſing iourney, as a good companion by his delightfull diſcourſes, abrid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth the tediouſneſſe of a long way. <hi>Berchorius</hi> well ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerueth,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:2460:13"/>that the larke, as long as ſhe fitteth on the ground, is very ſilent, and ſtill, but mounting vp into the aire, and houering in the golden beames of the delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſunne, ſhe lifteth vp her voice, and chanteth merri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and doubleth her various tunes, to the great pleaſure and contentment of thoſe that are partakers of her me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lody, and ſweet muſicke: So, and ſo is it, with mortall men, who, whilſt (they do fix, and riuet faſt their affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and their thoughts to the tranſitory vanities, and vaine negotiations of this wicked world; they are faint, yea, they are almoſt dead to all good works. But when they reuine their minds, and lift vp their cogitations deuoutly vnto God, with religious motions, and zealous meditations; then (and not before) their tunes are ſweet, they are delightfull, yea they are pleaſing vnto God himſelfe.</p>
            <q>
               <p>And like as the aire is the purer the neerer it is to the worlds chiefeſt light,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Idem. Pag.</hi> 154.</note> ſo mens deuotions are more ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtiall, and heauenly, by how much the neerer, (by true religion) they do aſcend, and preſent themſelues to the ſonne of God.</p>
            </q>
            <p>And thus (my ſonne) you ſee, that when your mind is ſanctified by true religion, then religion will make it pure, and a fit receptacle, and ſtorehouſe for euery kind of vertue. Wherein you ought daily to be exerciſed in this world.
<note place="margin">Virtue.</note>
            </p>
            <p>For without vertue your religion is but fained, your deuotions dul, and your praiers but varniſhed, and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſt with an outward ſhew of holineſſe towards God, and of charity towards men. The ofſpring of religion is vertue, and without vertue, religion is barren and neer vnto curſing. As was the figge tree,
<note place="margin">Mark. 11.13.</note> which yeelded no
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:2460:14"/>fruit to our Sauiour Chriſt, when (being hungry) he ſought it.</p>
            <p>Therefore (my Sonne) to the end that with a more ardent affection, and longing will, you may be deſirous to be retained into her ſeruice, it is moſt fitting that you be inſtructed plainly what ſhe is: that knowing her, and her worthineſſe, you may thinke your time to be well ſpent, in ſeeking her, and in honoring of her.</p>
            <p>Some men haue defined her to be, an vprighmeſſe of life,
<note place="margin">Seuerall opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning vertue. <hi>De ciuit. Dei. lib.</hi> 4.</note> in all things agreeable vnto reaſon: others that ſhe is the habite of doing well. Others that ſhe is the art of chooſing that which is good.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> ſaith, <hi>That ſhe is the skill to liue well.</hi> And <hi>Horace</hi> affirmeth, <hi>that virtue is nothing elſe, but the baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of vice:</hi> In ſumme they do all beſt agree when they ſay, that virtue conſiſteth in action, and that the medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation thereof without practiſe, is as an vnſtringed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument, whereon no man plaieth.</p>
            <p>For what auaileth it,
<note place="margin">Prudence.</note> that a man is wiſe, if the worlds occaſions be not partakers of his wiſedome? What mattereth it,
<note place="margin">Iuſtice.</note> if a mans knowledge be exquiſite to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne right from iniury, and from wrong? if he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce not ſentence for him that is oppreſſed.</p>
            <p>To what end is a mans mind, and the compoſition of his body framed to be valiant:
<note place="margin">Fortitude.</note> if (when the common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weales eſtate is in perill, and in danger) he be not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to ſupport, and to maintaine her cauſe.</p>
            <p>And wherefore is a man temperate,
<note place="margin">Temperance.</note> if to himſelfe only, and not vnto others, he be a preſident of modeſty, and of ſober gouernment.</p>
            <p>He that ſoweth virtue, ſhall reape honor. A vertuous man is neuer at reſt, vntill (by his endeuours) he hath
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:2460:14"/>done good: Neither doth he imagine that he hath done any good at all, except he do the beſt, and the moſt good that he is able.</p>
            <p>He ceaſeth not from any toile, if thereby he may profit others, either particularly to themſelues, or gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally for the good of many, and of the common weale.</p>
            <p>And though his actions be many, and various, yet they are alwaies vertuous: as in muſicke,
<note place="margin">Wiſd. 19.17.</note> the harmony doth ſtill remaine, though the notes, and tunes and ſongs, be oftentimes changed.</p>
            <p>It is not enough to boaſt of the name of vertue, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out vertuous deeds and actions; for without them, the name of vertue is fitly compared to a ſhadow without ſubſtance: And like to a drop of water on the ſands, or thirſty ground, which being quickly dried vp, leaueth no ſigne behind it, that it euer was.</p>
            <p>
               <q>Such men as do only deſire to know vertue, and not to practiſe her in their deeds, may fitly be compared vn. to children, who do delight to knocke flints together, that thereby they may ſee, and behold the ſparkles, but do not endeuour to make any true vſe of fire it ſelfe.</q>
            </p>
            <p>It is a pleaſing thing to be commended, but his prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes are more pretious who meriteth them, by exerciſing of his vertues.</p>
            <p>The practiſe of vertue is the chiefeſt patrimony, that a worthy man can expect, or ought (indeed) to deſire. <hi>Ipſa quidem virtus ſibimet pulcherrima merces: There is no price, which can counteruaile vertue.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Stillius Poeta.</note> A wiſe man placeth his contentment in nothing more, then by the actiue diſtribution of his vertues, to make himſelfe the more famous.</p>
            <p>Our parents may make vs rich, but it is God alone,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:2460:15"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:2460:15"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:2460:16"/>
               <q>that maketh vs to be vertuous: hence it is, that the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Monarchs, and of Kings, muſt be ſupported by the goodnes of their vertues: For he is much more gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous whom his vertues, then he whom his anceſtors <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aue made noble.</q>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>Much more is he to be admited, that ſwayeth a king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome by his vertues, then he that ruleth it by the only priuiledge of his enobled and heroicall diſcent. For ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors are but the ſeruants, and the attendants of vertue.</p>
               <p>If vertue be ioyned vnto Nobility, ſhe ſpreadeth her ſelfe into euery quarter, and darteth forth her glorious beames ouer large and ſpacious countries, as the ſunne doth his when (with them) he beautifieth the face, and viſage of the whole earth.</p>
            </q>
            <p>And like as an artificially carned picture, being pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented in gold, is much more delightfull to the eie, and is of a more choiſe eſteeme, then the ſame, being ſtam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped on iron, or on ſome baſer mettall. So though in men of low degree, and parentage, vertue be not without her deſerued praiſe and commendation, yet hauing the reſidence in the breaſts of ſuch as are of a generous ſtocke, and progeny, ſhe is more pleaſing, and ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, ſhe is more honorable, and more profitable to the common weale.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Gratior eſt pulchro veniens è corpore virtus,</l>
               <l>Then virtues are more pretious, and more deere,</l>
               <l>When in heroicke ſpirits they appeare.</l>
            </q>
            <p>This was the cauſe,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cominaeus.</hi> 265.</note> that made <hi>Cominaeus</hi> to be of this opinion, That wiſe men ought not ſo much to reſpect an honorable deſcent as a vertuous life.</p>
            <p>For as it is much better,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>D. Homfr. in Prax. Ieſuit</hi> 47.</note> to drinke good wine, out of an earthen pot, then vnwholſome liquor, in a golden
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:2460:16"/>cup, ſo he that is wiſe, will more eſteeme of the wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of a vertuous man, then of the honors, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motions of an only rich man, which hath none acquain tance or familiarity with vertue.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Leuinius Apolonius</hi> in his diſcouery of <hi>Peru,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Leuinius Apolonius.</hi> 16.</note> reporteth that thoſe Indians and barbarous nations, whom <hi>Pizar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> could not (by his ſword) violently, he eaſily conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and ſubdued, by the diſcreet practiſe, and pleaſing examples of his alluring vertues. <hi>Emitur ſola virtute po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtas.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lipſ.</hi> 59.</note> That command and that authority is moſt ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne, which deriueth her power from virtue.</p>
            <p>Vntill <hi>Alexander</hi> the great waxed proude, and drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, he wan more prouinces, ſubdued more kingdomes, and conquered more people, by the practiſe of his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable vertues, then he did by the vndaunted boldnes, and courage of himſelfe, and of his valiant men of war.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Neroes</hi> vertues (when he firſt began to raigne) gained him the due report of a moſt renowned Emperor: and <hi>Octauius Caeſar</hi> was neuer ſirnamed <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> vntill his experimented vertues crowned him with that immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talized dignity, and title.</p>
            <p>So profitable is vertue, that ſhe muſt be followed, and ſo amiable is ſhe, and ſo louely, that ſhe muſt be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced. She maketh her ſutors of poore men, to become rich: of rich men, ſhe maketh nobles, and of nobles, ſhe createth Kings, and Potentates, and Emperors of the world.</p>
            <p>A vertuous man cannot be miſerable in any fortune, nor vnfortunate, what chance ſoeuer happeneth. For vertue ſupplieth al wants, and ſwimmeth with vs, in eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſhipwracke.</p>
            <p>If we be ſicke, it mattereth not much, though our
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:2460:17"/>friends do forbeare to viſit vs, if at that tme, the true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of our vertues do keepe vs company: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will it be grieuous vnto vs to die in our beds, if our vertuous life warrant vs, that we die not in our ſinnes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pythagoras</hi> affirmeth, that riches are no ſure pillars, and that glory is vncertaine, that beauty fadeth as the flowers in the field, and that honors haue no long con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance, but virtue (ſaith he) is a ſtrong anchor, which holdeth vs from danger in euery ſtorme, you muſt not therefore hunt after thoſe things, that be moſt plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing: but after ſuch only, as are moſt vertuous, and you muſt vnderſtand, <q>(if you will effectually know any thing that he hath liued vnworthily, whoſe fame virtue hath not reported to poſterity: And death is neuer ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine, nor fearefull vnto him, who hath liued vertuouſly and well.</q> Therefore to conclude this point, that you may liue well, and die well, and that after death your fame may liue, and (as your children) ſuruiue, you being dead, loue vertue for her owne ſake, and practiſe her for the benefit of your ſelfe.</p>
            <p>She is the wife (my Sonne) whom you muſt wedde whilſt you are young: if you expect that your good deeds ſhall grow vnto any maturity, and ripenes, when you are old.</p>
            <p>This is the Miſtreſſe, whom you muſt ſerue in your tender yeeres, as an apprentize, if (by her) you will be made free, and receiue profit and reputation for your wages, and ſalary, when you are old.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In iuuentute cernuntur virtutis flores, vel fructus nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam.</hi> The Autumne cannot ſee the fruit of thoſe trees, whoſe bloſſomes the ſpring time neuer ſaw.</p>
            <p>If you begin not to loue vertue in your youth, it will
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:2460:17"/>be a harſh thing for you, to wooe her, when the threed of your life ſhall be tentred, and drawne forth almoſt to the vtmoſt length.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qui non eſt hodie, cras minus aptus erit,</hi> if your youth be moiſtned with her delightfull liquor, your age will alwaies retaine, and keepe the ſweet ſauor thereof: and if (whilſt you are young) you entertaine her for your ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance, the whole courſe of your earthly pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage will then be accompanied with her, as with a faithfull friend.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vir ſapiens is eſt, qui non patitur vitam: &amp; Iuuentutem, inter iocos, &amp; ſomnum affluere:</hi> and he is truely wiſe, who being young, reſolueth to attempt nothing but that, which by vertue, he ſhall be counſelled and aduiſed to take in hand.</p>
            <p>For her directions are religious without hipocriſie.</p>
            <list>
               <item>They are true without falſhood.</item>
               <item>They are plaine without diſſimulation.</item>
               <item>They are vpright without fraude.</item>
               <item>They are honeſt without wantonneſſe.</item>
               <item>They are temperate without exceſſe.</item>
               <item>They are graue without lightneſſe.</item>
               <item>They are conſtant without wauering.</item>
               <item>They are confident, without feare.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>Viaticum tibi (fili mi) ab Adoleſcentia ad ſenectutem,
<note place="margin">Diogenes Laertius.</note> vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutem compara.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From youth to age, let vertue be your paſſage, as a bridge is from the one ſide of a riuer to the other. So ſhall your yong yeeres bee reſpected by the aged, and ſo ſhall your old age be a preſident of vertue vnto thoſe that be yong.</p>
            <p>Now as it is not enough for a man to poſſeſſe great
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:2460:18"/>ſtore of ſiluer and of gold, vnleſſe he be alſo taught, and inſtructed by the rules of bounty, and of liberality, how to diſpoſe it well. So it is not only requiſite, that a man be vertuouſly enclined, but he muſt likewiſe be furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with learning, and with wiſedome: whereby he may be able to make a profitable diſpenſation and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtribution of his vertues,
<note place="margin">Learning. Wiſedome.</note> for the good of himſelfe and of other men.</p>
            <p>This made <hi>Salomon</hi> to ſay, <hi>That he that poſſeſſeth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding,
<note place="margin">Prou. 19.18.</note> loueth his owne ſoule: and keepeth wiſedome to find goodneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For like as a warlike galley ſwimmeth ſmoothly in her perfect ſtrength, againſt her enemies, being winged with her oares on either ſide, but (being maimed vpon one of them) can hardly defend her ſelfe. So vertue (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by learning and by wiſedome and by her harneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearers, mightily ſupported) marcheth as a ſtout cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion into the worlds field: and fighteth a ſtrong combat againſt wickedneſſe and ſinne. But being depriued of one of thoſe her helps, ſhe maketh a weake reſiſtance (not without much difficulty) to preſerue her ſelfe from danger, and from ſpoile.</p>
            <p>Concerning the neceſſity of being learned,
<note place="margin">Learning.</note> (for the better practiſing of religion, and of vertuous actions) you muſt know, that without learning, you ſhall be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable to the common-weale: as a ſhip is to the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant, if (irrecuperably) ſhe be moared, and grauelled in the ſands.</p>
            <p>He which walketh in darkneſſe, ſeeth not whither he goeth, neither can you, if you want learning (by reaſon of your ignorance) direct your owne waies.
<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 51.28.</note> 
               <hi>Learning is of ſo great a price, that you muſt get her with a great ſumme
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:2460:18"/>of mony, for that (by her) you may poſſeſſe much gold.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>There is gold (ſaith Salomon) and a multitude of pretious ſtones, but the lippes of knowledge are a pretious iewell,
<note place="margin">Prou. 20.15. Pro. 18.16. Pro. 18.25.</note> it brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth ſuch as keepe her company before great men. And if you do exalt her, ſhe will exalt you againe: A wiſe heart getteth knowledge and the eare of the wiſe ſeeketh learning.</hi> She fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth many fooliſh whom by her precepts ſhe maketh wiſe: She findeth many men poore, whom in ſhort time ſhe placeth vpon honors throne, ſhe findeth many men vitious, but by her inſtructions, ſhe maketh them in godlineſſe and in vertue to ſurmount others.</p>
            <p>By learning the king himſelfe, and his Nobles, are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabled to know God, and to rule the heady multitude; wiſely perſwading, or enforcing them to obey. <hi>Fortuna Craeſum facit: Minerua Platone<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> Fortune may make men rich, but learning maketh them wiſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Marcus Aurelius</hi> the Emperor of Rome was wont to ſay, that a Prince ought not to content himſelfe with ſo much learning as one man hath. But he aduiſed him (by ſtudy) to endeuour to know as much as many men did: becauſe he ruleth, &amp; gouerneth not one, but many.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Alexander</hi> the great eſtimated learning at ſo high a rate,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Plutarch. in vita Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andri.</hi> 676.</note> that he was much offended with <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> his ſchoolemaſter, becauſe he had publiſhed to the worlds view, thoſe notable precepts wherein he had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed him: ſaying, that he more deſired to excell others in knowledge, and in learning,
<note place="margin">Idem.</note> then in authority and power. This ſingular and extraordinary loue which he bare vnto learning, made him to carry with him in his wars, all <hi>Homers</hi> works, in a curious and coſtly caſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket which he found among the richeſt, and beſt iewels which he had taken from <hi>Darius</hi> the great king of the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:2460:19"/>Perſians. <hi>Leo</hi> a king of the Romans, was ſo great a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron, and ſo effectuall a louer of learning, that he wiſhed often, that he might once be ſo fortunate, as to conuert the wages of his ſoldiers into ſtipends for learned men.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Paulus Aemilius</hi> that noble Roman,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Plutarch in vita Pauli Aemily.</hi> 260.</note> who ouerthrew in a fierce and cruell battell, <hi>Perſeus</hi> the king of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedonians, refuſed to ſee the riches and the treaſure of his conquered enemy, becauſe he would not couet it. And would not permit his owne ſonnes to take any thing which belonged to him, but his books only, by whom their minds, and their vnderſtandings might be adored, and beautified with learning and with know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Cato Vtican</hi> in vacation times,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Idem in vita Catonis Vtican. Pag</hi> 776.</note> and at his beſt leaſure, went to recreat himſelfe in the country, he vſed to carry thither with him, the beſt Philoſophers, and his choiceſt books.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Demoſthenes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Idem on vitae Demoſthenis. Pag.</hi> 847.</note> to the end that his acquaintance, and neereſt friends might not (by carrying of him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad according to their cuſtome) withdraw him from his ſtudy, and from his books, cauſed the haires of his head to be ſhauen off.</p>
            <p>To one, who aſked of <hi>Thales</hi> the Philoſopher who was happy? he made this anſwer, <hi>Qui corpore ſanus eſt, Fortuna Diues, &amp; Animo eruditus:</hi> He that is healthy, wealthy, and learned.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Plato</hi> admired and wondred, how men would loue, and ſeeke after learning, if they knew her? And <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine</hi> the great made many lawes, for the furtherance of learning, and for the aduancement of learned men.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alphonſus</hi> king of <hi>Arragon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hartin. Sthedell.</hi> 248.</note> ſo greatly loued learning, that he omitted not his hard ſtudies in his moſt dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:2460:19"/>wars. And <hi>Pliny</hi> the ſecond ſo inwardly affected it,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Idem.</hi> 111.</note> that he would willingly and diligently read all books which were publiſhed: affirming the time to be loſt, which was not ſpent in ſtudy, and that no booke was ſo bad, but that ſome learning, and ſome inſtruction might be gotten in reading of it.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Pythagoras</hi> the great Philoſopher was wont to ſay, that men ought to be more carefull,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Idem. Pag.</hi> 61.</note> by learning to expell ignorance out of their minds, then by phyſicke to purge the diſeaſes of their bodies.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Empedocles</hi> ſaid,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Idem. Pag.</hi> 71.</note> that a wiſe man (aboue all things) ſhould long for future happines, contemne vncertaine riches, and adorn his mind with learning. &amp; with know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Albertus Magnus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Idem. Pag.</hi> 214.</note> (albeit that for his great learning and wiſedome, he were aduanced vnto many dignities, and created Biſhop of <hi>Ratiſbona;</hi> yet (finding his Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall imploiments, to be daily impediments to his ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies) he reſigned his place, and office to another, that in a more priuate courſe of life, he might make himſelfe the more familiarly acquainted with his books.</p>
            <p>It is reported of the Emperor <hi>Charles</hi> the fourth,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Idem. Pag.</hi> 231.</note> that on a time he continued more then foure howres in the ſchooles of the Philoſophers, harkning (with ſuch contentment, and with ſuch delight and pleaſure) to the ſerious and skilfull diſputations of thoſe learned men, that he forgat his dinner, and thereby) in ſome ſort diſpleaſed ſome of his Noble men. So that one (among the reſt) being more forwards then others were (couert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to reproue him for his long ſtay) told him, that his ſupper was ready. But the good Emperor mildly anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him thus: My ſupper indeed is ready, ſo is not thine,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:2460:20"/>meaning thereby, that the exerciſes of the learned, were as pleaſing to his mind, as meats and drinks were to the others belly.</p>
            <p>Infinitely therefore deceiued was <hi>Licinius</hi> the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror,
<note place="margin">Iuſtine.</note> who groſly did affirme, that learning was the poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and the ruine of the common weale. <hi>Scientia non ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet inimicum prater ignorantem:</hi> Learning hath no grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter enemy then ignorance: and ſo was <hi>Alacicus</hi> king of the Gothes deceiued, when he would not ſuffer his ſon to be inſtructed in learning, becauſe (as he ſaid) it would make him faint harted, and a coward: and ſo was <hi>Lewis</hi> the eleuenth the French King much deceiued: who (in a ſkorne of learning, and of learned men) would often ſay, that his ſonne ſhould only learne this one ſentence in the latine tongue: <hi>Qui neſcit diſsimulare, neſcit regnare:</hi> He hath not learned to rule, and to gouerne well, who hath not learned artificially to diſſemble, to cozen, and to deceiue. Nay rather it may be truly ſaid, that without learning, it is a hard matter to be a king: but to be a lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned king, it is to be a worthy, and a renowned king in deed. For like as grafts, being incorporated into the beſt ſtockes, do bring forth the beſt, the moſt pleaſing, and the faireſt fruit, ſo learning being ioined vnto he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roicall and princely nobility, or with gentry, produceth rare effects, and maketh ſuch (as do poſſeſſe her) truly noble, and deſeruedly to be reſpected and aduanced aboue other men.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Plutarch</hi> ſaith,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Plutarth. in vita Coriolani Pag.</hi> 221.</note> that the benefit which men do get by meanes of their learning, is very great: For it teacheth ſuch as by nature are rude, and rough, by the rules and compaſſe of reaſon, to be curteous and ciuill: and rather to be contended with a meane eſtate, which promiſeth
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:2460:20"/>much ſecurity, and peace, then to affect higher digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and eminent promotions. In whom there is neither ſafety nor certainty, nor contentment, nor eaſe.
<note place="margin">Ignorance.</note>
            </p>
            <p>An ignorant man without learning is altogether barren, and drie in all worthy proiects, and deuiſes whatſoeuer, by reaſon of his ignorance, like as the country of Egypt is vnfruitfull in that yeere, wherein it is not watered, and made fruitfull, by the ouerflowing pride of the riuer of Nilus: He that is ignorant hath fewer eies to diſcerne his owne good, and to preuent his owne miſfortunes, then <hi>Polyphemus</hi> had to foreſee his owne danger.</p>
            <p>As an Owle cannot behold the bright ſhining of the ſplendent ſunne, ſo a man that is ignorant, taketh no pleaſure in the ſociety of ſuch as are ſharply witted, and of mature iudgement and vnderſtanding.</p>
            <p>An ignorant man (becauſe he knoweth little, diſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth much: if he be ſilent, his wiſedome is ſuſpected, and if he ſpeake, his owne tongue is the proclaimer of his owne ſhame. If he heare other men diſcourſing wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, he is not thereby inſtructed, becauſe he can no better cenſure of their wiſdome, then a blind man can diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh of the variety, and diuerſity of many colours: But if he heare men ſpeaking fooliſhly, he augmenteth and encreaſeth thereby his owne folly: For his meane capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city (apprehending only things of the ſmalleſt conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence) is ſo benummed, as it cannot aſcend to the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of any knowledge or profitable learning.</p>
            <p>A man that trauelleth in a ſtrange country, may not be maruelled at nor held to be vnwiſe, though ſome times he chance to wander out of the right way. But a man that is ignorant may iuſtly be wondred at, becauſe
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:2460:21"/>he looſeth not his way, but his owne ſelfe. He walketh in darkneſſe in the brighteſt day, and is too too light in euery waighty matter.</p>
            <p>Ignorance in matters of profit, baniſheth all hopes either of preſent, or of future aduancement, in matters of rule and of gouernment, it ruinateth th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſtate, which it endeuoreth to ſupport. And in matters of religion, it carrieth mens ſoules headlong into the bottomleſſe pit of torments, and of eternall deſtruction.</p>
            <p>An ignorant man liueth in perpetuall captiuity and in bondage: For ignorance is ranke fooliſhneſſe, and who is in deeper thraldome then a foole?</p>
            <p>If a man be vnlearned, he wandreth vp and downe in the intricate labyrinth of the cunning world, like to a loſt traueller without a guide in a ſolitary, and in a vaſt deſert, and as a bird without wings, or as a ſouldier deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poiled of his armour, or as a ſhip without a director in the ocean ſea: ſo is he vnable, ſo is he vnperfit in all his waies. All his conceits, and all his imaginations, are as vntimely fruit, and all his labors and his actions are out of ioint.</p>
            <p>He deuiſeth things which are vnprofitable, and put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth them in execution to his owne hinderance, and loſſe.</p>
            <p>But he that is learned, treaſureth vp wiſedome, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he effecteth what he liſteth:
<note place="margin">Learning.</note> yea things iuſtly to be admired, and to be wondred at. This faire, and this loue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Lady cannot be won, but by an induſtrious care, and by a conſtant ſute, and ſhe is ouertaken by ſuch only, as with daily labor and ſtudy do follow after her.
<note place="margin">Study.</note> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (my ſonne) if you deſire to be her companion, you muſt (by frequent ſtudy) attempt to procure, and to win
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:2460:21"/>her loue. <hi>Nemo enim naſcitur Artifex,</hi> Learning is not obtained without labor, and <hi>labor improbus omnia vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit,</hi> as ſaith the poet, by hard labor, and daily ſtudy, we alwaies do ſtep neerer vnto learning.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Omnia dij laboribus vendunt,</hi> No excellent thing is at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chieued and gotten without difficulty and paine: and learning being ſo gotten) doth not only make men ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent, but ſhe is (indeed) the excellency of man.</p>
            <p>In euery day (therefore) you muſt make ſome pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe in the way towards learning, by your ſtudy. <hi>Perit enim omne tempus, quod ſtudio non impartitur,</hi> That time is loſt, which is not ſpent in ſtudy, and in ſerious meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for learnings ſake.</p>
            <p>But if you bend your reſolutions (with will and ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, as with the beſt, and ſwifteſt hounds) to hunt, and to runne after her, your paines will be delightfull, and your labors will be repleniſhed with variety of content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and with pleaſure. <hi>Conſuetudo enim facit alteram na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turam,</hi> cuſtome begetteth an habite, yea (in ſome ſort) it createth (as it were) a new nature, both in ſtudy, and alſo in all other negotiations whatſoeuer.</p>
            <p>And when a man (by frequent ſtudy) hath found lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and vnderſtanding, he then knoweth that <hi>ſtudioſis in otio nullum eſt otium:</hi> A ſtudent when he is moſt at lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, is neuer idle. This (my ſonne) is a worke of impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant waight, and conſequence, and therefore you muſt know, that <hi>opere in magno fas eſt obrumpere ſomnum.</hi> You muſt not be idle, negligent, nor ſlothfull in a buſineſſe of ſuch great moment and waight.</p>
            <p>But neither do I require, nor is it meete, and fitting,
<note place="margin">Moderation in ſtudy.</note> that your ſtudies be more painful then pleaſing, or more laborious then healthfull. For I my ſelfe haue learned
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:2460:22"/>long agone, that <hi>nullum violentum eſt perpetuum.</hi> Things that are violent, haue no long being, and continuance.</p>
            <p>The prouerb telleth vs, that it is the moderate pace comes ſooneſt to the iournies end. If the ſtrongeſt piece of ordinance be ſurcharged with power, and with ſhot, it will ſurely breake.</p>
            <p>A ſtrong ſhip, that is ouer-laden muſt needs ſinke.</p>
            <p>A bow kept alwaies bent, will either cracke in ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, or looſe his ſtrength. And a willing mind being op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed with ouermuch ſtudy, will rather wax feeble, and dull, then be capable of the multitude of thoſe things, which vnceſſant labors do offer, and preſent.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Gutta cauat lapidem, &amp;c.</l>
               <l>As ſtones are pearſt with drops of raine,</l>
               <l>Not by their force, but often fall:</l>
               <l>So men much learning do attaine,</l>
               <l>By reading oft, not reading all.</l>
            </q>
            <p>A man (not by infinite ſtudy, nor by continuall paine) is made learned, but by his moderate endeuours, duly imploied with pleaſure, and with delight.</p>
            <p>Let your ſtudy therefore be moderate,
<note place="margin">A rule for ſtudy.</note> not violent, more pleaſing, then painfull, that ſanity, and health of body may (with ſtudy, and with learning) be preſerued and maintained, <hi>nam fruſtra ſapit, qui ſibi non ſapit:</hi> you ſhall in vaine thinke to make your ſelfe to be profitable vnto others by your learning, if you be not carefull (by moderating of your ſtudies) to prouide for your owne health.</p>
            <p>It is true, that for the attaining of learning, <hi>Melior eſt vigilantia ſomno:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Night ſtudies hurtfull.</note> We muſt not be ſlothfull or ſluggiſh, but we muſt watch: But not too much in the night. For night watchings in ſtudy are dangerous and hurtfull,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:2460:22"/>both to the wit, and alſo to the eies: yea, they are gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally preiudiciall vnto the ſtate of the whole body.</p>
            <p>The mornings muſt therefore be the choiceſt,
<note place="margin">Morning Studies profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table.</note> and chiefeſt times in which I counſell you to ſpend, and to imploy your labors in thoſe ſtudies, and in thoſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects which by your religious, learned,
<note place="margin">Mr. Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niball Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon.</note> and honeſt tutor ſhall (for your beſt furtherance in knowledge, and in learning) be appointed to you, which times (I am right well aſſured) you can with the more facility, and alacrity imploy therein;
<note place="margin">Mr. William Periman.</note> becauſe you haue heretofore bin trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and enured ſo to do, by the prouident care, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections of your laſt ſufficient and kind ſchoolemaſter.
<note place="margin">Wiſdome.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The next pillar, vpon which true vertue (as on an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moueable rocke) is founded, and eſtabliſhed,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Wiſdome.</hi> 7.</note> is wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. <hi>Which Salomon the wiſeſt king that euer was, prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red before Scepters, and before thrones, and accompted riches to be nothing, and gold to be duſt, and grauell, and ſiluer to be clay in compariſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of her. And doth affirme,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eccles.</hi> 7.21.</note> that he who vſeth wiſedome, becommeth a partaker of the loue of God: And that wiſedome doth ſtrengthen a man more then ten mighty Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces that are within the City.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The heathen Philoſopher being ignorant of the true God, and guided only by the light of nature,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ethic. lib.</hi> 2.</note> and of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, defined wiſedome to be the knowledge of the truth, conſiſting in the choice of that which is good.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cicero</hi> ſaith, that ſhe is the beſt directer of a mans life, the ioy of good ſociety, the ground of vertue, the enemy of vice, the builder of cities, and the founder of king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, and of common weales. <hi>Iſocrates</hi> writing to <hi>Demon cus</hi> ſaith, that ſtrength of body without wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, is as a ſword in a mad mans hand, but he that is wiſe ordereth his ſteps by wiſedome, and by good diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion.
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:2460:23"/>A wiſe man hath one foot vpon the land, and another foot vpon the ſea. For by his wiſedome, he compaſſeth both ſea and land, ſeeking out, and finding thoſe things which are alwaies hidden from ignorant and from fooliſh men.</p>
            <p>He looketh vpon the heauens, and conſidereth of the circling of the ſunne, the courſes of the moone, and of the ſtars, the motions of the Spheres, and of the planets and of the reſt of the celeſtiall orbes, the cauſes of light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, and of thunders, the generating of winds, ſtormes, tempeſts, froſts, ſnowes, hailes, and of the raine.</p>
            <p>He diggeth deepe into the earths bowels (piercing almoſt her centre) where he findeth allkinds of mettall, and of pretious ſtones.</p>
            <p>He diſcerneth the natures of herbs, of trees, of ſtones, of fiſhes, of birds, and of creeping things innumerable both ſmall and great.</p>
            <p>He tameth and maketh gentle ſauage beaſts, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimeth birds from their wildneſſe, he ruleth cities, and countries, in times of peace, and in times of war, by his deuiſes, ſtratagems, plots, and policies, he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quereth his ſtouteſt enemies in the field.</p>
            <p>A wiſe man neuer attempteth any thing againſt his owne will, nor is ſorry for any thing that he hath done, becauſe he doeth nothing raſhly, nor of felſe will. He vnderſtandeth much when he heareth but a word, and concealeth enough when he heareth but little ſpoken.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sapienti omnia, licet inuia ſunt, tamen peruia:</hi> He tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth aduerſe fortune to his owne happineſſe, and bliſſe. And euill chances are (by his diſcretion, patience, and moderation) conuerted to his good.</p>
            <p>His mind is not captiuated, nor enthraled with any
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:2460:23"/>bations, nor with the worlds follies, and his wit diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth thoſe things which other mens eies did ſcarcely euer ſee.</p>
            <p>The whole world is to him but as one city, becauſe his wiſedome maketh him throughly acquainted with all paſſages, and with all occurrences whatſoeuer.</p>
            <p>A wiſe man diſpoſeth rightly of ſuch things as are preſent, he foreſeeth things that are to come,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lipſius.</hi> 13.</note> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membreth (with profit) things forepaſt.</p>
            <p>He will not deceiue, nor be deceiued,
<note place="margin">Cic. de orat. Eſchilus.</note> he neuer thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth that he hath found wiſedome, except he do make a commendable vſe of her. The common Prouerb tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth vs, that a wiſe mans words do draw water vnto the mill. For he ſpeaketh not in vaine, but frameth his ſpeech to ſound and to good purpoſe. He thinketh it not to be ſo needfull, to know many things (for often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations ſake) as a few with pleaſure, and with profit.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ethicks.</hi> 335.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Daneus</hi> doth affirme, that by how much the wiſer a man is, with ſo much the more commodity, and honor, he effecteth, and performeth thoſe things, that are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to his charge.</p>
            <p>A wiſe mans iudgement,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ren. de vit. Ieſu.</hi> 3.</note> and his diſcretion are of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes ſo much applauded, and approued, that the whole ſtate and the affaires of kingdomes, and of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon weales, are committed, and referred to the mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging and diſpoſing of one wiſe man.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Euripides</hi> ſaith, that <hi>mens vnaſapientis, multorum vincit manus.</hi> A wiſe man is ſo potent, by meanes of his wiſedome, that he ouercommeth multitudes, and bin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth them in fetters as his ſlaues.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Wiſd.</hi> 7.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The true reaſon whereof is plainly diſcouered by <hi>Salomon,</hi> where he ſaith, that <hi>God is the leader vnto wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:2460:24"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:2460:24"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:2460:25"/>and he is the director of the wiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A wiſe man only is rich, and where wiſedome kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth her reſidence, there pouerty dareth not to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, or to ſhew her face.</p>
            <p>His hands do not offend, becauſe they are reſtrained from euill by his wiſedome.</p>
            <p>His eies are not betraied, or beguiled by vanities, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe his mind hath pronounced her iudgement, that all things are but vaine. His eares are not open to the enchantments of folly, becauſe he is inſtructed and reſolued to neglect them, as the deceiuing ſweetneſſe of a Syrens ſong.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And his heart deſpiſeth and contemneth all wicked and vngodly motions,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45.1.</note> becauſe it is ſtill enditing of a good matter, as Dauids was.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that of a wiſe man, it is truely ſaid, <hi>Sapiens domina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitur astris,</hi> and that <hi>ſapiens eſt ipſo Ioue tantum minor:</hi> A wiſe man prieth, and ſearcheth into the ſecrets of the heauens: and is only inferior to the Gods. <hi>Yet muſt we not be wiſe in our owne opinions,
<note place="margin">Rule.</note> and conceits; for of ſuch a one, it is thus ſentenced: Seeſt thou a man that is wiſe in his owne conceit,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prouerb.</hi> 26.12</note> more hope is of a foole then of him.</hi> But we muſt ſtill labor to get wiſedome,
<note place="margin">Seiſe loue.</note> for one day ſpent in ſtudy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for her, is better imploied, then an eternity of time, conſumed in hunting after vanity and folly.</p>
            <p>It is reported in hiſtories, that <hi>Apelles</hi> the cunning and moſt renowned painter beſtowed ten yeeres (by his exquiſite and moſt curious art) to delineate, and rarely to ſet foorth the picture of <hi>Venus,</hi> and her beauty. And we may reade that the Grecians with the infinite expence of their treaſury,
<note place="margin">Dares Phri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ins.</note> and with the loſſe and death of many thouſand of skilfull captains, and of renowned
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:2460:25"/>and valiant men of war, ſpent as long a time to take to ranſacke, and to deſtroy the ſtoutly defended city of <hi>Troy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The winning of ſuch a city is of farre leſſer accompt, and moment, then the enioying of wiſedome: and in regard of her vnſpeakable excellency, painting is but a fooliſh art.</p>
            <p>Though therefore (my ſonne) you ſpend more time then ten yeeres, nay though you labor all your lifes daies in her ſtudy, and to obtaine her, you ſhall in the end reape more benefit, and commendations by thoſe your trauels, then either thoſe Grecians did by theirs, or <hi>Apelles</hi> by his. For wiſedome is ſo faire, that none but her owne penſill can depaint her, and ſo impregnable, that none but they whom ſhe pleaſeth, can aſſault and win her.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For wiſedome commeth from the Lord,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ecclus.</hi> 1.</note> and without her you cannot (as you ought) praiſe, and magnifie your God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore (my ſonne) embrace her, for ſhe is faire, court her, for ſhe is louely, follow after her, for ſhe is rich, reuerence her, for ſhe is honorable, and admire her for ſhe maketh her darlings, and her companions, the only wonders of the world.</p>
            <p>The next thing of great importance,
<note place="margin">Company.</note> which I counſell you aduiſedly to obſerue is, that you be wiſely reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiue and very wary, and chary, in making good choice of thoſe, with whom you do intend, and purpoſe to conuerſe. <hi>Nam plaerum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> tales ſumus, quales ij ſunt quibuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum viuimus:</hi> Such we are for the moſt part, as they are, with whom familiarly we liue, and with whom for the moſt part we ſpend our time.</p>
            <p>The Philoſophers do wel obſerue, that al waters (both
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:2460:26"/>in temperature, in colour, and in taſte) do anſwer, and agree with the nature, and the diſpoſition of thoſe grounds and of that earth, through which they make their ſecret paſſages, and their waies.</p>
            <p>And in like manner, men do put in practiſe thoſe things, which by frequent cuſtome they haue deriued to themſelues, from thoſe, with whom they haue had familiarity and friendly dealings.</p>
            <p>And like as it is quickly known, of what country, or prouince, ſhips are by their flags, and penions, which proudly they beare higheſt in their tops.</p>
            <p>And as the inward cogitations of a mans hart are publikely reuealed by his ſpeech, and outward actions, ſo is it plainly demonſtrated to ſuch as are wiſe, what motions do chiefly rule, and raigne in a man, by the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions and qualities of thoſe, with whom he doth in familiarity conuerſe. And though (my ſonne) by Gods grace, and furtherance you may be well inclined vnto godlineſſe, and holineſſe of life, yet if you be not mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched with correſpondent company, nor do fellowſhip with ſuch, as are in like qualities alike diſpoſed, you can no more produce into action thoſe good and vertuous things, whereunto you are by nature inclined, and well framed, then a clocke can (by a due conſent with time) ſignifie the howers of the day aright, if his waights, and poiſes, be not in all proportions anſwerable to his wheeles. Who but thoſe hacking fencers, impudent ſtage players,
<note place="margin">Examples.</note> beaſtly drunkards, polluted maſters of damnable brothell houſes, and deſperate companions (with whom <hi>Commodus</hi> the Emperor conuerſed in his youth) infected him with their looſe,
<note place="margin">Commodus imperator</note> and abhominable vices, and defiled him with all thoſe deteſtable, and
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:2460:26"/>vnmatchable ſinnes which wickedly and with greedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe they practiſed? Who? but Pierce <hi>Gaueſton</hi> and the two Spencers (the Father and the Sonne with whoſe company King <hi>Edward</hi> the ſecond was too too much delighted) inticed him by lightneſſe of his life,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vita. Edw.</hi> 2.</note> and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind behauiour to be iniurious vnto Queene <hi>Iſabell</hi> his vertuous wife? who (at that time was reputed to be the goodlieſt and the faireſt Lady in the world) and perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded him to contemne and to make hauocke of his no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles: and made him at length to be depriued both of his kingdome, and of his life?</p>
            <p>Who (in the raigne of King <hi>Richard</hi> the ſecond) but <hi>Robert Vere</hi> Duke of <hi>Ireland Michael</hi> de la <hi>Pool</hi> his Chan cellor <hi>William Scroope</hi> Earle of <hi>Wiltſhire,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vita. Rich.</hi> 2.</note> Robert Treſihan</hi> his chiefe Iuſtice, Sir <hi>Nicholas Brembre, Sir Iohn Buſh, Sir Iohn Bagot,</hi> and <hi>Sir Henry Greene,</hi> men of proud ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macks, flattering tongues, oppreſſors of the common people, contemners of the nobility, and enticers of their ſoueraigne to naughty and lewd behauior) occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned the ruine and the downfall of ſo great a king (who fawning more then was fitting on their company) was by their wicked counſell aduiſed and forwarded to put into execution and practiſe things which were hurtfull to himſelfe, and hatefull to the common weale?</p>
            <p>Who but the vnthrifty companions of <hi>Henry</hi> the fift, made him a wild, and a ſwaggering Prince? And what but their baniſhment? and a mutuall conuerſe with his graue, and prudent counſellors of eſtate, made him af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards to be a moſt renowned and a peerleſſe king?</p>
            <p>And though (my ſonne) I inſtance in this matter, (as in other paſſages of this diſcourſe) vpon kings and Princes, who (either to their vtter downfals, or to their
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:2460:27"/>great perill, and danger) haue chiefly experimented the bitter effects of hard fortune, by aſſociating to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues lewde and graceleſſe companions, yet may you certainly vnderſtand, and infallibly conclude thereby, that not only ſuch high, and imperious Monarchs, but inferior perſons alſo (in their ſeuerall places) will quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be corrupted, and endangered by the vngodly and wicked qualities of their wicked companions, with whom too familiarly they do conuerſe.</p>
            <p>Beware therefore of euill company, for like as a bad bird by nature cannot bring foorth a good egge, ſo an euill companion cannot (by his example, or by his counſell) produce in his friend, any commendable acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whatſoeuer.</p>
            <p>It is farre better therefore to be ſolitary, and alone, then to be ſorted with wicked company: For as a red roſe being ſmothered in the ſmoke of ſulphur looſeth her faire colour,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eerch. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct. Moral.</hi> 16.</note> and doth aſſume another, which is a counterfet and a falſe white.</p>
            <p>So a vertuous man, frequenting the ſociety of bad companions, looſeth his former vertues, and blemiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth himſelfe with the vnperfit die of impiety and ſinne. It is impoſſible to touch pitch, and not to be defiled therewith.</p>
            <p>A man cannot lie among dogs, but he ſhall be ſtung, and bitten, and troubled with many fleas.</p>
            <p>Neither can a man haunt, or vſually frequent the company of ſuch as are euill, and himſelfe remaine ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous and good.</p>
            <p>It is more ſafe for an Aſſe loaden with gold, to lodge among theeues, then it is for a vertuous man to engage himſelfe as a familiar companion to liue among ſuch as
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:2460:27"/>are Godles and vniuſt.</p>
            <p>For like as the Sunne is of himſelfe cleare, beutifull, and pure, and comforteth all liuing cratures with the nouriſhing and fruitfull influence of his glorious beames, but hurteth often times, if it be in coniuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with a planet, which is malignant &amp; vnfortunate; ſo though a man be of himſelfe vertuous &amp; wel diſpoſed: yet if he be tied and bound, if he be linked; and locked faſt to the loathſome Societie of a lewd and of a badde companio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, he ſhal (together with him) runne into ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny miſchiefes, and into many dangers: as <hi>Partridges</hi> doe vnwiſly follow one another into the fowlers net, to their owne perdition and deſtruction.</p>
            <p>It is the nature and property of ſicke men to loue them beſt, who doe giue vnto them and bring to them, ſuch things, as (moſt greedily) they doe deſire, though they doe much augment and encreaſe their ſicknes, and their griefe thereby.</p>
            <p>And ſo it is the qualitie of many men, who are not vertuouſly and well enclined, to affect moſt of all, ſuch men as are of all others worſt diſpoſed, and doe ſooth them in their vanities, and in their groſſe and pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable follies. Though (indeede) ſuch glozing, and ſuch hatefull flattery, doe daily (with their ſinne) augment their ſhame. But contrariwiſe,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Idem.</hi> 61.</note> a prudent man ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth his companion to bee wiſe, as a pleaſant ſpring moiſtneth, and fructifieth thoſe grounds, which doe next adioyne vnto her. And like as that part of all kindes of fleſh taſteth moſt delicately, which lieth next vnto the bones; by reaſon of the ſweetneſſe of the marrow that is in them, ſo the dearer and the neerer we be vnto honeſt and vnto religious and good
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:2460:28"/>companions; the more commendable and praiſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy will our actions be by reaſon of their choiceſt qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, and vertues.</p>
            <p>A faire morning commonly betokeneth a faire and a pleaſant day; and the good companie, which a man frequenteth, is a ſtrong argument that he is diſpoſed well. It is for painters to deuiſe for their pictures ſuch viſages, and ſuch faces, as they pleaſe, but you may not chuſe whom you liſt, for your familiar conſorts and companions.</p>
            <p>But like as good wine is to be choſen by the ſmell, and by the colour, and by the taſte: ſo muſt you chuſe your companions by their <hi>Religion,</hi> by their <hi>Wiſedome,</hi> and by their <hi>vertue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And though (perhaps) you may iuſtly find ſome fault in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:
<note place="margin">Rule.</note> 
               <hi>(Nam nemo eſt qui omnibus horis ſapit)</hi> yet may you not againe forſake your companion if (in his chiefeſt parts, &amp; in his generall diſpoſition) he be vertuous and good: no more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you can truly condemne the right, and the good vſe of a knife, or of a needle, becauſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduenture the one by a miſchaunce hath cut your hand, and the other prickt your finger.</p>
            <p>Let this ſuffice (my Sonne) for the beſt rules, and for the chiefeſt inſtructions which I am able to giue, and to preſcribe vnto you, concerning the electing, and the chuſing of your familiar companions, with whom you do intend familiarly to ſpend your time. Now as it is exceeding neceſſarie, that you be right well aduiſed in the choiſe of ſuch companions;
<note place="margin">Friendſhip.</note> as (by their <hi>wiſedome</hi> and good example) may make you a happy partner of their vertues; ſo is it as needfull, that ſome of them be reputed, nay rather, that ſome few of them be (indeede)
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:2460:28"/>your inward friends: for in the fruition of the loue of ſuch will conſiſt a great part of your contentedneſſe in this life.</p>
            <p>For your true friend oftentimes will preuent the cauſes of your misfortunes, or elſe (by his good ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice and counſell) hee will either expell, or at leaſt mitigate the vehemencie of your ſorrowes.</p>
            <p>His mutuall exchange of loue for loue, will augment your ioyes, and plentifully powre into your boſome, thoſe comforts which moſt of all you want, and do de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire.</p>
            <p>The preſence of a faithfull friend will make you (in ſome meaſure) to ſmile at your aduerſe fortunes; and wil ſo qualifie their bitternes, that therby they ſeeme to be leſſe, then indeede they be. <hi>Multa quae nos non poſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus animo, amico ſuperamus mala:</hi> A friend will teach with patience to endure calamities, which otherwiſe you ſhall not be able to diſgeſt.</p>
            <p>If your eſtate be ſmall, by friendſhip it will encreaſe; and though it be very ſplendent and eminent aboue o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, yet the want of faithfull friends will ſoone impaire it, and make it heauie and burdenſome vnto vs.</p>
            <p>The longeſt iourney will ſeeme to be but a common walke, if you be fellowſhiped with a faithfull friend; and if you ſeeke for a matchleſſe treaſure, you ſhall ſurely find it, if you find a conſtant friend: and of all other men, you ſhall be moſt miſerable, if you haue not ſuch a one.</p>
            <p>An ordinarie companion, if he doe but ſlightly fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie you will aſſiſt, and aide you in your aduerſities, if they be but ordinarie and common; but a ſure friend
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:2460:29"/>is tried both in matters of choiſeſt conſequence; &amp; of greateſt danger: In euerie ſocietie, ſome there are that will aduenture ſome part of their ſubſtance, and of their ſuperfluity and ſtore, to doe their diſtreſſed companion ſome little good. But a true &amp; a faithful friend reckeneth not of al his poſſeſſions, nor of al his goods, no he eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth not his owne libertie, nor his life; (if by the loſſe of them) he may preſerue and keepe his friend, whom he inwardly loueth, from like important harme, it therefore behooueth you much <hi>(My Sonne)</hi> that in the choiſe of thoſe you entertaine to be your friends, you doe obſerue (aboue other) principally theſe rules.</p>
            <p>Firſt of all,
<note place="margin">Rules touching friendſhip.</note> that your friends nature, and his quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, may in ſome proportion haue a ſimilitude, and a reſemblance with your owne, for in thoſe two reſpects, ſo neere ſhould your friend be, like vnto your ſelfe, that when you looke on him, you muſt ſuppoſe and thinke, that his picture is your owne, his will muſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree with yours,
<note place="margin">One minde be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt friends.</note> and yours muſt conſent with his, what he doth loath, you muſt refuſe, and what he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighteth in, you muſt eſpecially embrace; except rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon doe perſwade you otherwiſe, and that thereby you can reclaime him from his error, for in all precepts, and in all rules, concerning the chooſing, and the vſing of a faithfull friend, all things muſt be ſeaſoned with <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,</hi> with <hi>wiſedome,</hi> and with <hi>vertue,</hi> for without them there muſt bee no friendſhip, nor any yeelding to the affections, inclinations, or motions of your friend. Secondly your friend may not conueniently be your ſuperior:
<note place="margin">Equalitie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong friends.</note> except he (being ſo) will be contented, and pleaſed (for friendſhips ſake) to make you his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion, and will repute you to be his equall. <hi>Amicitia
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:2460:29"/>enim aut pares facit, vel quaerit.</hi> Except it be among e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quals (either indeede, or elſe by mutuall acceptation) there is no true and faithfull friendſhip.</p>
            <p>Thirdly when you haue gotten a faithfull friend (which is as rare a noueltie,
<note place="margin">No Ielouſie in frendſhip.</note> as a blacke ſwan) you muſt together (with him) haue but one heart in two bodies, and you may not ſuſpect him to be vnconſtant, faithles, or vntrue, for ſuch hateful ielouſie deſtroyeth frie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dſhip.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Et ſolem videtur è Mundo tollere, qui tollit Amicitiam.</l>
               <l>He ſeemes of Sunne the heauens to depriue,</l>
               <l>That from the world true friendſhip ſeekes to driue.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Fourthly, you muſt not ſuffer your friend to flatter you: <hi>Nam nulla eſt in Amicitia peſtis grauior quam a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulatio,</hi> There is not a greater enemie vnto friendſhip,
<note place="margin">No flatterie in friendſhip.</note> then baſe and ſeruile flatterie.</p>
            <p>For a flatterer ſeemeth to faune vpon his friend when (for his priuate commoditie and gaine) he could bee contented to ſpoile him, if he might.
<note place="margin">Flatterie.</note> As a Bee hath hony in his mouth, but ſtingeth with his taile: So a flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terer ſpeaketh ſmoothly when miſchief is lurking in his double heart. He beareth water in one hand, and carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth fire in the other, he hath roſes in his mouth, and thornes and prickles in his breaſt.</p>
            <p>He frameth his glozing ſpeeches, to ſerue his owne turne, without regard whether his wordes bee true or falſe.</p>
            <p>He maketh an <hi>Elephant</hi> of a Flie, and his tongue wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vpon vntrueth, as a Noble mans horſe doth for his maiſter at the Court gates. His flatterie hurteth more then a mad dog, which biteth cruelly, and when he ſpeaketh faireſt, then is there greateſt cauſe of feare.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Saepe latet molli coluber ſub graminis vmbra:</l>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:2460:30"/>
               <l>In greeneſt graſſe Miſchiefe to worke,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mantuan.</hi> 138.</note>
               </l>
               <l>A ſtinging Serpent oft doth lurke.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Kings by ſuch Traitors are ſooner ſupplanted, then ſubdued by their open enemies, and inferior perſons are more often beguiled by ſweete, then by bitter wordes.</p>
            <p>A flattering frend will ſalute you with his hat,
<note place="margin">Theatrum Mundi.</note> when his hart deuiſeth, how he may depriue you of your head. Such a flatterer,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sledan de quatuor Imper</hi> 32.</note> and ſuch a fained friend was <hi>Cicero</hi> who (whilſt he followed <hi>Pompey</hi> in his ſucceſful warres) diſdainfully depraued <hi>Caeſar,</hi> to magnifie and to extoll <hi>Pompeyes</hi> honor. But when <hi>Caeſar</hi> had ſubdued <hi>Pompey,</hi> and compelled him by flight, to meete his owne death in <hi>Egypt,</hi> he the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> exalted <hi>Caeſars</hi> name aboue the moone. But aſſoone as <hi>Caeſar</hi> was murdred by <hi>Brutus</hi> and <hi>Caſſius</hi> in the Senate houſe, he publikely ſcoffed at him, and reuiled him as the capitall enemie, and arch-traitor both to the people, and to Rome it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>As it is an vnworthy thing, that a man ſhould liue onely to pleaſe himſelfe: ſo is it hatefull vnto honeſt men, that any man ſhould liue to be pleaſing by his flatterie vnto others.</p>
            <p>Such flattering friends <hi>Alphonſus</hi> King of <hi>Aragon</hi> could not endure, who being aſked, <hi>qui fuerunt ſibi con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiliarij fideliſſimi,</hi> who were his moſt faithfull friends and counſellers? made this anſwer, <hi>Mortui ſcilicet libri, qui non adulantur:</hi> Such as are <hi>Dead</hi> (quoth he) meaning thereby his bookes, who would not flatter him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tiberius</hi> would not permit a knowne flatterer to call him King, or Emperour. And <hi>Caligula,</hi> not as a Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, though he were a hatefull one; but as an Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour regardfull to preſerue his ſtate, and perſon from
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:2460:30"/>ruine, and from deſtruction, commanded that all his courtiers and attendants, which were addicted to ſeruile flatterie, ſhould be put to death.</p>
            <p>By daily experience we are taught, that <hi>Adulatores fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unt ex lingua et ventre.</hi> flatterers are compoſed onely of a tongue to ſpeake ſmoothly, and of a belly, which muſt be pampered, and ſtuffed vp with ſuch viands and coſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dainties, as may be catered, and prouided by the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor of the tongue.</p>
            <p>Now as you may not admit him to be your friend,
<note place="margin">No diſſimu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation in frendſhip.</note> that flattereth you, ſo muſt you be carefull to foreſee, that your ſelfe do not diſſemble with your friend.</p>
            <p>For a diſſembler offendeth not through <hi>Ignorance</hi> againſt his will, but with a reſolued purpoſe to cozen,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luther ſuper Galath.</hi> 190.</note> and to deceiue, and vnder a falſe pretence of honeſtie, and of trueth, he ſhadoweth groſſe hypocriſie. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by hee winneth oportunitie, to put in practiſe (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſuſpition, or ielouſie) ſuch villanies, as haue beene contriued in his double heart. Such a diſſembler was <hi>Lyſander,</hi> who purpoſing to make hauocke of the <hi>Graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Plutarch in vita Lyſandri.</hi> 453.</note> willed them to preſerue their liues within the Cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of <hi>Athens,</hi> for that he intended to waſte the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries abroade, and would deſtroy all ſuch as he found in them: by meanes whereof, multitudes of credulous people (beleeuing that he purpoſed to ſhew fauour vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that Cittie, and vnto all ſuch as ſhould be therein) repaired thither. But forthwith he gyrded them round about with his <hi>Lacedemonian</hi> armie, and with a merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe Siege, ſuffering none to iſſue forth, by reaſon whereof greater numbers of the <hi>Athenians</hi> were more quickly waſted, and conſumed by <hi>Mortalitie,</hi> and <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi> then all his forces could in a longer time haue
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:2460:31"/>deuoured with their ſwords,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>pag.</hi> 449.</note> whereat he boaſted ſcof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fingly, and ſaid: That when a Lions skinne would not ſerue the turne, a Foxes muſt, ſuch a fained, and ſuch a diſſembling friend, is worſe then an open enemie, for as <hi>Ioſephus</hi> doth affirme,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Antiq. Judaeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum. lib.</hi> 6.</note> in the profeſſed maliciouſneſſe of an enemie, a man findeth the one halfe of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, but the ſecret enuie of a diſſembling friend cannot be quickly diſcouered, or auoided.</p>
            <p>Such a fained friend (holding with the haire,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bercho Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct. Moral.</hi> 123.</note> yet run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning with the hound) is fitly compared to a comet, which by her lucid light ſeemeth to bee a planet, but being none, is ſoone extinguiſhed and vaniſhed quite away.</p>
            <p>Such a friend (like to the ſummers ſwallow) affordeth his helping preſence, in the hot ſun-ſhine of proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, but betaketh himſelfe to a wilfull exile, and baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, when aduerſe fortunes do enforce his friend to deplore his caſe, and to implore his helpe.</p>
            <p>Such a frend (to fit his owne purpoſe, and to ſerue his owne turne) inclineth his vnſetled affections to all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of purpoſes whatſoeuer. As a ducke doth hers when (for foode and ſuſtenance) ſhe goeth on the land with beaſts, and ſwimmeth in the water with fiſhes, and fli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in the aire with birds.</p>
            <p>A diſſembling friend in the outward ſhew is faire, ſpotleſſe, and without any blemiſh, like vnto a ſwanne, but his inward parts do giue ſmal contentme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, either in taſte or in colour, that is to ſay, in honeſty, or in loue. A ſhadow plainly repreſenteth the ſhape of the body of a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> yet it altogether wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teth ſubſtance, &amp; a diſſembling friend ſeemeth to be ſuch a one as wil be ready, and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry forward to performe all neceſſarie and fitting ſerui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:2460:31"/>to his frend, but his diſſembling and double heart will not permit him, when times and occaſions doe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, to doe him any good,
<note place="margin">Sledan de quatuor Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perijs.</note> ſuch a diſſembling friend was <hi>Ptolomey, Dioniſius</hi> king of Egipt vnto <hi>Pompey</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing vnto him many gracious fauours, when he fled for ſuccour to him, but to gaine <hi>Caeſars</hi> loue, &amp; fauour, he ſecretly depriued <hi>Pompey</hi> of his life.</p>
            <p>A diſſembling friend looketh vpon his friend (as <hi>Lea</hi> did) with a ſquint eye, and ſeemeth to be ſuch a one, as indeede he is not, for as a barge-man turning his face one way, roweth another, ſo a diſſembling friend, hath honie in his mouth, but poyſon is in his heart.</p>
            <p>He is like vnto the glow-worme, which in the darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the night, ſeemeth to be fire, but is none, for hee promiſeth faith and fidelitie, when as his beſt thoughts are fraughted with hypocriſie, and al his ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations are contriuing how he may deceiue.</p>
            <p>Therefore this ſhort diſcourſe, which ſo plainly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribeth the folly, and the vanitie of ſuch falſe and fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned friends (<hi>My ſonne</hi>) beware, beware, I ſay, that you diſſemble not with your friend, for no diſſembler lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth conſtantly, and where there is no conſtant loue, there true and faithful friendſhip can take no place, nor beare ſway.</p>
            <p>And when you haue enricht your ſelfe with ſo ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimable a treaſure, as faithfull and honeſt friends are,
<note place="margin">Friends 'muſt not be forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fling faults.</note> then be you right well aduiſed, that you take not hold vpon ſmall and trifling occaſions, to eſtrange your ſelfe from them, but let this reſolution abide and dwell with you: <hi>That ſuch as loue you as their friend, cannot abuſe you as their foe: and that ſuch as doe affect you in their hearts will not willingly offend you with their tongues, nor hurt you
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:2460:32"/>with their hands, and that though by meanes of vnaduiſed raſhnes, they happen to doe you ſome wrong, yet they will aduiſedly reforme, and amend their faults, Humanum eſt er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rare:</hi> it is an incident to the frailty of man, ſometimes to ſpeake, and ſome times to doe amiſſe.</p>
            <p>A ſkilfull <hi>Hunter</hi> wil not put away a cunning <hi>Hounde,</hi> becauſe he hath a little faulted in hunting, and ſtraied from the game. A ſtrong ſhip is not by and by forſaken and lodged in her dock, becauſe now and then ſhe is ſearched, and pierced with ſome leake.</p>
            <p>A good horſe is not ſuddenly caſt off, becauſe he hath once or twiſe by a misfortune ſtumbled, and fallen to the ground.</p>
            <p>Nor may a faithfull friend be abandoned, though ſome times his actions be not in all points anſwerable to our wils.</p>
            <p>Neither muſt you aſſociate to your ſelfe <hi>good frends,</hi>
               <note place="margin">We muſt not get friends to gaine by them.</note> in hope to make ſome profit and gaine by them, for vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a faithfull friend, it is much better to giue, then to receiue, or to take any thing away from him, and in your bounty to your faithful friend, you ought to imitate the <hi>Fields,</hi> who do reſtore to the husbandman, a greater en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of benefit,
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Timothy. cap.</hi> 6. <hi>v.</hi> 10.</note> then they did receiue from him. <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetouſneſſe ſaith S. Paul, is the roote of all euill,</hi> but that <hi>Couetouſneſſe,</hi> which tempteth a man not to loue his friend, but for gaine and profit ſake, is the worſt fruite that proceedeth from a <hi>Couetous</hi> minde.</p>
            <p>No man will be willing by ſiniſter meanes to deceiue himſelfe of his owne goods, a mans friend is himſelfe, therefore he that deceitfully taketh any thing from his friend, vnwiſely taketh it from himſelfe.</p>
            <p>As vertue is to be loued, onely becauſe ſhe is vertue,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:2460:32"/>and for her owneſake, ſo a faithfull friend muſt be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected, onely for his owne ſake, and becauſe he is your worthy friend. Hence it is, as you may reade, that many haue beene willing to haue died, yea that ſome of them haue died to ſaue their frie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dsfro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the like peril &amp; miſchif.</p>
            <p>Their names are better knowne, then their examples practized: this therefore ſhall now ſuffice to informe you, that it is much better to enioy a true and faithfull friend, then to poſſeſſe much gold.</p>
            <p>Now though your frie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d be more then a principal part,
<note place="margin">Reueale not all ſecrets to your frend.</note> or member of your ſelfe, yet do I counſel you to retaine your cheifeſt ſecrets of choiceſt importance toyour ſelf.</p>
            <p>For vnto him you doe commit your libertie, and your fortunes, vnto whom you doe reueale ſuch counſels, and ſuch ſecrets.</p>
            <p>An earth-quake, is able to diſplace and to remooue the foundations of the ſtrongeſt Citties, frends are not ſo ſurely grounded &amp; founded, as Citties are, therefore leſſer cauſes then ſuch as bee miraculous, may make your friend to be your foe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> no mans iudgement is ſo infallible, that he cannot be deceiued in chooſing of his friend, his owne integrity is no ſufficient warrant for another mans fidelitie and loue.</p>
            <p>A good touchſtone trieth baſe copper from good and perfect gold, but an honeſt mind cannot ſo plainly diſcouer the inward intentions of anothers heart.</p>
            <p>One wiſe man may paſſe his cenſure, and ſentence of anothers wit, if he fill his hearers eare with ſharpe and pleaſant conceits, ſauoring of diſcretion, and of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, but whether, or no, that wit be matcht with an honeſt heart, he knoweth not, becauſe honeſtie conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth as much in the inward thoughts, as in the outward
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:2460:33"/>words or deedes. Seeing then, that to chuſe a friend which ſhall be both honeſt and faithfull, there is ſuch difficulty; nay ſeeing it is almoſt impoſſible (<hi>My Sonne</hi>) let it ſuffice you, to loue your choſen friend with your hart for his owne ſake, whilſt in proofe, you find him to be honeſt, but reueale not vnto him, your chiefeſt ſecrets, nor your counſels of greateſt moment and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance, leaſt if (in the end) he prouing to be vnfaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, you be enforced (but too too late) to repent your vnwiſe, and credulous folly.</p>
            <p>The next thing,
<note place="margin">Honeſtie and whordome.</note> which (with more then ordinarie affection, and vehement perſwaſions) I aduiſe, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire you to embrace, is <hi>Honeſtie</hi> of life, the ſame being a gemme of ſo rare, &amp; ſo in eſtimable a price, thatnone but ſuch as are aſſiſted by God, can purchaſe her. An ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt life maketh a mans preſence to be both louely, and comely, as women are more amiable, when they haue neatly attired themſelues in their looking-glaſſes. <hi>S. Paul</hi> affirmeth:
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.</note> 
               <hi>That our bodies are the temples of the holy Ghoſt,</hi> and thereupon he demaundeth this queſtion in ſome ſort by way of admiration, and of wonder, ſhall we then make them the members of an <hi>Harlot?</hi> God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid.</p>
            <p>To liue well and to enioy a bleſſed and a happie life, is nothing elſe but to liue honeſtly, for without honeſtie all our liues are polluted and defiled, as ſtreames of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter muſt be corrupted, if the ſprings, from which they doe deſcend, be filthy and vncleane.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Salomon,</hi> (by too much experience) was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed, that by his wanton conuerſation with lewd &amp; ſtrong women, he had offended the maieſtie of his God, (partly by way of repentance for that ſinne, and partly
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:2460:33"/>to admoniſh others to abhorre their ſocietie, and allu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring companie, he could then-ſay.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A VVhore forſaketh the guide of her youth (that is,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prou.</hi> 2.</note> her Huſband) and forgetteth the couenant of her God) that is, her ſolemne vow of honeſtie which ſhe made in the congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion when ſhe was maried, and then (with a ſurely) he was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to affirme, that her houſe tendeth to death, and her pathes vnto the dead, that all ſuch as goe vnto her, doe not returne againe, neither take they hold of the waie of life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Then could he ſay,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prou.</hi> 6.</note> that the lippes of a ſtrange woman drop as an hony-combe, and that her mouth is more ſoft then oile. But the end of her is bitter as wormewood, and ſharpe as a two edged ſword, that her feete goe downe to death, and that her ſteps take hold of hell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then could he giue to another this aduice. <hi>Keepe thee from the wicked woman,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pro.</hi> 6.</note> and from the flatterie of the tongue of a ſtrange woman, deſire not her beautie in thine h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>art, neither let her take thee with her eye-lids for by meanes of a whoriſh woman a man is brought to a morſell of bread, can a man (faith he) take fire in his boſome and his cloathes not burne? or can a man goe vpon coales, &amp; his feete not be burnt?</hi> So he that goeth into his neighbours wife, ſhall not be innocent, he that committeth adulterie with a woman, is deſtitute of vnderſtanding, he that doth it deſtroyeth his owne ſoule, he ſhall finde a wound, and diſhonour, and his reproach ſhall neuer be put away.</p>
            <p>We may further reade in thoſe his prouerbs:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prou.</hi> 7.</note> 
               <hi>That he that followeth the ſtraight waies of an harlot, is as an oxe that goeth to the ſlaughter, and as a foole to the ſtocks to be cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected, that her houſe is the way vnto the graue, which go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth downe to the chambers of death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That the mouth of a ſtrange woman is as a deepe pit,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prou.</hi> 22.</note> and that he with whom the Lord is angrie, ſhall fall therein, that
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:2460:34"/>a whore is a deepe ditch,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prou.</hi> 23. <hi>Prou.</hi> 26. <hi>Prou.</hi> 36.</note> and a ſtrange woman is as a narrow pit, that he who vſeth harlots, waſteth his (ubſtance, and ſhould not therefore giue his ſtrength vnto women.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By all which deſcriptions, caueats and admonitions, that prudent and beſt experimented king diſcouereth plainly, and to excellent purpoſe, the vgly and loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome ſhapes of thoſe beaſtly and filthy monſters, and endeuoreth to make them (as indeede they ought to be) hatefull and deformed, both in the eyes, and alſo in the hearts of vertuous, and of honeſt men.</p>
            <p>You may alſo reade in the holy ſcriptures (all which were publiſhed for our learning,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 23.</note> and for our inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that <hi>the price of a dogge: and the price of an harlot, were reckoned and accompted to be one.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Becauſe as a dogge fawneth vpon euery paſſer by, ſo a harlot proſtituteth her ſelfe impudently to euerie man that will entertaine her. When <hi>Painters</hi> by their art, and by their skil doe draw the portracture of <hi>Venus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Imago Deo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.</hi> 343.</note> that laſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciuious wanton, and <hi>Goddeſſe</hi> (as ſhe was termed) of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſt and diſhoneſt loue, they (ſometimes) doe leaue her naked, whereby is ſignified, that ſuch as doe plunge themſelues in the vanitie of her lewd follies, are naked and depriued of all grace and goodneſſe, and of all ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous qualities whatſoeuer.</p>
            <p>And ſometimes they paint her ſwimming in a quiet and in a calme ſea,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dewtr.</hi> 23.</note> noting thereby, that ſuch as do wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonly ſolace themſelues in the ſugred delights of a laſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uious and a whoriſh life, are ſubiect, and in great perill (yea in a moment, and in the middeſt of their ſecuritie and diſhoneſt life) to be ouerwhelmed with deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as a quiet and a peaceable ſea, is ſuddenly troubled withſtormes and with tempeſtuous windes.</p>
            <pb n="55" facs="tcp:2460:34"/>
            <p>The end of a laſciuious man, is ſeldome or neuer com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable and good.</p>
            <p>He that ſaileth in <hi>Cupids</hi> ſhip, ſhall hardly (if euer) arriue into the hauen, or port of godlineſſe and of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue</p>
            <p>Many men haue receiued their deſerued praiſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they haue hated vncleaneneſſe and wanton luſt, but the beaſtly vſe, and wicked practiſe thereof neuer yet made any man to attaine vnto true worſhip, or true honor.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>King Dauid (if he had not throughly repented for that ſin) had beene ſhut,
<note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 12. <hi>v.</hi> 13.</note> and pierced through with the firie dart of Gods vengeance, and of his wrath, the wicked Iudges which impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, and lewdly aſſaulted Suſannas chaſtitie (failing of their vngodly purpoſe, and yet falſly accuſing and condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning her were (by the prophet Daniel) found to be guilty of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious villany and iniuſtice, and were (according to their merits &amp; deſerts) ſtoned to death, in the ſight of all the people.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Nomb.</hi> 25.2.8.9.</note> The Iſraelites in the wilderneſſe committed whoredome, and were for the ſame ſinne plagued grieuouſly with the peſtilence, and with the ſword.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A mong the <hi>decemuiri</hi> in Rome <hi>Appius Claudius</hi> ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſhed <hi>Vergina</hi> the daughter of <hi>Verginius</hi> a worthy Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, whereupon he was depriued of his office,
<note place="margin">Plutarch.</note> and that authority and dignitie was (for a time) aboliſhed, and taken quite away.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Sextus Tarquinius</hi> the wicked ſon of as bad a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hurim Sche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dell.</hi> 65.</note> 
               <hi>Tarquinius Superbus</hi> (the laſt of the Roman Kings) by like rage and violence,
<note place="margin">Sledan de quatuor Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perijs.</note> rauiſhed <hi>Lucretia</hi> the wife of Noble <hi>Collatinus,</hi> for which offence, himſelfe, his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and all their name were baniſhed from <hi>Rome,</hi> and the kingly gouernment (which had continued there vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:2460:35"/>ſeuen Kings for the ſpace of 244. yeares) was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſhed, and the Conſulſhip of two Senators was eſtabliſhed in ſteede thereof.</p>
            <p>The wanton diſhoneſtie of <hi>Paris</hi> king <hi>Priams</hi> ſonne,
<note place="margin">Dares Phrigius</note> with faire <hi>Helena,</hi> the wife of <hi>Agamemnon,</hi> occaſioned the ruine and the deſtruction of the famous, and moſt renowned Cittie of <hi>Troy,</hi> and the deaths of many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of Princes, and of valiant men of warre. <hi>Antonies</hi> wanton loue with <hi>Cleopatra</hi> was the ruine of them both.</p>
            <p>The inordinate affection, which king <hi>Demetrius</hi> bare vnto his concubines,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Plutarch in vita Demetrij.</hi> 896.</note> and to his curtezans, made him to leuie a great taxe of two hundred and fiftie talents, and which hee beſtowed vpon one of thoſe wanton minions, to prouide her ſope, by meanes whereof he loſt the dutifull affections of his ſubiects, and was reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to be but a wantonking.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Idem fo.</hi> 38.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rodorick,</hi> ſometimes king of Spaine, filthily rauiſhed <hi>Cuba,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Felicitie of man. 48.</note> the daughter of the Earle of <hi>Cepta,</hi> for which cauſe her father reuolted to the Mores, and incited them to inuade Spaine, which they did, and with his ſuccor and aſſiſtance became Lords ouer <hi>Rodoricke,</hi> and ſubdued to their gouernment all his countries.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tymolea</hi> a renowned and chaſt Ladie among the <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bans</hi> (at the taking of that City) was villanouſly rauiſhed by a ſouldier,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Plutarch in vita Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dri. pag.</hi> 678.</note> who (hauing done to her that intolerable iniurie and wrong) demaunded of her, where her trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure was? who made anſwere that ſhe had caſt it into a well in the backe moſt part of all her houſe to preſerue it, but whilſt the ſouldier (being greedy to haue the ſpoile of them) looked narrowly into the well, the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowred Ladie (to reuenge her ſelfe) ſtanding cloſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:2460:35"/>him, tooke vp his legges and threw him headlong into the well, and forthwith ſtoned him to death.</p>
            <p>To abandon this beaſtly and loathſome ſinne from the Romans, <hi>Marcellus</hi> (hauing ſubdued the <hi>Siracuſans</hi>) placed the <hi>Temple</hi> of <hi>Venus</hi> at his returne without the Gates of <hi>Rome.</hi> Signifying thereby, that all laſciuious wantons ought to bee baniſhed out of that renowned and faire Cittie.</p>
            <p>Yea ſo ielous was <hi>Cato Cenſorius</hi> of any manner of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample that might intice others to wantonneſſe and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to diſhoneſtie of life,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Plutarch in vita Mar: Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to. pag.</hi> 356.</note> that he depoſed <hi>Manlius</hi> from his <hi>Senatorſhip</hi> in <hi>Rome,</hi> onely for that in the preſence of his daughter he had kiſſed his owne wife.</p>
            <p>Much deceiued therefore was <hi>Ariſtippus</hi> the <hi>Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Niphus de pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chre et amore.</hi> 145.</note> who (like vnto an Epicure) placed the <hi>Summum bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num,</hi> and chiefeſt happineſſe and felicitie of man, in the actuall exerciſe of laſciuious, and of wanton luſt.</p>
            <p>There is no earthly ſolace, ioy, or comfort, that can be compared to the peace, and to the tranquilitie of a quiet conſcience, neither is any mans conſcience more ioyfull or more quiet then his, who was neuer in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected, or polluted with this ſinne.</p>
            <p>It was <hi>Eſaus</hi> prophaneneſſe,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 25.</note> that made him to ſell his birth-right, and his inheritance for a meſſe of pottage.</p>
            <p>And it is a laſciuious mans fooliſhneſſe, and his fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that for a ſhort fleſhly delight, and a little vaine, and filthy pleaſure, he will abandon the tranquilitie, and the peace of his immortall ſoule.</p>
            <p>Therefore (my ſonne) expoſe not the wife of your youth (I meane your virgin chaſtitie) to the impudent and whoriſh enticements of a ſhameleſſe harlot.</p>
            <p>For all her pleaſures are but paine, all her ioyes are
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:2460:36"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:2460:36"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:2460:37"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:2460:37"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:2460:38"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:2460:38"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:2460:39"/>without true mirth, all her comforts are but ſorrowes, and her craftie baites do kill, as the fiſhers doe. Keepe her therefore from you, as enemies are carefully de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barred from entring into a beſieged Cittie, and let her not come neere you, leaſt, whilſt you ſleepe in her lappe, ſhe bereaue you of all godlineſſe and vertue,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iudges.</hi> 16.</note> as <hi>Dalila</hi> did <hi>Sampſon</hi> of his haires, in which his ſtrength did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Leaue her as the Iſraelites did the land of Egipt,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 17.3.</note> but neuer deſire, nor long (as they did) to returne to her againe.</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member how temperate and chaſt <hi>Alexander</hi> the great, ſometimes was,
<note place="margin">Plutarch in vita Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dri.</note> who neuer touched the wife, nor <hi>daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> of <hi>Darius,</hi> albeit, that (as vnto a conquerer) they were or might haue beene made ſubiect to his luſt. And call to minde his wonderfull virtue, when as he chaſtly paſſed by al the faireſt women, and maidens of the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians (whom he had vanquiſhed) looking vpon them onely, as men vſe to looke vpon images, and vpon pic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, which haue no life.</p>
            <p>And thinke vpon the modeſt chaſtitie,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Idem in vita Scip Affric. pag.</hi> 1088.</note> and much commended honeſtie of <hi>Scipio Affricanus,</hi> vnto whom (when he had taken new <hi>Carthage</hi> in <hi>Spaine</hi>) the faireſt, and the moſt beutifullladie of al his priſoners, being the young wife of <hi>Luceius</hi> the prince of the <hi>Celtiberians,</hi> was brought, that with her he might haue ſolaced himſelfe, after his turmoiles in thoſe warres, but preſeruing her honour, and her honeſtie, he reſtored her vntouched to her husband.
<note place="margin">God know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth al things.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And thinke not that any ſecret place can hide or co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer him from the preſence of <hi>almightie God,</hi> that perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trateth that abhominable ſinne.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For God that faſhioneth mens hearts, knoweth all their
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:2460:39"/>warkes. He knoweth the ſecret thoughts of men,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſ.</hi> 33.15. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 44 21. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 94.9. God ſeeth all things. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 139.</note> and that they are but vaine. If his eyes ſaw vs, when we were without forme. And if our bones were not hidden from him, though we were made in a ſecret place, and fa ſhioned beneath in the earth, ſhall he not then behold vs, being made and faſhioned in our full and perfect ſhapes? And ſhall he not then diſcouer our nakedneſſe, when ſinfully wee doe pollute our ſelues, and defile our members with harlots, and with whores?
<note place="margin">God heareth all things. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 194.</note> Hath God (which is omnipotent, and onely wiſe) planted the eare? and ſhall not he heare? Hath he formed the eye, and ſhall not he himſelfe ſee? Are not all our ſinnes, and all our tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions written and recorded in his booke? yea verily.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſ.</hi> 1.6.</note> The Lord knoweth the way of the righteous,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſ.</hi> 139. <hi>Eccles.</hi> 12.</note> and the way of the wicked ſhall periſh. There is not a word in our tongue, but he knoweth it, yea, God will bring euerie worke vnto iudgement with euery ſecret thing, whether it be good or euill.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sith then God ſeeth and heareth, &amp; knoweth al things, though they be ſpoken or contriued, or committed, and done in the moſt ſecret corners of the houſe. If light and darkeneſſe be vnto him alike, and ſeeing that no euill can dwell with him, beware, beware (I ſay) of this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouring and deadly ſin of damnable whoredome, the guilt whereof will cleaue as faſt to the offenders conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and to his ſoule,
<note place="margin">2. <hi>Reg.</hi> 5.</note> 
               <hi>as Naamans leproſie did vnto Geha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zies fleſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Runne from her therefore, as from a Lion, and from a Beare, for when ſhe fawneth and flattereth moſt, ſhee deſtroieth ſooneſt, as doth the <hi>Crocadile,</hi> and ſhe leaueth for an enheritance for her children, ſhame to diſgrace them, pouertie to afflict them, and Gods eternall an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and vengeance to torment and plague them in the world to come. <hi>Corrumpunt bonos mores colloquia praua,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:2460:40"/>Euill words doe corrupt good manners.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore be you well aduiſed,
<note place="margin">Modeſt talking.</note> and very warie, that your talke and communication be not wanton, laſciui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, or vncomely, and carefully auoide the company of all looſe, and of all ſuſpected women, and then (if dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly you implore Gods fauour and his grace, for your aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance and helpe) you ſhall neuer be polluted nor defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with this filthie loathſome and beaſtly ſinne of <hi>whor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.6.19.</note> but you ſhall preſerue your bodie ſpotleſſe, as the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the holy Ghoſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And further (to the end that a luxurious vnchaſt life may not defile you) you muſt eſpecially bee carefull,
<note place="margin">Idleneſſe.</note> that idleneſſe be auoided, and (like vnto an enemie) put to flight.</p>
            <p>For diſhoneſtie waiteth vpon idleneſſe, as the eyes of a ſeruant do vpon the hands of her miſtreſſe.</p>
            <p>It followeth idleneſſe as a ſhadow doth the bodie, but if idleneſſe be exiled, then luſt groweth faint, as a ſicke patient doth, when by his phiſitian hee is depriued of much bloud.</p>
            <p>Hence it is,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>arland.</hi>
               </note> that learned <hi>Barlandus</hi> in his <hi>Aphoriſmes</hi> ſaith thus: <hi>Nulla re alia facilius obruuntur libidinis incita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menta, quam labore.</hi> The allurements of <hi>Venus,</hi> and the temptations of filthie luſt, and of diſhoneſtie, are not by any waies or meanes ſooner or better ſhaken off, then by labour, by trauell and by paine. <hi>Otiaſi tollas periere eupidinis arcus.</hi> Luſt hath no commaund, where idleneſſe beares no ſway.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Quaeritur Aegiſtus,
<note place="margin">Onidius.</note> quare ſit factus adulter?</l>
               <l>In promptu cauſa eſt, deſidioſus erat.</l>
               <l>Aegiſtus ſoone became adulterate,</l>
               <l>When he his life to ſloath did dedicate.</l>
            </q>
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:2460:40"/>
            <p>The end of ſuch men is neuer good, who bequeath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and (as it were) ſacrificing their whole time vnto idleneſſe and pleaſure, can do no manner of good.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Numa Pompilius</hi> to auoide ſloth and idleneſſe in Rome, deuided the whole Cittie into ſeueral parts, quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring them moſt fittingly for euery ſeuerall myſterie,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Plutarch in vita Numa Pompily.</hi> 72.</note> and trade.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Pericles</hi> to auoide that enormious ſinne (as the roote and mother of many other vices &amp; ſins, ſent great numbers of ſloathfull people, into <hi>Cheroneſa,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Idem in vita Periclis pag.</hi> 163.</note> and into the Ilands of <hi>Napos,</hi> of <hi>Andros,</hi> and into many other places in <hi>Greece,</hi> there to be trained vp in honeſt myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and trades. <hi>Cymon</hi> (to the end that the Souldiers of <hi>Athens,</hi> ſhould not be infeebled by meanes of idleneſſe and luxurie) compelled them in times of greateſt peace to weare their armor,
<note place="margin">Idem in vita. Cimon.</note> and to carrie their weapons daily in their hands. By meanes whereof they not onely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued good and perfit ſoldiers, but were maruellouſly feared by their enemies.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Licurgus</hi> made a law, that no childe among the <hi>Spar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans</hi> ſhould be brought vpin idlenes, nor be ſuffered loi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tringly to ſpend his time,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Idem in vita Licurgi.</hi> 52.</note> but ſhould be inſtructed in ſome good thing or other, by meanes wherof he might be the more capable (as he encreaſed in yeares) to bee imploied in ſome one or other profitable art and trade.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tamberlan,</hi> the victorious <hi>Parthian</hi> (who ſcourged <hi>Baiazet,</hi> the great <hi>Emperor</hi> of the <hi>Turkes,</hi> with the fierce furie of his reuenging hand, ſlaying,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Harim Shed of</hi> 236.</note> and killing in one battaile more then two hundred thouſand of his men, and carrying <hi>Baiezet</hi> himſelfe with him as a ſlaue, and
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:2460:41"/>as the <hi>Trophey</hi> of his victories in a golden <hi>Cage</hi>) permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted no man in his armie to be idle, by meanes whereof his campe in the field was ruled and gouerned as a well ordered Cittie, wherein euerie man is ouerviewed and hardly kept to the exerciſing of his miſterie and trade: from idleneſſe enſueth no good effect, <hi>Praeſtat otioſum eſſe, quam nihil agere,</hi> it is much better to picke ſtrawes then (being idle) to doe nothing at all. Of that opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was <hi>Mantuan</hi> when he ſaid, <hi>Otia damnantur quae mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta negotia tractant, that ſloathfull and that lazieidleneſſe, is moſt of all to be condemned, which imployeth her ſelfe vnto no labour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qui molam fugit, fugitfarinam, he that ſcorneth to goe vnto the mill, muſt eate nobread.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Catt</hi> deſerueth not to eate <hi>Fiſh,</hi> which (being o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer curious and daintie of her labour) refuſeth to wett her foote.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hermanus Heſſus.</hi> 73.</note> As horſes (for our commoditie and profit) are laboured almoſt euerie day, ſo muſt we be buſied al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies, in one or another thing which is good.</p>
            <p>For if a mans minde be made dul and heauie through idleneſſe and ſloath, he will then be altogether vnfit for any worthie attempt, and ſeruice whatſoeuer.</p>
            <p>If after the creation of the world, God had firſt of all created man before any other of his creatures, then might he haue had ſome colourable excuſe, to haue ſpent his time in idleneſſe.</p>
            <p>But God created man, after he had created all his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther creatures, that he might forthwith bee imploi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and occupied in the workes of his creators hands.</p>
            <p>It is not lawful for any Scholler in a grammer ſchoole to ſit idle among his conſorts and companions, but he
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:2460:41"/>muſt imploy himſelfe to learne ſuch bookes, as by his maſter are appointed to his charge and taske.</p>
            <p>So when the great volume and booke of the world, and of all things which are therein, is ſpread and laid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad to each mans open view, none muſt be idle, but euery man muſt diligently imploy himſelfe in ſuch af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires and buſineſſe, as God (his maſter) hath commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to his care. <hi>A ſloathfull hand (ſaith Salomon) maketh poore, but the hand of the Diligent maketh rich.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prou.</hi> 10.4.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A ſloathfull man hideth his hand in his boſome,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prou.</hi> 19.24. <hi>Prou.</hi> 20.4.</note> and will not put it to his mouth againe, his puniſhment therefore is to begge in the ſummer, but nothing ſhall be giuen him becauſe he will not plough in the winter.</hi> When a man is idle, his minde is encombred with many variable cogitations, and ſundrie thoughts, but not with any which are ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous and good, if the aire and the ſea were not in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall motion, they would ſoone bee corrupted, and become noyſome in ſteede of being commodious, and helpefull for the life and vſe of man.</p>
            <p>The fieldes vnmanured will yeelde forth nothing but weedes, brambles and thornes, an oxe vnlabored is moſt vnfitting for the plough.</p>
            <p>A ſhip not vſed will ſooner moulder and rot away, then if ſhe were ſtill imployed to that end for which ſhe was made, and he that ſpendeth and paſſeth away his daies in Idlenes and in ſloath (forſaking labour and tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile and paine) becommeth vnapt and vnprepared for any good ſeruice and commendable action whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, and is thereby made more inclinable vnto luxurie, and to diſhoneſt luſt, then a proude man is vnto pride by gay and gariſh apparell, or then a couetous man is to his particular ſinne, by the abundant encreaſe of his
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:2460:42"/>ſiluer, and of his gold.</p>
            <p>Now as vncleaneſſe &amp; luſt are augmented by ſloth and idleneſſe,
<note place="margin">Niceneſſe, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queting and Feaſting.</note> ſo is it much prouoked by ſuperfluitie and exceſſe in diet, and by fooliſh feaſtings. <hi>Nam ſine Cerere et Baccho friget Venus,</hi> when the belly is ſtuffed vp and pampered with daintie meates and pleaſant drinks, then is the wit vnable to intertaine any ſharpe conceit, and the minde vntoward and vncapable of any vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous motion, or good conceit, <hi>Pinguis venter dormit libenter,</hi> the fulneſſe of the belly attacheth the whole bodie vnder the arreſt of idleneſſe and ſloth, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth it a priſoner to ignorance and to ſtupiditie, and to filthy and vngodly luſts, <hi>Pinguis venter non gigint tenuem ſenſum,</hi> and hence it is that both the body and the mind alſo being dull, heauie and ſluggiſh, with ſuperfluous feaſting and banqueting, the whole man it ſelfe will ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily be tempted with laſciuious and vnlawfull luſt.</p>
            <p>This poſition <hi>Darius</hi> approued to be true,
<note place="margin">Sledan de quatuor Jmper</note> when (to encreaſe his luſtfull appetite, and to enable himſelfe the more to performe ſuch wanton exerciſes, as with much exces he delighted in) he procured fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al forreine coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries (with vnualable expence and charge) the moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite and skilfull cookes and artizans, that did excell &amp; exceede others in deuiſing, compounding and mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſuch luſſhious and luxurious meates, drinkes, ſaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and ſuch like confections as extraordinarily would augment the ſuperfluous humor of his immodeſt appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite and luſtfull actions.</p>
            <p>The houſes of <hi>Marcus Antonius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Platarchs liues. pag.</hi> 956. <hi>pag.</hi> 534.</note> and of <hi>Lucullus</hi> (as <hi>Plutarch</hi> telleth vs) ſeemed to be the curious pallaces, and the luſtfull courts of wanton <hi>Venus,</hi> by reaſon of the rich furniture, veſſels of ſiluer and of golde, ſtate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:2460:42"/>plaies, ſweete muſicke, delicate paſteries, coſtly ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quets, rare deuices, and the exceſſiue aboundance of all things in them that might be pleaſing vnto any ſence.</p>
            <p>But becauſe thoſe vanities were allurements vnto luſt, the maiſters of thoſe ſuperfluities were reckoned to be enemies to the common wealth.</p>
            <p>More diſcrete and ſober was worthie <hi>Craſſas,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Plutarch in vita Craſſi. pag.</hi> 560.</note> who (albeit he were almoſt the richeſt Roman that liued in his time) yet would he be ſerued at his table with ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie and decent ſufficiencies, forbidding all exceſſe and coſtly diet, becauſe they incited and prouoked men to ſinne.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Idem in vita Lycurgi. pag.</hi> 52.</note>
            </p>
            <p>To baniſh all ſloath and voluptuouſneſſe out of <hi>Spar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta, Lycurgus</hi> baniſhed all banquetings and feaſts, and in Rome ſuch as vſed them,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Idem in vita. Quinti Flami nis. pag.</hi> 388.</note> were ſubiect to bee corrected by the Cenſor.</p>
            <p>But moſt of all is a man prouoked to luſt by drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, <hi>As Noah, and as Lot were.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 19: <hi>Gen.</hi> 9.</note> For drunkenneſſe (de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priuing a man of the true and perfit vſe of his reaſon) maketh him brutiſh as a beaſt, and conſequently a fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie proſecuter, and an intemperate actor of ſuch vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſt and vncleane ſuggeſtions, as whores and harlots doe contriue.</p>
            <p>Neither is whoredome the onely ſin, which as a vile effect proceedeth from drunkenneſſe, for it produceth other vices which are hatefull vnto God and to good men.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Alexander</hi> the great was drunken,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Quintus cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ius. lib.</hi> 8.</note> he cauſed <hi>Glytus</hi> his moſt familiar friend to be put to death, and burned the renowned and beautiful Cittie of <hi>Perſipolis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Idem. lib.</hi> 5.</note> to pleaſe and to content the whoriſh fancie of <hi>Thais</hi> his wanton and laſciuious queane.</p>
            <pb n="66" facs="tcp:2460:43"/>
            <p>For both which wicked facts being (though all too late better aduiſed) he fooliſhly repented, &amp; was ſorrie.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Ioſephus</hi> in his diſcourſe of the Iewiſh warres,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>De bello Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. lib.</hi> 1.</note> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porteth that when a king of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> named <hi>Alexander</hi> had in his conqueſts taken eight hundred <hi>Phariſies,</hi> as his priſoners, he cauſed them to be brought vpon the leades of his pallace, and in their preſence hee made a royall feaſt vnto his nobles, and (being drunke and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing himſelfe with ſuch mirth as was mercileſſe) he cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed all thoſe priſoners to be put to death, and merri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly laughed at their miſerie. The ancient prouerb telleth vs, that <hi>In vino eſt veritas,</hi> a drunkard can keepe no coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, but fooliſhly he reuealeth the inward counſels of his owne heart,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Garm. prou.</hi> 76.</note> 
               <hi>Aebrietas prodit quod amat cor ſiue quod odit.</hi> Hereof <hi>Ioſephus</hi> himſelfe had good experience, for ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing receaued by a bolde ſouldier, a ſmoothing letter from certaine perſons,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>In vita Ioſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phi.</hi> 542.</note> who (not louing him) had (he ſuppoſed) conſpired his deſtruction and his ouerthrow, and not preuailing (by any kind entreatie, or faire pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes) to vnderſtand the truth thereof from that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunted meſſenger, <hi>Ioſephus</hi> (pretending high fauour and extraordinarie loue to that ſouldier) inuited him for money to carrowſe in wine, which when he had im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moderatly done, then of his owne accord (without any requeſt or perſwaſion) he reuealed the treaſon &amp; the tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherie, whereby <hi>Ioſephus</hi> was ſufficiently armed, becauſe he was thereby warned to preuent, and to auoide it. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore, when men are drunken, they are for a time (in a manner) ſenceleſſe, and altogether vnable to eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chew their owne harmes.</p>
            <p>So was <hi>Holofernes,</hi> when <hi>Iudeth of Bethulia</hi> ſmote off his head with his owne ſword. So was <hi>Ariſtobulus</hi> a
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:2460:43"/>Iewiſh king, when (being drunken) he was poiſoned by the Ambaſſadors of <hi>Pompey.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Antiquit. Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daeorum lib.</hi> 14. <hi>pag.</hi> 359.</note>
            </p>
            <p>We may reade that <hi>Alexander</hi> the great at a ſolemne feaſt, which he made, propoſed for a reward,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Plutarch</hi> 708. <hi>in vita Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarch.</hi>
               </note> a golden crowne for him, who in quaffing could drinke moſt, and that one drunkard among the reſt woon it by drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (at the leaſt) foure gallons, but his vaine honor quickly faded, for hee died within foure daies after. A drunkard pleaſeth himſelfe beyond meaſure, to ſay thus: The earth drinketh vp the raine, the plants and trees doe drinke vp the moiſture of the earth, the fruites and flowers do drinke the iuice and ſappe of the plants and trees, wherefore ſeeing that all things doe drinke, I muſt and will drinke too. And thus doth the exceſſe of drinke beguile many, making them of men to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come monſters, and bereaueth them of the right vſe of their reaſon, and fooliſhly to diſplay the banner and colours of their owne ſhame.</p>
            <p>Little remembring that <hi>Anacharſis</hi> ſaid, that the firſt draught quenched thirſt, the ſecond noriſhed,
<note place="margin">Plutarch.</note> the third made men drunken, but the fourth made them ſtarke ſtaring madde.</p>
            <p>And little regarding to imitate the example of <hi>Cato</hi> Vtican, who vſed to drinke but once at one meale.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Idem in vita Cato, Vticam. pag.</hi> 770.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Or the ſaying of <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> who affirmed that three things changed mens natures, to witte lordſhip, women and wine, and little reſpecting,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 20.1.</note> and leſſe belieuing the true and the wiſe ſaying of King <hi>Salomon,</hi> that wine is a mocker, and that ſtrong drinke is raging, and that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer is deceiued thereby is not wiſe.</p>
            <p>Nor harkning to his aduice,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prom.</hi> 23.</note> when he counſelleth thus. Looke not vpon wine when it is red, and when
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:2460:44"/>it ſheweth his colour in the cup, or goeth downe plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſantly, for in the end it will bite as a ſerpent, and hurt like a cockatrice,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Grafton.</hi> 179.</note> and ſo did it hurt <hi>Hardicanutus</hi> king of the <hi>Saxons,</hi> within this land, who died whilſt he was carou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing immoderately at a mariage feaſt,
<note place="margin">Theat of Gods iudgm.</note> and ſo did it hurt <hi>Anacreon</hi> the drunken poet, who was choaked with the huske of a grape: whileſt he was ſwallowing downe his ſuperfluous boles of wine.</p>
            <p>To preuentſuch immoderate bibbing and ſwiniſh quaffing, the Grecians had Cenſours of their cups.</p>
            <p>And the Heluetians permitted not any man to drinke vnto his friend, leaſt ſome occaſion might be thereby of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fred to make men drunke.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Grafton.</hi> 156. Engliſh Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes againſt Drunkennes. 5 <hi>E.</hi> 6. c. 25. Ia. 1. c. 9. 4. Ia. c. 4.5.7. Iac. c. 10.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And Edgar king of the weſt <hi>Saxons</hi> commanded cups to bee made with pinnes and other markes, beyond which it was not lawfull for any man to drinke: farre dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent was that temperate and good kings practiſe, from that of the Emperour, <hi>Tiberius Claudius Nero,</hi> who (in a common skoffe for his exceſſiue drunkenneſſe) was nick-named and called <hi>Biberius Caldius Nero.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But leauing this odious and abhominable vice of drunkenneſſe (as vnworthie of further labor of my pen,
<note place="margin">Drunkennes.</note> I now doe aduiſe and counſell you to take a briefe ſuruey of temperance,
<note place="margin">Temperance.</note> as of a virtue, which farre excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the large limits of all praiſe, becauſe (with ſobrie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and contentedneſſe, ſhe will moderate and ſeaſon all your deedes and actions whatſoeuer.</p>
            <p>For if proſperitie doe aduaunce you to higher pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motions, dignities, offices, or fauours, then you can ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther well deſerue, or reaſonably expect, ſhee will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct you, not to waxe proude therewith, as the crowe did when ſhe was made faire with the plumes and fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:2460:44"/>of other birds, but was left naked and deformed when (for her prides ſake) euery bird had from her ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken her owne feathers.</p>
            <p>And if aduerſitie doe inuade you, ſhe will teach you (like a valiant ſouldier, and as a reſolued man of warre) to keepe her from you (with courage) at the ſpeares point.</p>
            <p>And if you cannot chooſe but become a priſoner vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to misfortunes, ſhe wil then inſtruct you with patience, to endure your paine, and ioyfully to hope for better happe, as <hi>Socrates</hi> did, who neuer altered his counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance for any chaunce, were it good or were it bad.</p>
            <p>If you be addicted to honeſt loue, ſhe will inable you (with ſound reaſon) to make your choiſe, and (for her virtues without wanton luſting) to loue her whom you haue choſen, and if you cannot obtaine ſuch fitting and ſuch pleaſing fauours, as you ſue for and doe deſerue, then ſhe will aduiſe you (with modeſt diſcretion) to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loue her from whom you can get no exchange of loue.</p>
            <p>And if you be iniuriouſly wro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged by a wrangling or by a froward <hi>Nabal,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 25.</note> by temperance you ſhal be perſwaded mildly to paſſe it ouer, and not to be thirſtie of reuenge, ſhe will perſwade you in your diet to auoide exceſſe for your healths ſake, as <hi>Lycurgus, Pompey,</hi> and as <hi>Craſſus</hi> did.</p>
            <p>In your apparel to be neither gariſh nor vile, but to be in the meane. In wealth not to be prodigall, nor in ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to be miſerable. In your pleaſures, not to be wanton nor Stoickly to paſſe by them, without taking notice of them. In great attempts not to bee fooliſhly deſperate, nor ſheepiſhly feareful.</p>
            <p>She teacheth vs (if we be beautifull) to thinke that we
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:2460:45"/>are but comely, and if we be not well fauoured. She then informeth vs that by our inward virtues, and good qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, we are ſhaped and framed according to the ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude of God himſelfe.</p>
            <p>If we be ſtrong and luſtie, ſhe telleth vs that we muſt make a gentle vſe thereof, becauſe we ſhall be weake.</p>
            <p>And if we be weake and feeble, ſhe then aduiſeth vs to hope for health and ſtrength againe: ſhe perſwadeth vs not to be angrie without a cauſe, and not to be furi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, though a iuſt occaſion be offered.</p>
            <p>If we be at libertie ſhe commandeth vs (for our owne good) to vſe it well. And if we be in captiuitie, ſhe nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tureth vs patiently to expect freedome and deliuerance from all thoſe troubles.</p>
            <p>When we haue ouercome others, ſhe teacheth vs to ouercome our ſelues (which is a greater victorie and conqueſt then all <hi>Alexanders</hi> were) for though he often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ouercame many nations, yet could he ſeldome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercome himſelfe.</p>
            <p>In puniſhing of offences, ſhe informeth vs not to bee too remiſſe nor too ſeuere.</p>
            <p>If any noble and worthie act be by vs performed for a priuate good, or for publike honor and profit to the common wealth, by temperance wee are ſchooled to crowne it with our praiſes, without aſſentation or baſe flatterie.</p>
            <p>And if a well intended action be not ſeconded with fortunate ſucceſſe, ſhe then teacheth vs not to accuſe the attempter thereof without reaſon or cauſe, but mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtly and kindly to impute the defect of ſpeeding to the truth it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>Temperance is neuer without meaſure, ſhe preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:2460:45"/>bounds and limits vnto happineſſe, and by her me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diation, ſhe maketh ſuch as be fortunate, to bee more mightie and more ſtrong.</p>
            <p>She ſheweth vs the way by curteſie to be reconciled to our enemies, and to regaine them to our ſelues, and with mutuall reſpects to enlarge our faith and hartie loue to our worthie friends, ſhe craueth nothing to be repented of; ſhe is not immoderate in her deſires, but ſubmitteth all her affections vnto reaſon, if ſhee loue riches, ſhe vſeth them well, ſhe is not perplexed, not vexed for the want of them. And if ſhee looſe them (hauing once had them) ſhe is not without meaſure greeued thereat.</p>
            <p>It is not therefore <hi>(my ſonne)</hi> ſo praiſeworthie to bee borne faire, and beutifull and comely, as it is to be made comely, beutifull and faire by this noble and heroicall virtue of temperance.</p>
            <p>Seeke her therefore as a pearle of ineſtimable price and find her, though with much trauell and paine; for in her companie there is contentedneſſe and much ioy.</p>
            <p>And when you doe poſſeſſe her, let her not goe from you, but keepe you onely vnto her, as long as you haue daies to liue.
<note place="margin">Humilitie.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And to the end that you may haue the more pleaſure in her companie,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prou.</hi> 11.2.</note> let humilitie be her hand-maiden to attend vpon her, for <hi>God giueth grace vnto the humble, and with ſuch as are lowlie there is vnderſtanding and wiſedome.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſ.</hi> 37.11.</note> Meeke men ſhall poſſeſſe the earth, and haue their delight in the multitude of peace, an humble man treaſureth vp loue, and is daily enriched with many friends.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If misfortunes doe violently runne towards a man of an humble ſpirit, they will paſſe by him, and will not hurt him, for he reſiſteth not but (lying on the ground)
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:2460:46"/>can take no fall. Humilitie ouercommeth ſuch as are otherwiſe inuincible, and raiſeth ſuch vnto great honor as were of a meane eſtate. An humble man is faſt moar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in a quiet hauen, where he is free from tempeſts and careleſſe of all ſtormes, he feareth not the diſpleaſures of potent and of mightie men, becauſe he will not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke the leaſt and the meaneſt vnto wrath, he ſtriueth not with his ſuperiour, nor skorneth the ſocietie of his inferiour, he exalteth not himſelfe becauſe he is learned but is alwaies more deſirous to harken then to ſpeake.</p>
            <p>He magnifieth not himſelfe by reaſon of his riches (becauſe they are not permanent, he boaſteth not in his ſtrength, becauſe olde age or ſickneſſe can make him weake, he is not confident of his health, becauſe he may quickly be diſeaſed.</p>
            <p>Finally in his owne reputation he is not ſuch a one as he is indeede,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Barland Apho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſ.</hi> 1 51.</note> but he is leſſer then himſelfe, yet grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then he who is great in his owne eyes. It is not true humilitie for a man to reuerence his elders, nor to dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie his ſuperiors, nor with good reſpects to reckon of his, equals for this is rather to bee deemed and eſteemed a dutie, but to preferre before himſelfe ſuch as are honeſt and vertuous (yet in eſtate and in degree are lower and inferiour vnto him) this, and none but this is true, and abſolute humilitie.</p>
            <p>A bucket before it can be filled withwater, muſt deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend into the well, and men by humilitie, and with hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſpirits muſt firſt deſcend into the loweſt roomes of their meeke hearts before they can be truely wiſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vt nemo te euertat cadas ſponte,</hi> that no man may be able to throw you downe, fall of your owne accord.</p>
            <p>Be humble that no ſtout ſtomacke may find any oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:2460:46"/>or haue any power to make you lower then you will make your ſelfe to be, ſo ſhall your humilitie raiſe you with more aſſurance of continuance then ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or pride can. <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith,
<note place="margin">Pride. <hi>Peru.</hi> 29.23.</note> that a <hi>mans pride ſhal bring him lowe, but that the humble in ſpirit ſhall enioy glorie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This was approued (by wofull experience) to be true by all the famous and moſt renouned Citties in <hi>Greece,</hi> euerie one of them proudly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tending againſt theother (by force of armes) for preheminence and ſoueraignty, by meanes whereof all of them in a ſhort time were by their enemies ruinated and ſubuerted.
<note place="margin">Nunc ſeges est ybi Troia fuit.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The ambitious and vnbounded haughtineſſe of <hi>Caeſar</hi> was the cauſe of the warres in Rome, &amp; <hi>Pompeys</hi> pride weakned the Romans ſtrength, and haſtned his owne death, for ambitious mindes make great men to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt many deſperate things, and they are dangerous in the common weale. The prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> telleth vs,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 18.27. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 31.23.</note> that <hi>the Lord caſteth downe the proude lookes, and that hee rewardeth aboundantly the proude doer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Before deſtruction (ſaith he) the heart of a man is hauty.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſ.</hi> 18.12. <hi>Dau.</hi> 4.</note> So was Nebucadnezzers heart before hee was caſt from his princely throne, and compelled by the ſentence of God to eate graſſe in the field like a beaſt, for the ſpace of ſeuenyeares, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till</hi> that by his puniſhment he acknowledged God, and became humble.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And ſo was Hamans heart, who (being glutted and ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged with thoſe vnſpeakable honors which were vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily and without iuſt deſerts conferred vpon him by Ahaſhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eroth the king,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſter.</hi> 7.</note> was hanged vpon his owne gallows at the ſame time, when (in his malice and in his pride) he intended to haue inſulted wickedly vpon the death of Mordocai, and vpon the bloudie maſſacring, and murdring of Gods people the Iewes.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="74" facs="tcp:2460:47"/>
            <p>
               <hi>And ſowas Abſoloms heart,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 18.</note> who (in his pride) traiterouſly and againſt nature affecting his fathers crowne &amp; kingdome was in his flight ſuddenly hanged by the haires of his head on a tree,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Regum. cap.</hi> 18. <hi>et. cap.</hi> 19.</note> vntill his bodie was pierced through with three ſpeares, by Ioab his mortall enemie. And ſo was the heart of Senache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rib who (truſting in his owne ſtrength) and in the multitude of his men of warre) impiouſly and proudly blaſphemed the great name of the liuing God, but was (forthwith) plagued with the loſſe of the greateſt part of his huge armie, &amp; not long after was murdred as he ſacrificed in the temple of Niſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roch his God, by Adramelech and Sharezar his owne ſonnes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo were the proude harts of <hi>Ceſar</hi> who (in his am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious humor) ſcorned an equall, and of <hi>Pompey</hi> who (diſdained to admit of any ſuperiour) vntil <hi>Pompey</hi> was compelled by <hi>Caeſar</hi> to flie into Egypt where he was tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherouſly ſlaine by his falſe friend,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sledan.</hi> 31.</note> and that <hi>Caeſar</hi> was by <hi>Brutus</hi> and <hi>Caſſius</hi> aſſaulted and murdred with pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kniues in the ſenate houſe.</p>
            <p>And ſo was the heart of that monſter among men; <hi>Caligula,</hi> who cauſed the Gods of the <hi>Grecians</hi> to bee brought vnto Rome, where he himſelfe wore their or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments and crownes, and would be adored as a God. And ſo was the heart of the proud wife of the Venetian duke, named <hi>Dominico Seluio,</hi> ſiſter to <hi>Niceforus</hi> the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour,
<note place="margin">Hiſtoria Itali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca.</note> who vſed ordinarily to waſh her bodie in baths made of the dewes of heauen, but was (before ſhe died) choaked, and poiſoned with the noiſome ſtench of her owne rotten and putrified fleſh.</p>
            <p>You may reade that the Grecian monarch vſed the dining table of <hi>Darius</hi> the late monarch of the <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Perſians</hi> (being al made of beaten gold) for his foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoole as he ſate at meate.</p>
            <pb n="75" facs="tcp:2460:47"/>
            <p>And that Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> the third,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Harim Sche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dul.</hi> 102.</note> proudly treading vpon the necke of the firſt <hi>Fredericke</hi> abuſing &amp; peruer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the attributes of our Lord &amp; Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt, &amp; conuerting them by way of application to his owne pride, ſaid with king <hi>Dauid</hi> (but with a wicked mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning) <hi>Super Aſpidem, et baſiliſcum ambulabis, et conculcabis Leonem et Draconem: Thou ſhalt walke vpon the Aſpe, and baſiliſke,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſ.</hi> 91.13. <hi>Harim Sche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dul. fo.</hi> 192. <hi>Sledan.</hi> 83.</note> and ſhall tread the Lion and the Dragon vnder thy feete.</hi> Did not Pope <hi>Gregorie</hi> the ſeuenth, compell the noble Emperour, <hi>Henrie</hi> the fourth (in the depth of an vnſeaſonable winter) to attend, and to wait at his gate barefooted, by the ſpace of three daies, before he would giue him any audience, and abſolue him, being excommunicated, becauſe hee had conferred biſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rickes on diuers men without the Popes leaue or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent (according the old and auncient rites, priuiledges, and cuſtomes of the Empires.</p>
            <p>Theſe and ſuch like monſtrous effects of pride, doe make men (in their owne eyes) to ſeeme to be immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall Gods, when as (indeede) they are no better then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate fiendes, and incarnate deuils, and (inſtead of being famouſed for many vertuous qualities) to be infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with perpetuall ignominie and ſhame.</p>
            <p>For like as a planet, by how much the higher it is, by ſo much the more ſlowly it attaineth to the full compaſſe of his ſphere, ſo by how much the more a proude man is elated and puffed vp with vaine glorie and ambition, the further off he is from his end, which is, or ought to be, God: as it appeared by Lucifer and his bragging angels, who (in their vſurping pride) coueting and deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to be <hi>Gods,</hi> were ſuddenly caſt downe from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and transformed, and changed in to hideous feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:2460:48"/>and loathſome hagges of hell.</p>
            <p>Therefore (my ſonne) you muſt be warie that you clime not too hie, leaſt (the boughs failing you, by which you ſtriue and ſtruggle to aſcend) you fall downe flatte vnto the ground, vnable and hopeleſſe to ariſe any more.</p>
            <p>If you carry greater ſailes then your barkes can beare, you ſhall vndoubtedly be drowned in the high ſeas of your owne pride.</p>
            <p>When pride poſſeſſeth a mans heart, it poyſoneth the whole man, like as a deuouring canker (hauing feſtered and putrified one principall member) quickly by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees deſtroyeth the whole body.</p>
            <p>There is no calamitie which (in the end) is not a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar companion with haughtineſſe, and with pride.</p>
            <p>Neither is there any felicitie or happineſſe that can make him truely bleſſed, that is proude, and of an ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious minde.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 18.</note> 
               <hi>Diogenes Lacrtius</hi> in <hi>Solons</hi> life reporteth, that when <hi>Craeſus</hi> the great and rich king of <hi>Lydia,</hi> had proudly apparelled himſelfe, in the fineſt, faireſt, and moſt coſtly ſilkes that could for any price be procured, and when he had deckt and imboſt his bodie with the richeſt ornaments of pearle of gold, and of pretious ſtones which hee poſſeſſed, and had with pompous maieſtie, ſeated himſelfe in his aduaunced royal throne he then demaunded of <hi>Solon</hi> if (in all the courſe of his life) he had euer ſeene and beheld ſo ſplendent and ſo faire a ſight, to whome the graue and wiſe Philoſopher (mildly reproouing and reprehending his vanitie and pride) made anſwere, yea for that (quoth hee) cockes, hennes, pheſants, peacockes, partridges, and ſuch like birdes are more gloriouſly clothed and couered with their owne faire and beautiful feathers, but thou (quoth
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:2460:48"/>he) art varniſhed &amp; ouer-floriſht with the excrements &amp; counterfaited colours and riches of other creatures.</p>
            <p>A proude mans minde neuer taketh reſt, for when it is leaſt occupied, it then buildes caſtles in the aire.</p>
            <p>But an humble man knoweth,
<note place="margin">Humilitie.</note> that no man can attaine vnto happineſſe, but he that is lowly in his owne heart, for like as the higheſt ſoaring Eagle cannot be fed, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept ſhe doe deſcend from the skies, and fall vpon the ground, ſo no man (of what eſtate or condition ſoeuer he be) can be happie, either in this life, or in the life to come, except he be humble and lowly, and leauing the hight of his proude and ambitious conceits, do behaue himſelfe humbly both towards God, and alſo towards men. In a word know this for a truth &amp; ſuretie, that this monſtrous and wicked ſinne of pride, draweth downe from heauen, Gods iudgements and his vengeance vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on man.</p>
            <p>And therefore ſeeing it muſt be hated with a perfit hatred, ſeeing it is moſt aſſured in the end to receiue a ſhamefull fall, come not neere vnto her, for ſhee is as infectious as the plague, be not acquainted with ſuch as (through their pride and ambition) haue heades which are lighter then their hattes, but (contenting your ſelfe with your owne eſtate,
<note place="margin">Selfe loue. Boaſting.</note> and liuing decently within the bounds and limits thereof) doe you endeuour by honeſt meanes, voide of pride, to aduaunce it when and as God will.</p>
            <p>And (in any caſe) be not in loue or liking with your ſelfe, nor with your owne conceits, neither doe you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh too pleaſingly your owne actions and doings, but rather frame them diſcreetely, to be ſuch as that others (hauing iuſt cauſe) may ſpeake well of them, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:2460:49"/>them, for nothing ſoundeth more harſhly in a wiſe mans eares then a mans owne praiſes, vainely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed with his owne tongue, <hi>Laus propria ſordet in ore.</hi> Endeuour your ſelfe and bend your courſes (rather for the practiſe of your vertues, then (for the vaine boaſting and tatling of them by your ſelfe) to bee eſteemed and commended: <hi>Fruſtra enim de radice gloriatur, qui nihil adfert niſi folia,</hi> it is an idle thing to praiſe, and to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend that tree which bringeth forthno fruit but leaues.</p>
            <p>It was <hi>Narciſſus</hi> his vaine follie, to drowne himſelfe, being in loue with his owne watrie ſhaddow.</p>
            <p>And many men doe fooliſhly vaniſh quite away, as ſhadowes doe without merit or remembrance, becauſe they doe more affect to be well ſpoken of, then indeede to doe well.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Virtus in actione conſiſtit,</hi> the true honour of vertue conſiſteth not in the onely ſpeculatiue knowledge and contemplation thereof, nor in boaſting tatling and idle talking, but in exerciſing of vertue, when ſhe is knowne.</p>
            <p>For like as a barking dogge doth not often bite, ſo he that bableth ouermuch of himſelfe, doth ſeldome put in practiſe any thing worthie of praiſe and commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the deepeſt waters doe glide and paſſe away with the ſmalleſt noice, &amp; a wiſe man is moſt ſilent, when he deſerueth beſt.</p>
            <p>Conuerſe not with ſuch as (relating wonders of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues) will ſtriue to perſwade you, that they haue out whet-ſtones inſunder with their kniues, and that (with one word or with a ſterne looke) they haue compelled an boaſt of armed men to flie before them.</p>
            <p>Credit me, no wiſedome can proceede from ſuch
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:2460:49"/>boaſters, leaue them therefore alone like vnto winde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mils, vpon the mountaines of their owne vanities, to be turned about with euerie blaſt of wind of their owne praiſe.</p>
            <p>Next vnto theſe <hi>(My ſonne)</hi> my counſell is,
<note place="margin">Courteſie. Gentlenteſſe. Affabilitie. Clemencie. Humanitie.</note> that you be courteous, affable, gentle, and familiar in all your carriage and behauiour, vnto all ſuch as do either keepe you companie, or craue your helpe. For none other qualities then theſe, can more commend you to your friends, nor make you to bee better reſpected among your foes, becauſe they doe bind your wel-willers firm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to your frendſhip, and (in ſome ſort) doe procure wonder and admiration in your enemies, when they ſhall ſee, and perfectly vnderſtand, that the mildneſſe of your nature (though perchaunce prouoked) doth neither incline to anger nor to reuenge, but rather vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a faire inuitation to reconciliation, and vnto loue.</p>
            <p>Wee may eaſily obſerue, that like as a generous (though a proude) horſe is ſooner turned about with a gentle, then with an hard or a ſtubborne bit, ſo many mens natures (though fierce and haſtie) are notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding ſooner reclaimed from rage and furie, by the courteous diſpoſition, and gentle humanitie of thoſe with whome they doe contend, then otherwiſe they would be by their aſperitie and ſtouteneſſe of their ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mackes to commaund.
<q>
                  <l>Peragit tranquilla poteſtas,</l>
                  <l>Quod violentanequit.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Clemencie and gentleneſſe haue ſooner freede ſome beſeeged Citties from ſacking, from ſpoyling, from fire, and from the ſword, then policie or ſtrength, or skill in armes could doe.</p>
            <pb n="80" facs="tcp:2460:50"/>
            <p>The ſtrong and the tall oke that proudly confronteth the boiſterous and the wherling winds, is ſooner ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne and tumbled to the ground then weaker trees, and lower ſhrubbes are, which make no reſiſtance for want of abilitie and ſtrength.</p>
            <p>If a ſhippe ſailing on the ſeas, ſhould ſtemme both wind and tide, ſhe wil be in great hazard and peril to be drowned. And if bitterneſſe and rough conditions bee oppoſed againſt the violence of haſtie ſpirits, there will be no pleaſing peace, but rather a beginning of perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall mutinies and of iarres.</p>
            <p>Soft clay maketh ſtrong and hard walles, and curteſie (mitigating other mens wrath and furious paſſions) doth both gaine them and retaine them for kind and for heartie friends.</p>
            <p>By courteſie and humanitie, all ſocieties among men are maintained and preſerued, <hi>Societas enim nihil aliud eſt quàm amica hominum inter ſe coniuncta familiaritas,</hi> ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is nothing elſe but a mutual &amp; a reciprocal exchange of gentlenes, of kindneſſe, of affabilitie, of familiaritie, and of courteſie among men. In hiſtories we may read that <hi>Antonius Pius</hi> the Emperor was ſingularly beloued of all men, becauſe he was affable and frendly vnto all.</p>
            <p>And that <hi>Theodoſius</hi> was ſo familiar with his ſubiects that he ſeemed onely to differ from them in the faſhion and in the worth of his apparell.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Traian</hi> (the Emperour) being on a time deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded why he was ſo familiar with his ſubiects, made this anſwere, that a king ought to be vnto his ſubiects ſuch a one as his ſubiects ought to be vnto him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Clemencie</hi> in a man, may (in ſome ſort) be compared to the loue of God towards man, for as God (louing vs)
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:2460:50"/>ſatiſfieth and filleth vs with all good things, ſo a man that is courteous and gentle, and beutified with <hi>Clemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie</hi> and kindneſſe towards his friend helpeth him in what he is able, and ſtandeth him in ſteede, when hee may doe him any good. Humanitie pardoneth without ſute or much entreatie, ſuch things as (among frends) are now &amp; then vnwittingly or vnwillingly committed and done amiſſe, and ſpareth to giue iudgement, when it ſeeth and knoweth that griefe and ſorrow is concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued for an offence, it pittieth where it may iuſtly correct and puniſh, and it gaineth by mildneſſe where by ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie it may ſtrike.</p>
            <p>Therefore let theſe faire and pleaſant flowers, be the primroſes in your garland, ſet this rich iewell in the front of your brow, that others (beholding it and taking perfit notice of ſo faire a ſigne) may voluntarily repaire to you as frends, and be kindly lodged in your loue.</p>
            <p>So ſhall your wel-willers be many, and your ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies very few, your frends expectation ſhall be anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and your ſelfe bee pleaſed in the fruition of their companie and good liking.</p>
            <p>Vnto curteſie and to thoſe other vertues,
<note place="margin">Patience.</note> you muſt ioyne patience, which deſerueth no leſſe to bee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended and embraced then the reſt, becauſe none o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vertue is ſo good a preſeruatiue or ſo ſoueraigne an antidote againſt iniuries receiued, and aduerſitie to be endured, as patience is, for if a man be wronged by his frend, ſhe maketh him to baniſh anger, and telleth him,
<note place="margin">Anger.</note> that in forbearing to reuenge, he is truely valiant, who can ſuppreſſe and diſcreetely conquere his owne rage.</p>
            <p>She telleth him, that anger is an infallible argument of ſmall courage, and that it is an ardent, and an eger ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:2460:51"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:2460:51"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:2460:52"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:2460:52"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:2460:53"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:2460:53"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:2460:54"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:2460:54"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:2460:55"/>to reuenge, and that no reuenge is free from its owne proper danger.</p>
            <p>She telleth him, that an angry man is (for a time) a madde man, and that he muſt therefore giue place vnto wrath whilſt it runneth and paſſeth by, according to the Poets wiſe inſtruction, when hee ſaieth <hi>Currenti cede furori.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>She telleth him,
<note place="margin">Silius Italicus.</note> that whilſt a man is furious, and with anger ranging, he wanteth the vſe of reaſon, whichſhould be the director and the guide of all his paſſions, and that an angrie man may ſooner repent then amend what he doth amiſſe. And that it is more praiſe-wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie to pardon, then baſely to reuenge iniuries and wronges.</p>
            <p>She preſenteth before your eyes the example of the impatience of <hi>Coriolanus</hi> the great Roman,
<note place="margin">Plutarch in vita Coriolani.</note> who vſed to bee ſo angry, that he was ſenſeleſſe, vntill he did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge.</p>
            <p>And teacheth you,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Idem in vita Marcelli. pag.</hi> 319.</note> how much more commendable the patience of <hi>Marcellus</hi> was, who being falſely accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of many faults to the Citie of Rome &amp; to the ſenate there, by the <hi>Syracuſans,</hi> whom he had conquered, &amp; ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing cleared himſelfe of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all, was notwithſtanding ſo patient, that he not onely remitted their wilfull offence and great ingratitude, but procured (of his owne ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord) a confirmation from the ſenate, that they ſhould enioy their owne lawes, liberties and cuſtomes, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to a former grant which he had made vnto them in that behalfe,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Idem in vita Polopid. pag.</hi> 299.</note> the like curteſie was ſhewed by <hi>Epami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nondas</hi> to the <hi>Thebans,</hi> when he had cleared himſelfe of ſuch treaſons, as by them were falſely obiected againſt him, and laid vnto his charge. And of <hi>Marcus Antonius</hi>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:2460:55"/>it is reported, that the greater misfortunes that did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall him,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Idem in vita Antonij. pag.</hi> 919.</note> with the more conſtancie and patience he did endure them all.</p>
            <p>This is a principall effect of true patience,
<note place="margin">Aduerſitie. Afflictions.</note> that if ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſities doe with rage and furie ruſh in vpon a man, ſhe inſtructeth him to beare them patiently as a burden impoſed on his ſholders by God himſelfe, it telleth him that <hi>God chaſteneth euery one whom hee doth receaue,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.6. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.13.</note> and tempteth no man aboue his ſtrength, and it teacheth him to know that as little children ſeeme to be baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from their fathers houſes (but are not) when they are put forth to be nurſed, but being growne to riper age and ſtrength, are ioyfully receiued &amp; entertained as members of their fathers families, ſo a repentant ſinner (when he is tried with any tribulation or affliction for his ſoules health) ſeemeth for a time to be caſt out, and to be exiled from the loue and preſence of his moſt gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious and good God, but he is not, for when thoſe affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions and thoſe croſſes haue begotten in him a true confeſſion of his ſinnes, an heartie repentance for his tranſgreſſions, &amp; an amendment of his wretched life, he is then receiued againe by his father and good God, and by him acknowledged for his child, as by the hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of the prodigal ſonne it appeareth luke. 15. Patience perſwadeth men quietly to endure their trials, and eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſupport their aduerſe fortunes.
<note place="margin">Reaſons per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwading to pauence.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Either becauſe there was no poſſibilitie that they might be auoided, or elſe becauſe they haue deſerued that croſſe and puniſhment, and more, or elſe becauſe aduerſitie and affliction (ſooner then eaſe or proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie) will draw them to the amendment of their ſinfull liues.</p>
            <pb n="84" facs="tcp:2460:56"/>
            <p>Or elſe becauſe by them they ſhould be ſeaſoned for better fortunes, or elſe becauſe (if their afflictions bee but ſmall) they ſhould thereby bee perſwaded, yea throughly reſolued of Gods fauour, and of his loue to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them, who hath not ſo greeuouſly, and in that heauie meaſure corrected them, as hee hath puniſhed other men.</p>
            <p>And if they be great &amp; burdenſome, that then (through repentance) they ſhall in the end be recompenced with much ioy, and be rewarded with vnſpeakable gladneſſe in the world to come.</p>
            <p>Theſe and many more be the ſweete and the comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table fruites, which (with a liberall and an enlarged hand) patience powreth into our boſomes.</p>
            <p>It is written,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Diogenes Laer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius.</hi> 197.</note> that <hi>Diogenes</hi> the Cinicke vſed inſtantly, and with much importunitie to craue and begge rich gifts of the ſtatues and pictures of Noble men, of Princes, of Kings, and of Emperours (which long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore were dead) becauſe he would exerciſe his patience in not obtaining of ſuch things as ſo earneſtly he had ſued for.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jdem. pag.</hi> 59.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And that <hi>Socrates</hi> was ſo patient, that being immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derately and immodeſtly chidden and reuiled by <hi>Zanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe</hi> (his curſt and froward wife) he quietly went out of his doores, to free himſelfe from the hearing of thoſe domeſticall chidings, but as he ſate vnder his window, he was filthily polluted and defiled with vrine, which in great aboundance, ſhe powred vpon his head, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at he ſmilingly and mildly ieſted without choller or an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger in this quiet and merry faſhion, I knew (quoth he) that after ſo great a thunder, a ſhower of raigne would fall.</p>
            <pb n="85" facs="tcp:2460:56"/>
            <p>You ſee therefore that a patient man (if hee cannot with mildneſſe preuent it) endureth (without anger or deſire to reuenge) as much iniurie and wrong,
<note place="margin">Engliſh fugi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues.</note> if not crueltie, as the worſt inuentons of his enemies can<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> adde vnto the extremitie of their hatred.</p>
            <p>He will not bend his owne bowe, though himſelfe be in hazard to be ſhot quite through. But if he may peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably and quietly preuent, or auoide his owne danger, he then breaketh in ſunder the darts, and plucketh out the teeth of anger, of rage, and of furie, that they may doe no harme.</p>
            <p>Seeing then that patience wil not be ſeruile or ſlauiſh vnto anger, nor to reuenge, but will rather contend and ſtriue by meeke ſufferance to preuent, or to beare ſuch future miſchiefes, as rage and haſtie furie cannot auoid, let her bee entertained by you as a friend that alwaies bringeth with her contentment,
<note place="margin">Contentment</note> without which riches and honor, and pleaſure (mens chiefeſt darlings) and all things elſe will be as vnwelcomed, as water is into a ſhip, and will ſound no better then muſicke out of tune, nor taſte any ſweeter then bitter pils, which ſicke men (againſt their ſtomackes) are enforced to ſwallow down. And thus (my ſonne) I hauing briefely diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vpon theſe former qualities, Liberalitie ſhall be the next virtue which I will commend vnto you for her owne ſake:
<note place="margin">Liberalitie.</note> but cannot commannd you to put her much in practiſe, becauſe your meanes are ſmall.</p>
            <p>Yet doe I wiſh you to vnderſtand, that ſuch is her comelines and beautie, that it cannot be diſcerned, but in a faire and in a large glaſſe.</p>
            <p>That her minde is ſo noble, and truely generous, that ſhe is onely familiar with men and women of good abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:2460:57"/>and of good worth.</p>
            <p>That ſhe is ſtrong as a Lion, and ſo powerfull, that at her pleaſure, and when ſhe liſteth, ſhe can throw downe huge and mightie gates of braſſe.</p>
            <p>That Citties and countries, and kingdomes, and Empires, are ſubiect to her command, that ſhe diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uereth ſecret things, and vnderſtandeth Princes coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels.</p>
            <p>That ſhe compelleth the fierceſt and the ſtouteſt ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to ſtoupe, and to become captines at het becke. And maketh weake armies to preuaile againſt ſuch as are puiſant and very ſtrong.</p>
            <p>Without liberalitie, a rich man cannot eſtabliſh his eſtate, nor purchaſe fame. Neither can poore men (without her) receaue ſuch reliefe and comfort as their neceſſities doe require.</p>
            <p>Without liberalitie, charitie ſoone waxeth cold, and worketh not by loue. Without her, arts &amp; ſciences are laid aſleepe with ignorance, that vgly monſter, as Og the king of Baſan was with his crueltie and tyranny lodged in his iron bed.</p>
            <p>Without her peace cannot long continue, nor wars be waged with good and fortunate ſucceſſe.</p>
            <p>Liberalitie reſembleth and repreſenteth Gods boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, in being open handed to ſuch as want and ſtand in neede of helpe, ſhe teacheth rich men rightly to vſe their riches which they poſſeſſe. And true liberalitie doth principally conſiſt in theſe things.
<note place="margin">Eight rules in Liberalitie.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt that we giue that which is our owne, and not that which belongeth vnto another man, for otherwiſe we ſhall no leſſe offend then theeues, bribers, and extor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioners doe, who practiſe their vnconſcionable villanies
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:2460:57"/>thereby to enable themſelues to bee charitable vnto o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men who ſtand in neede of helpe.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that we giue not where nothing is deſerued for it argueth a great defect and ſcarſitie of diſcretion, to be bountifull to an vnworthie man.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, that in giuing wee doe proportion our gift with the merit and deſert, for proportion in all things (eſpecially in the practiſe of liberalitie) is carefully to be reſpected and obſerued.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, that in giuing we doe obſerue a fitting and a conuenient time, for he which giueth not, when by his gift he may doe good to the diſtreſſed partie, vpon whom he purpoſeth to extend his bountie, cannot at a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other time benefit and pleaſure him, as he intendeth by his gift to doe.</p>
            <p>Fiftly that (though vpon good deſert) yet wee giue not ſo much, that by the large extent of our liberalitie our owne families be wronged and doe want, for hee who is not carefull of thoſe whom God hath commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to his charge, is worſe then an infidell, and hath denied the faith.</p>
            <p>Sixtly, that we do not giue in hope to receiue againe for it is a more bleſſed thing to giue then to take.</p>
            <p>Seuenthly, that we giue with a readie and with a wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling minde, for <hi>Hilarem datorem amat Deus.</hi> God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe is well pleaſed with a cheerefull giuer.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, that we giue not any thing to, and for a wicked end and purpoſe. <hi>Finis enim beat exitum,</hi> the end of our liberalitie muſt be honeſt, for otherwiſe we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be truely liberall. Now as euery one that worketh vpon timber is not a cunning and a skilfull Carpenter, ſo euery man or woman that giueth gifts is not rightly
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:2460:58"/>and indeede liberall, for if his gift be not approued and warranted by all theſe former obſeruations, then it is not the effect, or the fruit of liberalitie, but of prodiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, and it is rather diſgraceful then (in any ſort) praiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full or commendable to the giuer. And we muſt know that liberalitie is attended with two extreames, that is to ſay,
<note place="margin">Prodigalitie.</note> with prodigalitie and with couetouſneſſe.</p>
            <p>Prodigalitie exerciſeth her ſelfe about ſuperfluous expences and needeleſſe gifts,
<note place="margin">Couetouſnes.</note> and couetouſneſſe gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily heapeth and hoordeth vp al which ſhe can ſcratch and gripe, not communicating her fortunes with other men, no though they ſtand in great neceſſitie and in neede.</p>
            <p>The former of theſe two is in exceſſe, and the latter of them is in defect, the former hath a faire ſhew of virtue, but the other hath none at all.</p>
            <p>Of prodigalitie it ſhall not be needefull to diſcourſe further, or to dilate more, for (in a word) he is not true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly liberall, but riotous and prodigall, who performeth not all thoſe former recited requiſits in giuing.</p>
            <p>But of Couetouſneſſe ſome what ſhall be ſpoken,
<note place="margin">Couetouſnes.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I haue a longing deſire to make her loathſome and odious vnto you, whom moſt men ſo affectionatly doe loue.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Col.</hi> 3.5.</note> She is a <hi>Species</hi> or a kind of idolatrie (as the Apoſtle Saint Paul doth teſtifie) becauſe ſhee perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth her vaſſals, and her ſlaues, impiouſly to adore mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie and riches, as their God.</p>
            <p>A couetous man ſhutteth his eyes againſt all others, and openeth them onely to himſelfe.</p>
            <p>His hands are alwaies faſt, when they ſhould bee ſtretched foorth to giue bountifully vnto other men. He doth al things for his owne commoditie and gaine,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:2460:58"/>and nothing, by which he may be beneficiall to his friend.</p>
            <p>He leaueth no ſtone vnremoued, if by his trauell, and by his toile he may augment and encreaſe his ſtore. All is fiſh that commeth into his net, and he careth little, by what meanes his ſubſtance is enlarged, ſo that his eſtate be aduanced thereby.</p>
            <p>A couetous man is neuer ſatisfied, nay hee is alwaies needie, and his thirſt after riches is neuer quenched, he ſupplieth not his owne neede with thoſe things which he poſſeſſeth, but as in the extremitie of laughter there are ſome teares, ſo in a couetous mans greateſt ſtore and plentie, there is ſcarcitie and want: <hi>Nam auaro tam deeſt quod habet, quam quod non.</hi> A couetous man wanteth aſwel that which he hath, as that which he hath not, he enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth none but ſuch as doe bring him gaine and profit, commending the poets opinion, when in a couetous mans behalfe he ſaith thus.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Si nihil attuler is, ibis Homere foras.</l>
               <l>If emptie handed thou appeare,</l>
               <l>No welcome gueſt thou canſt be here.</l>
            </q>
            <p>His labour to gather wealth and riches is reſtleſſe, his care to keepe them is boundleſſe, and his ſorrow (if hee chance to looſe them) is endleſſe.</p>
            <p>If any thing be taken from him, he thinkes he hath loſt his ſoule, and if any thing be giuen to him, he prizeth it at a greater value then his life. If he be ouer-loaden with ſiluer and with gold, he ſaieth his burden is too too light.</p>
            <p>And though nature be (of her owne diſpoſition) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented with a little, yet a couetous man imagineth that he can neuer haue enough. <hi>Nunquám ſatiatur auarus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The more that he hath, the more he ſtill deſireth, his eyes are neuer ſatisfied, his hands are neuer filled, his hart
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:2460:59"/>is neuer contented with the too much aboundance of his wealth, a couetous man is compaſſed round about as a ſhip is oftentimes with craggie rockes, and at length he is daſhed againſt them to his deſtruction, as ſhe is againſt thoſe to her vtter ruine.</p>
            <p>And like as the moone, by the interpoſition of the earth betwixt her and the Sunne, ſuffereth an Eclipſe, ſo a man (when couetouſneſſe intrudeth betwixt his God and him) is depriued of his heauenly grace and is dead to all good workes.</p>
            <p>For like as a ſponge licketh and drinketh vp much li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor, but giueth none forth againe, except it be ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly preſſed &amp; bruſed: ſo a couetous man heapeth vp much riches and great treaſure, but departeth not with any to ſupplie and to relieue the diſtreſſed neceſſities of ſuch as want, and doe ſtand in neede, vntill that by death it be wrung and wreſted out of his fiſt.</p>
            <p>And like as a gooſe wil onely diſcloſe her owne egges, and not thoſe which are laied by other birdes: ſo a coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous man will not doe any good but onely to, and for himſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pliny</hi> writeth of a kinde of Eagle, who (hauing one claw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foote and the other flat) is armed and prouided,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bercho. Reduct Moral.</hi> 178.</note> and vſeth to take her pray both vpon the water, and vpon the land alſo. Such a deuouring Eagle is a couetous man, who (both by land, and by ſea, by good meanes and by bad, by right and by wrong) ſcrapeth and ſcratcheth wealth and riches together, and powreth it by heapes into his owne boſome, though in ſo doing, he doe robbe, ſpoile, and vndoe others.
<note place="margin">Caeſars Coment.</note> 
               <hi>Caeſar</hi> in his commentaries doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, that <hi>Scipio Affricanus</hi> was ſo couetous, that to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe his wealth he robbed Churches, Temples, Statues
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:2460:59"/>and the rich ſepulchers of the dead.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Arthipertus</hi> king of the Lombards flying from <hi>Aſprandus</hi> (his enemie) was ſo heauily loaden with gold,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deſcriptio Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liae.</hi> 20.</note> that ſwimming ouer the riuer Teſino to ſaue his life, hee was miſerably drowned by reaſon of the waight and ponderouſneſſe thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pontanus</hi> in his Booke of liberalitie,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Theat. Mundi.</hi> 98.</note> maketh mention of a Cardinall named <hi>Angelot,</hi> who was ſo baſely wretched and couetous, that almoſt euery night (when his bed ſhould haue contained him) hee vſed (in the darkenes of the ſame) to goe ſecretly into his owne ſtable, and to ſteale away from his owne horſes, ſuch prouender as by his horſeman was giuen to them, by meanes whereof his horſes became feeble, faint, and very leane, whereat the horſeman much maruaeled, becauſe hee ſuppoſed their allowance to bee liberall and large, and fitting to haue made them fat, wherefore he watched one night priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the ſtable, to make a triall whether any theeſe did there practiſe his skill or no, and at length the Cardinall (according to his manner and cuſtome) came in at his owne ſecret dore, and performed his nightly taske, in taking his horſes allowance from them, but the horſeman (perceiuing that a theefe was there, and not knowing who it was) with a ſtiffe and ſtrong cudgel ſo guirded, and laced the backe and ſhoulders of his couetous maſter, that in the end (to free himſelfe from that vnexpected entertainement) he was enforced to confeſſe his fault, and very ſhamefully to bewray himſelfe. Such and ſo vile and baſe is the wretched nature of a couetous man, that it maketh him to forget himſelfe, and to commit ſuch things as are vnſeemely and vile, any it maketh him to doe any thing, bee it neuer ſo vncharitable, and
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:2460:60"/>bee it neuer ſo wicked and vngodly.</p>
            <p>Therefore <hi>(My ſonne)</hi> though the weakeneſſe of your thinne purſe will not ſuffer you to be liberall, yet let your generous and free nature teach you to hate and deteſt couetouſneſſe, becauſe ſhe will ſtriue to alienate your af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections from virtue, as an harlot doth the beſt loue of a woman from her husband.</p>
            <p>The next thing which you muſt principally,
<note place="margin">Playing. Dice and Cardes.</note> and with an extraordinarie care ſhunne and auoide, is playing at cardes, and at dice, becauſe (among many others) theſe inconueniences, nay theſe miſchiefes doe eſpecially pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede and flow from ſuch gaming, and from ſuch play.</p>
            <p>Firſt of all, the expence and loſſe of time, which (in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede) I may truly terme to be loſt, becauſe no time can (almoſt) be worſe ſpent,
<note place="margin">Time.</note> then that which is vainely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed in ſuch fooliſh ſporting. And if we could (with a iudicious eye) behold how pretious and how inualuable a thing time is, we ſhould then thinke, nay we ſhould then know our fortune to be very bad, to looſe time, though wee were (otherwiſe) aſſured to winne all whatſoeuer we plaied for.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fugit irreuocabile Tempus,</hi> time which is paſt, and gone away, cannot (with millions of golde and of ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer) bee recalled to our preſence, no, not with the price of a whole world. It is commonly ſaid, that <hi>Tempus eſt edax rerum,</hi> time is the conſumer and the deuourer of all thinges. But a buſie gameſter falſifieth this poſition, for by his vnthriftieneſſe, hee is the deuourer of time it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>Another miſchiefe, which gaming doth produce, is an encreaſing of a greedy deſire, in ſuch a gameſter, not to recreate and to refreſh, but to tire &amp; wearie out himſelfe,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:2460:60"/>with the continuall vſe of that vaine exerciſe and ſport, euery minute of time, ſo being ſpent, encreaſing in him a greater delight, and a more longing appetite to ſpend more and more time therein, as men diſeaſed with the dropſie, by drinking much, doe augment their deſire to drinke, and to drinke againe.</p>
            <p>Another miſchiefe proceeding from playing at dice, and at cardes, is couetouſneſſe, which animateth a game<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, greedily to deſire that mony which rightfully doth belong vnto another man, not contenting himſelfe with the ſweete enioyment of his owne; and this kinde of couetouſneſſe exceedeth, and is much worſe then briberie, extortion, and vſurie, for theſe three doe offer, or doe giue to him that paieth, ſome kinde of recompence for his monie (either in ſhew or in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance) but he that gaineth another mans coine by play, affordeth him no amendes nor valuable conſideration for the ſame, but rather (in ſome ſort, like to a cunning and to a craftie theefe) he robbeth his friend (by a deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full skill without violence) of his monie, which might ſupplie his wants, and do both himſelfe and others good.</p>
            <p>The next miſchiefe which is begotten by gaming and playing at cardes, and at dice, is diſcontentment and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quietneſſe of minde, for he who looſeth his monie, forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with grudgeth at, and condemneth his vnaduiſed folly, adiudging himſelfe to be worſe then a foole, becauſe he might haue kept his monie if hee had beene wiſe. And from this difcontentment, and from this diſquietneſſe of minde, ariſeth want of ſleepe, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tempt of honeſt mirth or careleſneſſe to conuerſe with honeſt companie, a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholie diſpoſition which hatcheth, and foſtereth bad conceits and many more inconueniences, beſides which
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:2460:61"/>my ſelfe (not being ſuch a gameſter) cannot (for want of euill experience) repeate and name.</p>
            <p>The next miſchiefe which ſpringeth from gaming, is a ſullen and a ſecret murmuring, which he that looſeth doth inwardly conceaue againſt his cogameſter (yea though he be his welwilling &amp; his familiar frend) weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning thereby his loue towards him, and ſcarſly reputing him to be ſuch a one as he is indeede. Becauſe in gai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning from him his monie, he leaueth him (ſometimes) penileſſe, and ſubiect vnto many wants, which (intruth) he ſhould not do.</p>
            <p>Againe, euill fortune in gaming, maketh moſt men (vſing it) to be impatient, yea (in many men) it breedeth a kind of frenzie and madneſſe, which tranſporteth them into a blaſphemous kinde of ſwearing, whereby the cares of good-men are diſpleaſed, and Gods hands are ſtretched forth to puniſh and to correct (with great ſeueritie) ſuch as (ſo groſſely doe offend.
<note place="margin">A Rule.</note> Therefore among wiſemen, this poſition (as amaxime or a principle, not to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted of) doth firmely hold, that in prouiding of trifling things, tending to our conuenient repoſe, and honeſt recreation, the charge in prouiding of them, muſt be ſmall and trifling, and anſwerable in due proportion to thoſe merriments and ſports. Seeing then that al play and gaming (if euer it be vſed) ought to be practiſed as a trif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſport, for none other end, but onely to recreate our defatigated and wearied mindes, we ought (if we will be accompted wiſe) ſo to proportion the monie for which we plaie, that in winning or in looſing we be recreated, not grieuing others with our too much gaine, nor vexing our ſelues, by reaſon of our pinching loſſe.</p>
            <p>Neither muſt we ſhew our ſelues weake and vnwiſe, if
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:2460:61"/>aduerſe fortune in gaming doe tempt vs vnto anger, by blaming and reprouing the dice, or cardes, and threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to caſt them into the fire, as if they knew in what ſort we were wronged, for if we will repute and accompt him to be ouer angrie, who looking in a true iudging glaſſe, with a confidence &amp; an aſſured hope to ſee there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a faire viſage of his owne, and perceiuing it to be fowle or euill fauored, will therefore breake the glaſſe, imputing it to be the author and the occaſion of his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formitie or fowleneſſe, when as (indeede) the blemiſh is in his face it ſelfe, then muſt wee needes thinke him to want a great meaſure of true diſcretion, who (if at play he looſe his monie) will condemne the dice or cardes, and threaten their ruine, whenas (indeede) the dammage which he receiueth is onely occaſioned by his owne fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and not in them.</p>
            <p>Seeing then that ſo many inconueniences,
<note place="margin">Rules for Playing.</note> and ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny miſchiefes doe follow this kinde of play at cardes, and at dice (<hi>My ſonne</hi>) if you vſe it at all, then vſe it but for a ſhort time, and very ſildome, and for little monie, onely to recreate your wearied ſpirits, or for honeſt companie ſake, without a greedie deſire to gaine by it. But for your better and more gentlemanlike ſporting and recreatoin, I will (vpon mine owne experience) commend vnto you (aboue other exerciſes) dauncing and vauting,
<note place="margin">Dauncing. Vauting.</note> the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer of them putting in to practiſe, the more ſoft and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, but the latter more ſtrong and manlike nimbleneſſe, and agilitie of bodie, &amp; both of them ſo enliuening both limmes and ſpirit, that they doe make them the more apt and able in caſes aſwell of pleaſure as of neceſſitie, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme what ſhall be expedient and conuenient, the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer of thoſe two, beſt beſeemeth the hall or the dining
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:2460:62"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:2460:62"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:2460:63"/>roome, to paſſe the time for honeſt recreation ſake, and for modeſt mirth to the good contentment of ſuch as are actors or beholders thereof, but oftentimes may vawting ſtand you in better ſteede abroade, when your life may be in perill or in danger.</p>
            <p>I like not that dauncing which maketh a man either laſciuious or proude,
<note place="margin">A rule for Dauncing.</note> for ſuch an abuſefull vſe thereof ſerueth as a baude to an haughtie or to a wanton minde, neither is the praiſeable exerciſe of vawting to bee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended,
<note place="margin">A rule for Vauting.</note> if the actor do either immoderately affect praiſe or if he doe thereby hunt baſely after profit and filthie gaine,
<note place="margin">Rules for both.</note> but both thoſe two, I meane dauncing and vaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, muſt propoſe for thoſe chiefeſt ends, comelineſſe without Pride; pleaſure without wantonneſſe; recreation without ſelfe-liking; ſocietie without ribaldry; exerciſe without wearineſſe; and contentedneſſe, without coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe.
<note place="margin">Another rule.</note> And if (<hi>My ſonne</hi>) you liſt for your recreation, and for your exerciſe to intertaine theſe two delightfull and pleaſing qualities, I doe aduiſe and counſell you, that in the practiſe of them you hold a diſcreete moderation, and a meane, leaſt that too much violence in the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of them, doe make thoſe ſports irkeſome, which ſhould delight you; and diſable your bodie (by the weari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of your limmes, and by the ſtifneſſe of your ioints) to act them as you ſhould. Thus leauing you to theſe as vnto your beſt and cheefeſt bodily exerciſes (if they bee with ſobrietie,
<note place="margin">Speech. Tonge.</note> and with a moderation vſed.) you ſhall next vnderſtand, that it behooueth you exceeding much principally to regard and obſerue, that your ſpeech and communication be alwaies ſuch, as that the virtues of your inward parts, and of your outward actions may be approued and confirmed thereby, and that no diſcouerie
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:2460:63"/>at all, be made of many follies, by the looſe and lauiſh tat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of your tongue.</p>
            <p>For your tongue is the meſſenger of your minde, and of the aboundance of your heart your mouth ſpeaketh, whether it be good or bad, a good man is better knowne by his talke, then good wine is by the Iuy-buſh. The tongue of a Marchant ſpeaketh of his commodities, of his aduentures, and of his loſſe, or of his gaine.</p>
            <p>The tongue of the Phiſition, ſpeaketh of the natures of herbes, of plants, of ſtones, and of other creatures, and of the diſeaſes, the griefes the recoueries, relapſes, and deaths of his cheefeſt patients. The tongue of the lawyer maketh mention of his caſes, his <hi>Quaeres,</hi> his demurres, his iſſues ioyned, his iudgements, and of his clients.</p>
            <p>The tongue of a Souldiour, boaſteth of his skarres of his woundes, of his maimings, and of ſuch ſtrong encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters as he hath had, and as the tongue of theſe, and of ſuch like doe exerciſe themſelues in making mention of things which are moſt incident and proper to their honeſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions, arts, and ſciences.</p>
            <p>So the tongue of an avaritious &amp; of a couetous man is neuer wearied whilſt it ſingeth deſcant vpon his monie. The tongue of a prodigall man is bragging of his riotous exceſſe, and of his ouermuch lauiſhneſſe and ſpending.</p>
            <p>The tongue of an amorous wanton vainely ſpeaketh of his minions and of his drabs, and finally euery mans tongue beateth vpon the anuill of his owne paſſions. And forgeth ſuch formes and ſuch ſhapes as are contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in his owne braine.</p>
            <p>The tongue is one of the leaſt members in the bodie, yet if ſhe bee not reſtrained and gouerned by wiſedome and by good diſcretion, ſhe will make a man captiue and ſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſh
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:2460:64"/>to the greateſt woe, and like as the helme of a ſhip being turned the wrong way, carrieth her quite a way, and daſheth her ribs againſt the rockes, ſo the tongue of a man (if it ſpeake euill things) tranſporteth the whole man vnto many miſchiefes, and bringeth him quickly vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ruine and deſtruction.</p>
            <p>Therefore to the end that your ſpeech, your talke, your communication, may be graue, and ſauour of wiſedome and of diſcretion, you muſt (in ſpeaking) be carefull and well aduiſed to obſerue theſe rules and inſtructions which doe follow.</p>
            <p>Firſt that your ſpeech be not laſciuious,
<note place="margin">Rules for ſpeaking well.</note> light and wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, for euill words corrupt good manners, and looſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of life is firſt conceaued in the heart, next vttered by the tongue, and laſt of all put in practiſe by the reſt of the members of the bodie. A man by the wanton diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes of his tongue may doe more miſchiefe then he who is (indeede) lewd and diſhoneſt.</p>
            <p>For when a man doth actually tranſgreſſe againſt cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitie and honeſtie, hehath few or no witneſſes of his ſinne but he that talketh looſely and with a wanton tongue, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſeth no companie, but maketh all ſuch as are preſent partakers of the iniquitie, and of the beaſtly defilements of his polluted tongue.</p>
            <p>As a Traitor conſpireth the ouerthrow &amp; the deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his Lord and ſoueraigne, ſo a wanton and a laſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uious tongue ſubuerteth and vndermineth the fame, the honor, and the reputation of his maiſter. Your talke therefore muſt be ſober, modeſt and cleanely, ſeaſoned with wiſedome, and with temperance, if you doe effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally deſire to be, and to be deemed and reputed for an honeſt man.</p>
            <pb n="99" facs="tcp:2460:64"/>
            <p>Secondly, in your talke you muſt be moderate and ſparing, not babling to others all that you heare or know, in which rule nature her ſelfe ſeemeth to inſtruct you, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſhe hath giuen you two eares, and two eyes, and but one mouth, ſignifying thereby, that you ought not to ſpeake all that you doe heare and ſee.</p>
            <p>For as a foole is diſcouered by his ouermuch laughter, ſo an vnwiſe man is reuealed by the ouerflowing of his tongue, the tongue of a common ſpeaker oftentimes breedeth much offence. <hi>Nam minùs nocet pedum, quàm Lin quae lapſus:</hi> By the ſliding and ſlipping of your foote, you receiue not ſo much harme, as you doe by the lauiſhnes of your buſie and vnmaſtered tongue.</p>
            <p>The volubilitie of a ſmooth tongue is nothing profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, nor pleaſing if it bee not circumſcribed within the boundes, and within the limits of temperance and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration.</p>
            <p>A wiſe man delighteth not in ſpeech which is exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into a prolixe and needleſſe length, compriſing lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle matter and little ſubſtance.</p>
            <p>A roling and a tumbling ſtone neuer gathereth any moſſe, neither doth a tatling tongue purchaſe reputation or merit deſerued praiſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In Multiloquio non deeſt peccatum,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pro.</hi> 10.19. <hi>Pro.</hi> 15 2.</note> many wordes (ſaith Salomon) want not iniquitie, the tongue of the wiſe (ſaith he) vſeth knowledge aright, but the mouthes of fooles doe babble out fooliſhneſſe.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pro.</hi> 6.17.</note> A lauiſh and a bufie tongue is one of the ſixe thinges which God hateth,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eccles.</hi> 5.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> as a dreame commeth by the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of buſineſſe, ſo the voice of a foole is in the multitude of wordes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The tongue of an idle babler is like vnto a ſickmans pulſe, which alwaies beateth, but euer out of order, it is
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:2460:65"/>alſo like vnto the braying of an Aſſe, which maketh an imperfect ſound without knowledge or inſtruction.</p>
            <p>The third thing which in ſpeaking muſt be obſerued, is, that you be well aduiſed before you ſpeake. For often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times many mens tongues doe ouer-runne and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrippe their wits. <hi>Bias</hi> the philoſopher held it for an in fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible rule of reaſon, that ſpeaking raſhly without preme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation or aduiſe was a branch of madneſſe. And <hi>Xe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nophon</hi> ſaid, that it had repented him oftentimes that hee had ſpoken, but was neuer ſorrie for his ſilence, you <hi>muſt make a dore,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eccles.</hi> 18.25.</note> and a barre, and a ſure bridle for your mouth.</hi> And if it bee a good point of diſcretion to looke before we leape,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Not Hiſt. Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bro.</hi> 11.</note> it is an argument of greater wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome for you to be well aduiſed before you ſpeake.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pliny</hi> noteth well, that it is long ere thoſe children can goe, that can ſpeakk quickly, whereupon <hi>Berchorius</hi> doth well inferre, that ſuch as are haſtie and vnaduiſed in their ſpeaking,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>fol.</hi> 41.</note> are ſlow in doing and performing of any good, you muſt therefore obſerue this counſell in your aduiſed ſpeech and ſpeakings, that the ſame be fitting to the time, to the place, to the perſon, and to the matter.</p>
            <p>For if your ſpeech be not applied and fitted vnto thoſe foure neceſſarie, and incidentall circumſtances, it will ſoone diſcouer your weakneſſe and your folly; to know when to ſpeake, and when to be ſilent is great wiſedome, and if you deſire to liue a peaceable and a quiet life, you muſt ſee much &amp; heare much, but not ſpeake much, for lit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tle ſaid is ſoone amended, &amp; words vainely ſpoken can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be recalled &amp; vnſaid, it is an abſurd folly for a man to ſpeake fooliſhly, and then by way of ſorrow and of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance to excuſe it with a <hi>Non putaram,</hi> or had I wiſt.</p>
            <p>The fourth thing which in ſpeaking muſt bee
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:2460:65"/>regarded, is that you ſlander not another with your tongue, for the tongue of a ſlanderer is ſharper then a ſword, and <hi>Mantuan</hi> ſaieth, that it is,
<note place="margin">Mantuan.</note> 
               <hi>Res male tuta vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ros lingua irritare proterua,</hi> it is a wicked and an vngodly thing to prouoke men to wrath with a ſlanderous tongue for though the tongue (in her ſelfe) haue not any bones, yet is it able to breake more then bones.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Eccleſiaſticus</hi> you may reade, that <hi>euill tongues haue diſquieted many, troden downe great Citties,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>cap.</hi> 23.</note> ouerthrowne the houſes of great men, brought downe the ſtrength of the people, and haue beene the decay of mightie Nations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith, that <hi>hee who inuenteth ſlanders,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pro.</hi> 10. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 15.</note> is a foole, and the prophet Dauid, that ſuch as are ſlanderers ſhall not dwell in the tabernacle of the Lord:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſ</hi> 101.</note> and deſtruction is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced againſt him that priuily ſlandereth his neighbour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What is deerer to a man then his fame, his honeſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, and his good name, nothing beſides his ſoule,
<note place="margin">Fame.</note> for many me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue confidently beene of this opinion, that it is better to die with honor, and in a good report, then to enioy their liues with ignominy, and with ſhame.</p>
            <p>For he who dieth and leaueth behind him an honeſt and a good report,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioſeph. de An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiqu. Iud.</hi> 156.</note> in regard of his manifold and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable virtues, leaueth an honorable poſterity to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue his memoriall, and his name vnto many ages that ſhall ſucceede. <hi>A good name is better then a good omtment,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eccles.</hi> 3. <hi>Pro.</hi> 22 1.</note> and it is to be choſen before great riches.</hi> There is no greater theft then to rob a man of his good fame.</p>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>Qua ſemel amiſſa, poſtea nullus erit.</l>
                  <l>Which being loſt by fooliſh ſlandrous meane,</l>
                  <l>Flies quite away, and comes not back againe.</l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <p>Finally as one mad-dog, biting another dog, maketh him that is bitten mad too. So a ſlanderer (in his mad fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:2460:66"/>skandalizing another mans name and good report, maketh him angry, diſcontented and furious, and is the occaſion of great diſcord, and vnquietnes among men.</p>
            <p>Fiftly in ſpeaking, you muſt be warie that you be no tale-bearer, for ſuch tatlers and ſuch buſie-bodies doe blow and kindle the coles of ſtrife,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 18.8.</note> of variance and of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſention among good neighbours, and louing frends. <hi>The wordes of a tale-bearer are as flattering, they goe downe into the bowels of the belly</hi> (that is they doe goe deepe, or doe pierce vnto the quick, and like as a little flaw kindleth ſuch a fire as a great winde cannot put out, ſo a fooliſh tale-bearer, by his folly raiſeth many troubles which are not againe pacified, and reconciled by the mediation and helpe of many frends. Let vs therefore wiſely conſider, that as fire is quenched when the wood faileth, ſo with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a tale-bearer ſtrife ceaſeth, and peace continueth in a louely conſort, and harmony among frends.</p>
            <p>The ſixt obſeruation in ſpeaking is, that in your talke you do auoid fooliſh ieſting &amp; peeuiſh ſcoffing at other men:
<note place="margin">Ieſting.</note> yet ieſting amongſt merry frends and frendly company is not vtterly to be diſliked or forbidden, nay rather it is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable and praiſeworthie, ſo that it be prettie &amp; witty, not bitter, not ſcorning, nor wounding the reputation &amp; credit of him vpon whom your ieſts ſhall be beſtowed, &amp; ſo that they be ſparingly vſed (as ſauce vnto good fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and grauitie) <hi>But a ſcorner is an abomination vnto men, yea iudgements are prepared for ſuch a one,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pro.</hi> 24.9. <hi>Pro.</hi> 19.29. <hi>Pro.</hi> 14.6. <hi>Pro.</hi> 22.10.</note> he ſeeketh wiſedom and findes it not,</hi> he is therefore to be caſt out, that ſtrife and contention and reproach may haue an end.</p>
            <p>The ſeuenth rule in ſpeaking is, that you ſpeake the tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth from your hart, for <hi>lying lips are an abhomination to the
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:2460:66"/>Lord, but they that deale truely are his delight.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pro.</hi> 12.22. <hi>Pro.</hi> 19.6. <hi>v.</hi> 9 22. <hi>Pro.</hi> 23.23.</note> He that ſpeaketh lies ſhal not eſcape, but ſhall periſh, &amp; a poore man is better then a rich lier.</hi> Therfore you muſt buy truth, &amp; hauing bought her, you muſt not ſell her againe, no not for any gaine.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 12.19.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The lips of truth ſhall bee ſtable for euer, but a lying tongue varyeth incontinently:</hi> he who vſeth to lie, is ſeldome or neuer credited and beleeued, no, though ſometimes he ſpeake truely, but he who ſpeaketh the trueth winneth much credit.
<note place="margin">Truth.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Truth is fairer and more amiable then <hi>Helena</hi> of Greece was, ſhe cannot be too dearely bought, if ſhe be bought for any price.</p>
            <p>She is beautifull within, and her outward apparell is made of needleworke, ſhe is without ſpot or blemiſh, and her fame reacheth vnto the cloudes, without her there can be no frendſhip among priuate men, nor any ciuill commerce among neighbours, no leagues among princes, nor any ſupport of a kingdome or common wealth.</p>
            <p>She is victorious in al her warres, and in times of peace ſhe ruleth and raigneth as an imperious Queene that is ſuſtained and held vp with proſperitie and with honor.</p>
            <p>Though ſhe haue many enemies, yet ſhe careth not for their malice, nor for their diſpleaſure, but ſhe breaketh their arrowes and their darts in ſunder, ſo that they are vnable to doe her any harme.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Opprimi poteſt, non deprimi,</l>
               <l>Poteſt periclitari, non perire,</l>
               <l>Impugnari poteſt, ſed non expugnari veritas.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Truth may be oppreſſed, but ſhe cannot be quite preſſed downe, ſhe may be indangered, but ſhe cannot periſh, and ſhe may be aſſaulted, but ſhe can neuer be ſurprized.</p>
            <pb n="104" facs="tcp:2460:67"/>
            <p>She is not made ſplendent by craſtie and by cunning ſpeaking, but by ſinceritie and by plainenes ſhe is made noble, ſhe animateth a man to be confident as a Lyon in all dangers and misfotunes, and ſhe departeth not from him, when all his other frends doe forſake and leaue him, ſhe diſperſeth the thicke cloudes of ſubtill plots and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſes, and ſhe prepareth the way to a right iudgement.</p>
            <p>You muſt (therefore) ſeeke her without ceaſing, or wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſſe, vntill you haue found her, and hauing found her, you muſt dwell with her, for her lips drop ſweetnes, and her inſtructions doe teach wiſedome.</p>
            <p>Many other things (<hi>My ſonne</hi>) as well as theſe muſt be obſerued in ſpeaking, which I will onely touch and point at, without any amplification, or diſcourſing vpon them, leaſt that in framing of a tedious deſcription or method for ſpeaking well, I my ſelfe may be iuſtly taxed for ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ill, by ſpeaking ouermuch.</p>
            <p>Briefly therefore I doe exhort you, that in ſpeaking you doe not cauill nor contend eagerly about the truth, but modeſtly with temper and with ſubſtance, leaſt you chance to looſe her, whilſt vainely you diſpute and ſtriue about her.</p>
            <p>Next that you argue not, nor do maintaine talke &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference againſt the truth, but in matters which are indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent, and onely for diſputations ſake, and the better to make triall of the truth, wherein I wiſh you not to be vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olent, nor ouer long.</p>
            <p>Next that you put not your familiar, or your common friend to an open foile, to his reproach or diſgrace in the preſence of other hearers, when in diſputing you may (perhaps) haue the vpper hand.</p>
            <p>Next that in your communication with other men you
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:2460:67"/>be not peremptorie, nor idlie wedded to your owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits and will, thinking your owne opinion to be more-found, and profound then other mens.</p>
            <p>Next that you make not any anſwere before you haue heard and conſidered of the propoſition, obiection or queſtion, for he that doth otherwiſe, committeth folly, and publiſheth his owne ſhame.</p>
            <p>Next that in caſes materiall &amp; of ſubſtance, you ſpeake as you thinke, without pride, enuie, equiuocation, men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall reſeruation, diſſimulation, lying or ſuch like.</p>
            <p>Next that you ſpeake not any euil of ſuch as are abſent, nor of the dead, but rather wiſely make choiſe, that you be ſilent, if you cannot truely vtter any good of them.</p>
            <p>Next that you be not ſilent, where and when your ſpeaking may either profit or pleaſure another man, and likewiſe that you ſpeake not at all, when by ſpeaking you may doe harme.</p>
            <p>Next that you ſpeake not ſtifly, or too earneſtly in matters either triſling or abſurd.</p>
            <p>Next that in your ſpeaking, you doe neither diſcouer your owne, nor your friends counſell, which may turne either him or your ſelfe to loſſe, reproofe or ſhame.</p>
            <p>Next that you ſpeake little or nothing at all, in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of fooles, captious perſons, tale bearers, and of ſuch as vſe to ſlander.</p>
            <p>Next that your ſpeech be not interrupted with anger, for <hi>anger peruerteth the minde,</hi> and oftentimes diſableth the ſpeaker to finiſh that which he hath well begunne.</p>
            <p>And laſt of all, that you reproue not in another man, ſuch defects, faults or offences, as your ſelfe are guiltie of, <hi>Nam turpe eſt Doctori, cum culpa redarguit ipſum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe rules and theſe directions (<hi>My ſonne</hi>) if you doe
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:2460:68"/>carefully obſerue in ſpeaking, your ſpeech and your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication wil be ſeaſoned with wiſedome and with diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion, and by meanes thereof you ſhall purchaſe grace and fauor, and reputation, with thoſe, vnto whom, or with whom you ſpeake, and now hauing thus informed you, touching the ordering, and well diſpoſing of your ſpeech and talke, it will be as neceſſarie, that you be alſo inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and directed in the manner of your proceedings, in ſuch affaires, and buſines as you take in hand, wherein you muſt principally, and aboue others, obſerue theſe rules.</p>
            <p>Firſt,
<note place="margin">Actions.</note> that you doe nothing raſhly: <hi>Nam ſat citó, ſi ſat bene,</hi> things are ſoone enough done, if they bee well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough done.</p>
            <p>Secondly,
<note place="margin">Deliberation.</note> that with your leaſure in doing of any thing, you do alſo ſoundly ponder, and deliberate of that which you haue to doe, ſo ſhall you not neede to repent what you haue done.
<note place="margin">Aduiſe, Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, Delibera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, Preme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And laſt of all, that in doing you take the aduiſe, and counſell of other men, to ſupply your owne defects, or to ſtrengthen your owne iudgement, <hi>Plus enim vident oculi, quam oculus,</hi> and make not more haſt then good ſpeede, for want of ſuch aduice: <hi>Canis enim feſtinans caecos parit Catulos,</hi> haſt makes waſte.</p>
            <p>It is not ſomuch the part of a wiſe-man to put in prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize and execution,
<note place="margin">Raſhneſſe.</note> thoſe things which hee ſeeth before his eyes, as it is firſt to foreſee, and then to deliberate and conſider whether the end of his actions and imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments be good or euill.</p>
            <p>He is but a fooliſh man, who will not firſt thinke how to come out of the riuer againe before hee enter into it, miſchiefes and dangers are preuented with more facility, then they are ſhaken off, when they are hapned. Raſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginnings
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:2460:68"/>haue (for the moſt part) vnfortunate ends: to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fruit before it be ripe, argueth the want both of skill and of diſcretion.</p>
            <p>In phiſicke nothing is more dangerous then the admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtring of ſuddaine and of haſtie medicines. A wiſe mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riner will not raſhly lanch into the deepe, but hee will firſt be perſwaded of a ſucceſſefull winde. For like as a prodigall man begins to ſpare too late, after he hath vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thriftily diued into the bottom of his exhauſted &amp; peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les purſe, ſo he that hath ouer haſtily vndertaken a buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, which (for want of more aduiſe and good delibera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) ſorteth not to a faire, and to an expected end, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penteth too too late, and cannot (at his owne pleaſure, and when himſelfe is diſpoſed) repaire and amend that which fooliſhly and improuidently he hath done amiſſe.</p>
            <p>A wiſe man (in all his negotiations and affaires) muſt be buſied vpon premeditation &amp; good aduiſe, for it skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth not whether he doe many things or no, if he doe a few things ſubſtantially and well. One taske wil be ſoone enough performed, if with mature aduiſe, and ſound de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberation it be ended.</p>
            <p>Wee doe vſe to commend that raine, which (falling moderately) waſteth not nor waſheth quite away, by too much violence, where it ſhould onely mollifie and make fruitfull, by ſoft and by gentle dropping.</p>
            <p>A wiſe man before he goeth out of his houſe know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth what he intendeth to doe, when hee is abroade, and being returned home, he conſidereth of that which hee hath done.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Agrippa</hi> counſelled the <hi>Iewes</hi> that they ſhould not obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately reſiſt the rage &amp; furie of the <hi>Romans,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioſephus:</note> telling them that where deliberation was, there was alſo ſafetie, and
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:2460:69"/>things would come to an happie end.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Scipio Affricanus</hi> wan <hi>Carthage,</hi> more by delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and lingring delaies, then by violence, or with haſt.</p>
            <p>Now therefore (<hi>My ſonne</hi>) if your owne diſcretion cannot manage a buſineſſe of more then ordinarie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent and moment.
<note place="margin">Aduiſe.</note> Then vſe the aduiſe of other men, many eyes doe ſee more then one eye can, and often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times we doe perceiue, that thoſe things which time de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nieth to afford, are by counſell obtained to our comfort and good content.</p>
            <p>Aduiſe and counſell helpeth the defects and the impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diments of nature,
<note place="margin">Counſell.</note> it is the part of a wiſe man, firſt to har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken vnto, and then to put in practiſe the aduiſe and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of other men.</p>
            <p>For it is a rare thing for a man, by his owne onely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuours to waxe wiſe, nay without inſtruction and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, a man cannot informe himſelfe of thoſe things which are difficult and hard.</p>
            <p>Hence it was that <hi>Xenophon</hi> the Philoſopher ſaid, that a wife man muſt haue many eares, and many eyes, for that he ought to heare and to ſee more with the eyes and with the eares of other men, then with his owne.</p>
            <p>By counſell, men, houſes, citties, prouinces, countries, kingdomes, and empires are eſtabliſhed, ſuſtained and preſerued.</p>
            <p>To conclude this matter, let nothing bee done or at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted raſhly, but by good deliberation with your ſelfe, or with the aduiſe &amp; counſell of other men (if your owne experience and skill doe not enable you of your ſelfe to performe them, wiſely as you ought.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>My ſonne,</hi> concerning your apparell, and your diet, I
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:2460:69"/>will ſay nothing,
<note place="margin">Apparell. Diet.</note> hoping that if you doe with diligent obſeruation, oftentimes peruſe this ſmal diſcourſe, which in my deereſt loue towards you I haue compoſed, you wil be ſufficiently inſtructed to be temperate in them both, and the rather becauſe pride and g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uttonie are the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heires of the Deuill, whoſe poſſeſſion and inheritance is hell.</p>
            <p>And as for the chooſing and practizing of your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon exerciſes,
<note place="margin">Exerciſes.</note> and of ſuch other qualities as are moſt fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting for you to entertaine, I will referre you to the deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berate reading and meditating vpon that excellent,
<note place="margin">Balthaſar. Caſtilion, or the Courtier.</note> and euer moſt praiſe-worthie worke of <hi>Balthazer Caſtilion,</hi> who by his choiſe precepts, hath caſt young gentlemen into a fairer moulde then their fathers did.</p>
            <p>And now ſeeing that this my diſcourſe hath accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed her intended viage, and hath finiſhed her race and iourney, I doe moſt humbly pray and beſeech my moſt gracious and euerliuing God, ſo to bleſſe and proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per you (<hi>My ſonne</hi>) that by traueling in theſe my labors, you may the better, and the more happily (in this life) attain to the period and height of vertue, and of true god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, which will make you moſt bleſſed, and moſt hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie in the life to come, which God grant, Amen.</p>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Qualis vita, Finis ita.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:2460:70"/>
            <head>The Table.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Actions.</hi> 106</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Aduerſitie.</hi> 83</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Aduiſe.</hi> 106. 108</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Affabilitie.</hi> 79</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Affliction.</hi> 83</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Anger.</hi> 81</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Apparell.</hi> 109</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Banqueting.</hi> 64</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Boaſting.</hi> 77</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Card-play.</hi> 92</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Clemencie.</hi> 79</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Company.</hi> 37</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Conſcience.</hi> 11</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Contentment.</hi> 85</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Counſell.</hi> 108</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Couetouſneſſe.</hi> 88</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Curteſie.</hi> 79</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Dauncing.</hi> 95</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Deliberation.</hi> 106</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Dice-play.</hi> 92</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Diſſimulation.</hi> 47</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Drunkenneſſe.</hi> 68</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Dyet.</hi> 109</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Exceſſe.</hi> 94</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Exerciſe.</hi> 109</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Fame.</hi> 101</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Feaſting.</hi> 64</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Flattery.</hi> 45</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Frendſhip.</hi> 42</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Frendſhips. Rules.</hi> 44</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Gaming.</hi> 92</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Gentleneſſe.</hi> 79</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>God feared.</hi> 4</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>God ſerued.</hi> 1</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>God knoweth al things.</hi> 58</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>God ſeeth al things.</hi> 59</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>God heareth al things.</hi> 59</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Honeſtie.</hi> 52</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Humanitie.</hi> 79</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Humilitie.</hi> 71. 77</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Idleneſſe.</hi> 60</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Idolatrie.</hi> 14</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ieſting.</hi> 102</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ignorance.</hi> 29</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Learning.</hi> 24. 29</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Leaſure.</hi> 108</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Liberalitie.</hi> 85</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Liberalities Rules. ibid</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Nicenes.</hi> 64</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Patience.</hi> 81</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Play.</hi> 92</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Premeditation.</hi> 106</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:2460:70"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Pride.</hi> 73</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Prodigalitie.</hi> 88</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Raſhneſſe.</hi> 106</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Religion.</hi> 12. 15</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Reputation.</hi> 101</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Secreſie.</hi> 51</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Selfe-loue.</hi> 77</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Speech.</hi> 96</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Speech. Rules.</hi> 98</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Studying.</hi> 29</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sinne.</hi> 6</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Temperance.</hi> 68</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Tongue.</hi> 96</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Truth.</hi> 103</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Time.</hi> 92</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Vawting.</hi> 95</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Virtue.</hi> 17</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Whoredome.</hi> 52</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Wiſedome.</hi> 24. 33</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>Pag 13. l. 19. for ſinner read ſunne. p. 20. l. 20. for the reſidence, her reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence p. 24. l. 16. and by her harnes bearers, as by &amp;c. p. 34. l. 27. concealeth, conceiueth, p. 39. l. 14. Treſihan Treſilian. p. 56. l. 14. and, all p. 62. l. 9. multa. nulla p. 96. l. 13. thoſe chiefeſt ends, their chiefeſt &amp;c. p. 100. putaram, puta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:2460:71"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2460:71" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
